[{"question":"<p>A second alkanol can be oxidized to give an<\/p>","options":["alkanone","alkyne","alkanoic acid","alkanal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following will give a precipitate with an aqueous solution of copper (I) chloride?<\/p>","options":["But-2-ene","But-1-ene","But-2-yne","But-1-yne"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The IUPAC name for CH\\(_3\\)CH\\(_2\\)COOCH\\(_2\\)CH\\(_3\\) is<\/p>","options":["methylpropanoate","ethylethanoate","ethylpropanoate","methylethanoate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A certain hydrocarbon on complete combustion at s.t.p produced 89.6dm\\(^3\\) of CO\\(_2\\) and 54g of water. The hydrocarbon should be<\/p>","options":["C\\(_6\\)H\\(_6\\)","C\\(_4\\)H\\(_{10}\\)","C\\(_5\\)H\\(_{10}\\)","C\\(_4\\)H\\(_6\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>2-methylprop-1-ene is an isomer of<\/p>","options":["3-methyl but-1-ene","2-methyl but-1-ene","but-2-ene","pent-2-ene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Hydrocarbons which will react with Tollen&#39;s reagent conform to the general formula<\/p>","options":["C\\(_n\\)H\\(_{2n}\\)","C\\(_n\\)H\\(_{2n + 2}\\)","C\\(_n\\)H\\(_{2n - 2}\\)","C\\(_n\\)H\\(_{2n + 1}\\)OH"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The IUPAC name of the compound CF\\(_3\\)CHBrCl is<\/p>","options":["2-chloro-2-bromo-1,1,1-trifluoroethane","2-bromo-2-chloro-1,1,1-trifluoroethane","1-bromo-1-chloro-2,2,2-trifluoroethane","1,1,1-trifluoro-2-bromo-2-chloroethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A synthetic rubber is obtained from the polymerization of<\/p>","options":["neoprene","isoprene","butandiene","propylene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Burning magnesium ribbon in air removes which of the following<br \/>\r\n(i) oxygen (ii) nitrogen (iii) argon and (iv) carbon(iv)oxide?<\/p>","options":["i and iv only","i, ii, iii and iv only","i only","i and ii only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is the best starting material for the preparation of oxygen? Heating of trioxonitrate (v) with<\/p>","options":["Pb","Zn","Ca","Na"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following metals is the most essential in the regulation of blood volume, blood pressure and osmotic equilibrium?<\/p>","options":["Zinc","Manganese","Sodium","Iron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following alkaline metals react more quickly spontaneously with water?<\/p>","options":["Calcium","Beryllium","Magnesium","Strontium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>When chlorine water is exposed to bright sunlight, the following products are formed<\/p>","options":["HCl\\(_{(aq)}\\) and Cl\\(_2\\)","HOCl\\(_{(aq)}\\) and Cl\\(_2\\)","HCl\\(_{(aq)}\\) and O\\(_2\\)","HOCl\\(_{(aq)}\\) and O\\(_2\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which process(es) is\/are involved in the turning of starch iodide paper blue-black by chlorine gas?<\/p>","options":["chlorine attacks the starch to give the blue-black color","chlorine attacks the iodide ion to give the blue-black color","chlorine oxidizes the iodide ion to produce iodine which attacks the starch to give the blue-black color","iodine attacks the starch to give the blue-black color"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is a set of neutral oxides?<\/p>","options":["N\\(_2\\)O, H\\(_2\\)O, CO","N\\(_2\\)O, SO\\(_2\\), CO","N\\(_2\\)O, Na\\(_2\\)O, ZnO","N\\(_2\\)O, SO\\(_3\\), NO"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>SO\\(_3\\) is not directly dissolved in water in the industrial preparation of H\\(_2\\)SO\\(_4\\) by the contact process because<\/p>","options":["SO\\(_3\\) is an acidic gas","Acid is usually added to water and not water to acid","The reaction between SO\\(_3\\) and water is violently exothermic","SO\\(_3\\) does not dissolve readily in water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following statements does not show Rutherford&#39;s account of Nuclear Theory? An atom contains a region<\/p>","options":["which contains protons and neutrons","which is positively charged","which is massive and can cause deflection of a few projectiles","which is very large and in which close to 98% of projectiles pass undeflected"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Elements X and Y have electronic configurations 1s\\(^2\\)2s\\(^2\\)2p\\(^4\\) and 1s\\(^2\\)2s\\(^2\\)2p\\(^6\\)3s\\(^2\\)3p\\(^1\\) respectively. When they combine, the formula of the compound formed is<\/p>","options":["XY","X\\(_2\\)Y","Y\\(_2\\)X\\(_3\\)","X\\(_2\\)Y\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>By what amount must the temperature of 200cm\\(^3\\) of Nitrogen at 27&deg;C be increased to double the pressure if the final volume is 150cm\\(^3\\) (Assume ideality)<\/p>","options":["150\u00b0C","177\u00b0C","75\u00b0C","120\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The combustion of carbon(ii)oxide in oxygen can be represented by equation.<br \/>\r\n2CO + O\\(_2\\) &rarr; 2CO\\(_2\\)<br \/>\r\nCalculate the volume of the resulting mixture at the end of the reaction if 50cm\\(_3\\) of carbon(ii)oxide was exploded in 100cm\\(_3\\) of oxygen<\/p>","options":["75cm\\(^3\\)","125cm\\(^3\\)","100cm\\(^3\\)","50cm\\(^3\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>When ammonia and hydrogen ion bond together to form ammonium ion, the bond formed is called<\/p>","options":["electrovalent bond","co-ordinate bond","ionic bond","covalent bond"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following represents the kind of bonding present in ammonium chloride?<\/p>","options":["ionic only","covalent only","ionic and dative covalent","dative covalent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Consider the reaction<br \/>\r\nA\\(_{(s)}\\) + 2B\\(_{(g)}\\) &rarr; 2C\\(_{(aq)}\\) + D\\(_{(g)}\\)<br \/>\r\nWhat will be the effect of a decrease in pressure on the reaction?<\/p>","options":["the equilibrium will shift","rate of forward reaction will increase","rate of backward reaction will increase","rates of forward and backward reaction are not affected"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>For the general equation of the nature<br \/>\r\nxP + yQ \u21cc mR + nS, the expression for the equilibrium constant is<\/p>","options":["k[P]\\(^x\\)[Q]\\(^y\\)","\\(\\frac{m[R][S]}{x[P]y[Q]}\\)","\\(\\frac{[P]^x[Q]^y}{[R]^m[S]^n}\\)","\\(\\frac{[R]^m[S]^n}{[P]^x[Q]^y}\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following reactions is an oxidation process?<\/p>","options":["2H\\(^+\\) + 2e\\(^-\\) \\(\\to\\) H\\(_2\\)","2O\\(^{2-}\\) + 4e\\(^-\\) \\(\\to\\) O\\(_2\\)","OCl\\(^-\\) + H\\(_2\\)O + 2e\\(^-\\) \\(\\to\\) 2OH\\(^-\\) + Cl\\(^-\\)","Cl + e\\(^-\\) \\(\\to\\) Cl\\(^-\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>If acidified Potassium Dichromate(VI) (K\\(_2\\)Cr\\(_2\\)O\\(_7\\)) acts as oxidizing agent, color changes from<\/p>","options":["yellow to green","orange to green","yellow to red","orange to red"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The heat of formation of ethene, C\\(_2\\)H\\(_4\\) is 50 kJmol\\(^{-1}\\), and that of ethane, C\\(_2\\)H\\(_6\\) is -82kJmol\\(^{-1}\\). Calculate the heat evolved in the process:<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>C\\(_2\\)H\\(_4\\) + H\\(_2\\) \\(\\to\\) C\\(_2\\)H\\(_6\\)<\/p>","options":["-122kJ","-132kJ","-88kJ","-60kJ"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following statements about catalyst is false?<\/p>","options":["biological catalysts are called enzymes","catalyst do not appear in the balanced equation","catalyst reduce the activation energy for a reaction","catalysts do not alter the mechanism of the reaction and never appear in the rate low"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following does not support the fact that air is a mixture?<\/p>","options":["the constituents of air are in a fixed proportion by mass","it cannot be represented with a chemical formula","the constituents of air can be separated by physical by physical means","none of the above"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>What technique is suitable for separating a binary solution of potassium chloride and potassium trioxochlorate (V)?<\/p>","options":["Fractional crystallization","Fractional distillation","Filtration","Evaporation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>At 27&deg;C, 58.5g of sodium chloride is present in 250cm\\(^3\\) of a solution. The solubility of sodium chloride at this temperature is?<br \/>\r\n(molar mass of sodium chloride = 111.0gmol\\(^{-1}\\))<\/p>","options":["2.0 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","0.25 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","1.0 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","0.5 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following properties increases from left to right along the period but decreases down the group in the Periodic Table?<br \/>\r\ni. Atomic Number&nbsp; &nbsp;ii. Ionization energy&nbsp; iii. Metallic character&nbsp; iv. Electron affinity<\/p>","options":["ii and iii only","ii and iv only","iii and iv only","i and ii only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The molecular shape and bond angle of water are respectively<\/p>","options":["linear, 180\u00b0","bent, 109.5\u00b0","tetrahedral, 109.5\u00b0","bent, 105\u00b0"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Na\\(_2\\)CO\\(_3\\) + 2HCl \\(\\to\\) 2NaCl + H\\(_2\\)O + CO\\(_2\\)<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>The indicator most suitable for this reaction should have a pH equal to<\/p>","options":["5","7","3","9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A radioactive nucleus has a half-life of 20 years, starting with 100,000 particles, how many particles will be left exactly at the end of 40 years<\/p>","options":["75,000 particles","35,000 particles","25,000 particles","50,000 particles"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which two gases can be used for the demonstration of the fountain experiment?<\/p>","options":["SO\\(_3\\) and NH\\(_3\\)","SO\\(_2\\) and NH\\(_3\\)","HCl and NH\\(_3\\)","SO\\(_2\\) and HCl"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following pollutants will lead to the depletion of ozone layer?<\/p>","options":["chlorofluorocarbon","carbon (ii) oxide","hydrogen sulphide","sulphur (iv) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following describes the chemical property of acids?<\/p>","options":["None of the above","Acid + XCO\\(_3\\) \\(\\to\\) Salt + H\\(_2\\)O + NH\\(_3\\)","Acid + NaOH \\(\\to\\) Normal salt + CO\\(_2\\)","Acid + X\\(_n\\)CO\\(_3\\) \\(\\to\\) Salt + H\\(_2\\)O + CO\\(_2\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following pairs cannot be represented with a chemical formula?<\/p>","options":["air and bronze","bronze and sodium chloride","copper and sodium chloride","caustic soda and washing soda"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Consider the equation below:<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>Cr\\(_2\\)O\\(_7 ^{2-}\\) + 6Fe\\(^{2+}\\) + 14H\\(^{+}\\) \\(\\to\\) 2Cr\\(^{3+}\\) + 6Fe\\(^{3+}\\) + 7H\\(_2\\)O.<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>The oxidation number of chromium changes from<\/p>","options":["+5 to +3","+6 to +3","-2 to +3","+7 to +3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is a physical change?<\/p>","options":["Exposing white phosphorus to air","Burning kerosene","Dissolving calcium in water","Freezing ice cream"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>In the reaction between sodium hydroxide and tetraoxosulphate (VI) solutions, what volume of 0.5 molar sodium hydroxide would exactly neutralize 10cm\\(^3\\) of 1.25 molar tetraoxosulphate (vi) acid?<\/p>","options":["25cm\\(^3\\)","10cm\\(^3\\)","20cm\\(^3\\)","50cm\\(^3\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Sulphur exists in six forms in the solid state. This property is known as<\/p>","options":["Isomerism","Allotropy","Isotopy","Isomorphism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>In the reaction:<br \/>\r\nM + N &rarr; P<br \/>\r\n&Delta;H = +Q kJ<br \/>\r\n<br \/>\r\nWhich of the following would increase the concentration of the product?<\/p>","options":["Adding a suitable catalyst","Increasing the concentration of P","Increasing the temperature","Decreasing the temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A compound contains 40.0% carbon, 6.7% hydrogen and 53.3% oxygen. If the molar mass of the compound is 180. Find the molecular formula.<br \/>\r\n[H = 1, C = 12, O = 16]<\/p>","options":["C\\(_3\\)H\\(_6\\)O\\(_3\\)","C\\(_6\\)H\\(_6\\)O\\(_3\\)","C\\(_6\\)H\\(_{12}\\)O\\(_6\\)","CH\\(_2\\)O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The IUPAC nomenclature of the compound<br \/>\r\nH\\(_3\\)C - CH(CH\\(_3\\)) - CH(CH\\(_3\\)) - CH\\(_2\\) - CH\\(_3\\)<\/p>","options":["3,4- dimethylhexane","2,3- dimethyl pentane","2- ethyl hexane","2,3- dimethylhexane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following gases contains the least number of atoms at s.t.p?<\/p>","options":["1 mole of butane","4 moles of chlorine","3 moles of ozone","7 moles of argon"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>What mass of magnesium would be obtained by passing a current of 2 amperes for 2 hours 30 mins, through molten magnesium chloride?<br \/>\r\n[1 faraday = 96500C, Mg = 24]<\/p>","options":["1.12g","4.48g","1.80g","2.00g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which important nitrogen-containing compound is produced in Haber&#39;s process?<\/p>","options":["NH\\(_3\\)","NO\\(_2\\)","NO","HNO\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Elements in the periodic table are arranged in the order of their<\/p>","options":["atomic numbers","metallic character","mass number","relative atomic mass"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>What volume of 0.100M sodium trioxonitrate (V) solution contains 5g of solute.<br \/>\r\n[Na = 23, N = 14, O = 16]<\/p>","options":["1.7 litres","0.420 litres","0.588 litres","2.35 litres"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The two ions responsible for hardness in water are<\/p>","options":["Ca\\(^{2+}\\) and \/ or Mg\\(^{2+}\\)","K\\(^+\\) and \/ or Mg\\(^{2+}\\)","Ca\\(^{2+}\\) and \/ or Li\\(^+\\)","Ca\\(^{2+}\\) and \/ or Na\\(^+\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following could not be alkane?<\/p>","options":["C\\(_4\\)H\\(_{10}\\)","C\\(_5\\)H\\(_{12}\\)","C\\(_7\\)H\\(_{14}\\)","C\\(_8\\)H\\(_{18}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The electronic configuration of element Z is 1s\\(^2\\) 2s\\(^2\\) 2p\\(^6\\) 3s\\(^2\\) 3p\\(^1\\). What is the formula of the compound formed between Z and tetraoxosulphate&nbsp;(VI) ion.<\/p>","options":["Z\\(_3\\)(SO\\(_4\\))\\(_2\\)","ZSO\\(_4\\)","Z\\(_2\\) SO\\(_4\\)","Z\\(_2\\)(SO\\(_4\\))\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The hybridization in the compound \\(CH_3 - CH_2 - C \\equiv H\\) is<\/p>","options":["sp\\(^3\\) and sp","sp","sp\\(^2\\)","sp\\(^3\\) and sp\\(^2\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The following are isoelectronic ions except<\/p>","options":["Na\\(^+\\)","Mg\\(^{2+}\\)","Si\\(^{2+}\\)","O\\(^{2+}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Consider the reaction: A + 2B\\(_{(g)} \\rightleftharpoons&nbsp;\\) 2C + D\\(_{(g)}\\) (\\(\\Delta\\)H = +ve)<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>What will be the effect of decrease in temperature on the reaction?<\/p>","options":["Rate of backward reaction will increase","The equilibrium constant will shift","Rates of forward and backward reactions are not affected","Rate of forward reaction will increase"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A cell shorthand notation can be written as A \/ A\\(^+\\) \/\/ B\\(^{2+}\\) \/B. The double slash in the notation represents the&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["electrolyte","electrodes","salt bridge","solid - liquid interface"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The shapes of water, ammonia, carbon (iv) oxide and methane are respectively<\/p>","options":["linear, tetrahedral, angular and pyramidal","angular, pyramidal, linear and tetrahedral","pyramidal, linear, tetrahedral and angular","tetrahedral, angular, pyramidal and linear"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which quantum divides shells into orbitals?<\/p>","options":["Spin","Principal","Azimuthal","Magnetic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The oxidation state(s) of nitrogen in ammonium nitrite is\/are<\/p>","options":["-3, +3","+5","-3, +5","-3"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Hydrogen bond is a sort of<\/p>","options":["van der waals force","dative bond","ionic bond","a covalent bond"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Methane is prepared in the laboratory by heating a mixture of sodium ethanoate with soda lime. The chemical constituent(s) of soda lime is\/are<\/p>","options":["Ca(OH)\\(_2\\) and NaOH","Na\\(_2\\)CO\\(_3\\)","NaCl","NaOH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following sets of operation will completely separate a mixture of sodium chloride, sand and iodine?<\/p>","options":["addition of water, filtration, evaporation to dryness and sublimation","filtration, evaporation to dryness, addition of water and sublimation","sublimation, filtration, evaporation and addition of water","sublimation, addition of water, filtration and evaporation to dryness"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>200cm\\(^3\\) of 0.50mol\/dm\\(^3\\) solution of calcium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (IV) is heated. The maximum weight of solid precipitated is<\/p>","options":["10g","25g","20g","15g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following conditions will most enhance the spontaneity of a reaction?<\/p>","options":["\\(\\Delta\\)H is negative and greater than T\\(\\Delta\\)S","\\(\\Delta\\)H is negative and \\(\\Delta\\)S = 0","\\(\\Delta\\)H is positive and less than T\\(\\Delta\\)S","\\(\\Delta\\)H is positive and equal to T\\(\\Delta\\)S"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>X is a substance which liberates CO\\(_2\\) on treatment with concentrated H\\(_2\\)SO\\(_4\\). A warm solution of X can decolorize acidified KMnO\\(_4\\). X is<\/p>","options":["HCOOH","NaHCO\\(_3\\)","FeCO\\(_3\\)","H\\(_2\\)C\\(_2\\)O\\(_4\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The velocity, V of a gas is related to its mass, M by (k = proportionality constant)<\/p>","options":["V = \\(\\frac{k}{M}\\)","V = \\(\\frac{k}{M^{\\frac{1}{2}}}\\)","V = \\(kM^2\\)","V = \\((\\frac{k}{M})^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The emission of two successive beta particles from the nucleus \\(^{32} _{15} P\\) will produce<\/p>","options":["\\(^{30} _{14}\\)Si","\\(^{32} _{13}\\)Al","\\(^{32} _{17}\\)Cl","\\(^{32} _{16}\\)S"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Hydrogen diffused through a porous plug<\/p>","options":["thrice as fast as oxygen","at the same speed as oxygen","four times as fast as oxygen","twice as fast as oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>If the cost of electricity required to discharge 10g of an ion X\\(^{3+}\\) is N20.00, how much would it cost to discharge 6g of ion Y\\(^{2+}\\)?<\/p>\r\n\r\n<p>[1 faraday = 96,500C, atomic masses are X = 27, Y = 24]<\/p>","options":["N10.00","N6.00","N20.00","N9.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The cost of discharging 6.0g of a divalent metal, X from its salt is \u20a612.00. What is the cost of discharging 9.0g of a trivalent metal, Y from its salt under the same condition?<br \/>\r\n[X = 63, Y = 27, 1F = 96,500C]<\/p>","options":["N12.00","N27.00","N63.00","N95.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>How many alkoxyalkanes can be obtained from the molecular formula C\\(_4\\)H\\(_{10}\\)O?<\/p>","options":["4","2","1","3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The reaction \\(2H_2 S + SO_2 \\to 3S + 2H_2 O\\) is<\/p>","options":["not a redox reaction because there is no oxidant in the reaction","not a redox reaction because there is no reductant in the reaction","a redox reaction in which H\\(_2\\)S is the oxidant and SO\\(_2\\) is the reductant","a redox reaction in which SO\\(_2\\) is the oxidant and H\\(_2\\)S is the reductant"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A solution X, on mixing with AgNO\\(_3\\) solution gives a white precipitate soluble in aqueous NH\\(_3\\), a solution Y, when also added to X, also gives a white precipitate which is soluble when heated solutions X and Y respectively contain<\/p>","options":["Al\\(^{3+}\\), Cl\\(^-\\)","Hg\\(^+\\), SO\\(_4 ^{2-}\\)","Pb\\(^{2+}\\), Cl\\(^-\\)","Ag\\(^+\\), SO\\(_4 ^{2-}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>How many electrons will be found in the nucleus of an atom with mass number 23 and 17 neutrons?<\/p>","options":["none","6","7","8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>An element Z contains 80% of \\(^{16} _8\\)Z and 20% of \\(^{18} _8\\)Z. Its relative atomic mass is<\/p>","options":["16.2","17.6","16.0","16.4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>When the end alkyl groups of ethyl ethanoate are interchanged, the compound formed is<\/p>","options":["propylmethanoate","ethylpropanoate","methyl ethanoate","methyl propanoate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The part of the total energy of a system that accounts for the useful work done in a system is known as<\/p>","options":["Enthalpy change","None of the above","Gibb's free energy","Entropy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following factors will speed up the rate of evolution of carbon (iv) oxide in the reaction below?<br \/>\r\n2HCl + CaCO\\(_3\\) &rarr; CaCl\\(_2\\) + H\\(_2\\)O + CO\\(_2\\)<\/p>","options":["Increasing the concentration of the acid","Increasing the surface area of CaCO\\(_3\\)","A and B","Reducing the concentration of the acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A given amount of gas occupies 10.0dm<small>5<\/small>&nbsp;at 4atm and 273&deg;C. The number of moles of the gas present is [Molar volume of gas at s.t.p = 22.4dm\\(^3\\)]<\/p>","options":["0.89 mol","1.90 mol","3.80 mol","5.70 mol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>According to Charles&#39; law, the volume of a gas becomes zero at<\/p>","options":["0\u00b0C","-100\u00b0C","-273\u00b0C","-373\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A substance that is used as a ripening agent for fruits is<\/p>","options":["ethene","propane","methane","butane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The Sulphide which is insoluble in dilute hydrochloric acid is<\/p>","options":["FeS","CuS","ZnS","Na2S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>What is the PH of 0.00 1 moldm\\(^3\\)&nbsp;solution of the sodium hydroxide<\/p>","options":["14","13","12","11"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The type of bonding in [Cu(NH\\(_3\\))\\(^4\\)]\\(^{2+}\\)&nbsp;is&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["coordinate","electrovalent","metallic","covalent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is an example of a chemical change?<\/p>","options":["dissolution of salt in water","rusting of iron","melting of ice","separating a mixture by distillation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>To what temperature must a gas at 273k be heated in order to double both its volume and pressure?<\/p>","options":["298K","546K","819K","1092K"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>According to the Kinetic Theory an increase in temperature causes the kinetic energy of particles to<\/p>","options":["decrease","remain constant","increase","be zero"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>An element used in the production of matches is<\/p>","options":["nitrogen","aluminium","copper","sulphur"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following gases may not be dried with concentrated sulphuric acid?<\/p>","options":["HCl\\(_{(g)}\\)","NH\\(_3\\)","Cl\\(_2\\)","SO\\(_2\\)"],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The Consecutive members of an alkane homologous series differ by<\/p>","options":["CH","CH\\(_2\\)","CH\\(_3\\)","C\\(_n\\)H\\(_n\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A correct electrochemical series can be obtained from Na, Ca, Al, Mg, Zn, Fe, Pb, H, Cu, Hg, Ag, Au by interchanging<\/p>","options":["Al and Mg","Zn and Fe","Zn and Pb","Pb and H"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A basic postulate of the kinetic theory of gases is that the molecules of a gas move in straight lines between collisions. This implies that<\/p>","options":["collisions are perfectly elastic","forces of repulsion exist","forces of repulsion and attraction are in equilibrium","collisions are inelastic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>On which of the following is the solubility of a gaseous substance dependent?&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nI. Nature of solvent&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nII. Nature of solute&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nIII. Temperature&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nIV. Pressure<\/p>","options":["I, II, III and IV","I and II only","II only","I, III and IV only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following statements is correct about the periodic table?<\/p>","options":["Elements in the same period have the same number of valence electrons","The valence electrons of the elements in the same period increase progressively across the period","Elements in the same group have the same number of electron shells","The non-metallic Properties of the elements tend to decrease across each period"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The periodic classification is an arrangement of the elements<\/p>","options":["atomic weights","isotopic weights","molecular weights","atomic numbers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>If 1 litre of 2.2M sulphuric acid is poured into a bucket containing 10 litres of water and the resulting solution mixed thoroughly, the resulting sulphuric acid concentration will be<\/p>","options":["2.2M","1.1M","0.22M","0.11M"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the shown experiment (Fig. 1) the litmus paper will initially<\/p>","options":["be bleached","turn green","turn red","turn blue"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The boiling of fat and aqueous caustic soda is referred to as<\/p>","options":["hydrolysis","esterification","acidification","saponification"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following pairs of substances will react further with oxygen to form a higher oxide?<\/p>","options":["CO\\(_2\\) and H\\(_2\\)O","NO and H\\(_2\\)O","CO and CO\\(_2\\)","SO\\(_2\\) and NO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the preparation of oxygen by heating KCIO, in the presence of MnO\\(_2\\) only moderate heat is needed because the catalyst acts by \\(_2\\)<\/p>","options":["lowering the pressure of the reaction","increasing the surface area of the reaction","increasing the rate of the reaction","lowering the energy barrier of the reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Methanoic acid mixes with water in all proportions and has about the same boiling point as water. Which of the following methods would you adopt to obtain pure water from a mixture of Sand, water and methanoic acid?<\/p>","options":["Fractional distillation","Filtration followed by distillation","Neutralization with sodium hydroxide followed by distillation","Neutralization with sodium hydroxide followed by filtration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A quantity of electricity liberates 3.6g of Silver from its salt. What mass of aluminium Will be liberated from its salt by the same quantity of electricity? [Al = 27, Ag = 108].<\/p>","options":["2.7g","1.2g","0.9g","0.3g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Suitable reagents for the laboratory preparation nitrogen are<\/p>","options":["sodium dioxonitrate(III) and ammonium chloride","sodium trioxonitrate(V) and ammonium chloride","sodium chloride and ammonium trioxonitrate(V)","sodium chloride and ammonium di-ozonitrate(III)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The number of electrons in the valence shell of an element of atomic number 14 is?<\/p>","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>What volume of oxygen will remain after reacting 8cm of hydrogen gas with 20cm of oxygen gas<\/p>","options":["10cm\\(^3\\)","12cm\\(^3\\)","14cm\\(^3\\)","16cm\\(^3\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>If one of the following oxides is heated with hydrogen or carbon using a bunsen burner. it is not reduced to the metal, Which one is it?<\/p>","options":["lead oxide","Magnesium oxide","Copper oxide","Tin oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The lUPAC name for<\/p>","options":["1-methyl pentane","3-methylbutane","2-methylbutane","1-dimethyl propane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>An aqueous solution of a metal salt, M. gives a white precipitate with NaOH which dissolves in excess NaOH. With aqueous ammonia, the solution of M also gives a white precipitate which dissolves in excess ammonia Therefore the cation in M is<\/p>","options":["Zn","Ca","Al","Po"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>What is the concentration of a solution containing 2g of NaOH in 100cm<small>3<\/small>&nbsp;of solution? [Na = 23, O =16, H = 1]<\/p>","options":["0.40 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","0.50 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","0.05 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)","0.30 moldm\\(^{-3}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>How many atoms are present in 6.0g of magnesium? [Mg = 24, N.A = 6.02 x 10 \\(^{23}\\)mol]<\/p>","options":["1.20 x 10\\(^{22}\\)","2.4 x 10\\(^{22}\\)","1.51 x 10\\(^{22}\\)","3.02 x 10\\(^{22}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The radio isotope used in industrial radiography for the rapid checking of faults in welds and casting is?<\/p>","options":["carbon-14","phosphorus-32","cobalt","iodine-131"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Beryllium and Aluminium have similar properties because they<\/p>","options":["are both metals","belong to the same group","belong to the same period","are positioned diagonally to each other"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>mE + nF -----&gt; pG + qH&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nIn the equation shown, the equilibrium constant is given by?<\/p>","options":["\\(\\frac{[E]^m[F]}{[G]^p[H]^q}\\)","\\(\\frac{[E][F]}{[G][H]}\\)","\\(\\frac{[G]^p[H]^p}{[E]^m[F]^n}\\)","\\(\\frac{[G][H]}{[E][F]}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>(I). 3CuO<small>(s)<\/small>&nbsp;+ 2NH<small>3(g)<\/small>&nbsp;-----&gt; 3Cu<small>(s)<\/small>&nbsp;+ 3H<small>2<\/small>O<small>(l)<\/small>&nbsp;+ N<small>2(g)<\/small>&nbsp;<br \/>\r\n(II). 2NH<small>3(g)<\/small>&nbsp;+ 3Cl<small>2(g)<\/small>&nbsp;-----&gt; 6HCl<small>(g)<\/small>&nbsp;+ N<small>2(g)<\/small>&nbsp;<br \/>\r\n(III). 4NH<small>3(g)<\/small>&nbsp;+ 3O<small>2(g)<\/small>&nbsp;-----&gt; 6H<small>2<\/small>O<small>(l)<\/small>&nbsp;+ N<small>2(g)<\/small>&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nThe reactions represented by the equations above demonstrate the<\/p>","options":["basic properties of ammonia","acidic properties of ammonia","reducing properties of ammonia","oxidizing properties of ammonia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The salt that reacts with dilute hydrochloric acid to produce a pungent smelling gas which decolourizes acidified purple potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solution is<\/p>","options":["Na\\(_2\\)SO\\(_4\\)","Na\\(_2\\)SO\\(_3\\)","Na\\(_2\\)S","Na\\(_2\\)CO\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The refreshing and characteristic taste of soda water and other soft drinks is as a result of the presence of<\/p>","options":["carbon(IV)oxide","carbon(ll)oxide","soda","glucose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following are mixtures?&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nI. Petroleum&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nII. Rubber latex&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nIII. Vulcanizer&#39;s solution&nbsp;<br \/>\r\nIV. Carbon sulphide<\/p>","options":["I, II and III","I, II and IV","I and II only","I and IV"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A balanced chemical equation obeys the law of<\/p>","options":["conservation of mass","definite proportions","multiple proportions","conservation of energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>When air which contains the gases Oxygen, nitrogen, carbondioxide, water vapour and the rare gases, is passed through alkaline pyrogallol and then over quicklime, the only gases left are;<\/p>","options":["nitrogen and carbondioxide","the rare gases","nitrogen and oxygen","nitrogen and the rare gases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the laboratory preparation of oxygen, the gas cannot be collected by displacement of air because<\/p>","options":["the density of oxygen is greater than that of air","the density of air is nearly the same as that of oxygen","oxygen is a component of air","air is an impure substance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>2KClO3(g) MNO3&rarr; 2KCl(s) + 3O2(g)<br \/>\r\nThe importance of the catalyst in the reaction above is that<\/p>","options":["heating may not be required before the reaction takes place","the reaction is controllable even at a high temperature","the reaction produces large quantity of oxygen","the reaction takes place more rapidly at a lower temperature"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following is used to power steam engines?<\/p>","options":["lubricating oil","coal","bitumen","diesel oil"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the reaction between sodium hydroxide and sulphuric acid solutions, what volume of 0.5 molar sodium hydroxide would exactly neutralise 10cm3 of 1.25 molar sulphuric acid?<\/p>","options":["5cm\\(^3\\)","10cm\\(^3\\)","20cm\\(^3\\)","50cm\\(^3\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>To what volume must 300cm\\(^3\\) of 0.60M sodium hydroxide solution be diluted to give a 0.40M solution?<\/p>","options":["450cm\\(^3\\)","300cm\\(^3\\)","200cm\\(^3\\)","150cm\\(^3\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Diamond is a bad conductor of electricity because its bonding electrons are used in<\/p>","options":["crystal lattice formation","covalent bond formation","metallic bond formation","coordinate bond formation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The reaction between an organic acid and an alcohol in the presence of an acid catalyst is known as;<\/p>","options":["saponification","dehydration","esterification","hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The constituent common to duralumin and alnico is<\/p>","options":["Co","Mn","Al","Mg"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The solubility of the solids that dissolves in a given solvent with the liberation of heat will<\/p>","options":["increase with an increase in temperature","decrease with an increase in temperature","decrease with a decrease in temperature","not be affected by changes in temperature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>What mass of Cu would be produced by the cathodic reduction of Cu\\(^{2+}\\)&nbsp; when 1.60A of current passes through a solution of CuSO\\(_4\\) for 1 hour. (F=96500Cmol\\(^{-1}\\)&nbsp;, Cu=64)<\/p>","options":["7.64g","3.82g","1.91g","0.96g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Calculate the pH of 0.05 moldm\\(^{-3}\\) H\\(_2\\)SO\\(_4\\)<\/p>","options":["1.30","1.12","1.00","0.30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The choice of method for extracting a metal from its ores depends on the<\/p>","options":["strength of the core","position of the metal in the electrochemical series","source of the core","position of the metal in the periodic table"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>At what temperature is the solubility of potassium trioxonitrate(V ) equal to that of sodium trioxonitrate (V)?<\/p>","options":["0\\(^o\\)c","30\\(^o\\)c","40\\(^o\\)c","45\\(^o\\)c"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following produces relatively few ions in solution?<\/p>","options":["NaOH","Ca(OH)\\(_2\\)","KOH","AI(OH)\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The figure above shows the electrolysis of molten sodium chloride. Z is the<\/p>","options":["anode where the Cl\\(^-\\) ions are oxidized","cathode where the Cl\\(^-\\) ions are reduced","anode where the Na\\(^+\\) ions are reduced","cathode where the Na\\(^+\\) ions are oxidized"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The knowledge of half-life can be used to<\/p>","options":["Create an element","Detect an element","Split an element","Irradiate an element"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>An element X forms the following compounds with chlorine; XCl\\(_4\\), XCl\\(_3\\), XCl\\(_2\\). This illustrates the<\/p>","options":["law of multiple proportions","law of chemical proportions","law of simple proportions","law of conservation of mass"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The hydrogen ion concentration of a sample of orange juice is 2.0 X 10\\(^{-11}\\)moldm\\(^{-3}\\). What is its p\\(^{OH}\\)? [log102 = 0.3010]<\/p>","options":["3.30","13.00","10.70","11.30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>From the graph above, it may be concluded that<\/p>","options":["AgNO\\(_3\\) is probably not soluble at 1100","NaCl is insoluble in water","Pb(NO\\(_3\\))\\(_2\\) is more soluble than KCIO\\(_3\\)","The solubility of KCIO\\(_3\\) exceeds that of NaCl at all temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>2SO\\(_2\\) \\(_{(g) }\\)+ O\\(_2\\) \\(_{(g) }\\) &harr; 2SO\\(_3\\)\\(_{(g) }\\) &Delta;H = -395.7kJmol\\(^{-1}\\)<br \/>\r\nIn the equation, an increase in temperature will shift the equilibrium position to the<\/p>","options":["left and equilibrium constant decreases","left and equilibrium constant increases","right and equilibrium constant increases","right and equilibrium constant decreases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The end products of burning a candle in the atmosphere are water and&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["carbon (II) oxide","sulphur (IV) oxide","carbon (IV) oxide","sulphur (VI) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The collision theory explains reaction rates in terms of<\/p>","options":["size of the product","frequency of collision of the reactants","size of reactant","frequency of collision of the products"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The presence of ammonia gas in a desiccator can exclusively be removed by<\/p>","options":["phosphorus (V) oxide","fused calcium chloride","calcium chloride","concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Aluminium does not react with either dilute or concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid because<\/p>","options":["it is insoluble in either dilute or concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid","it is lower than hydrogen in the electrochemical series","the reaction with trioxonitrate (V) acid has a light activation energy","an insoluble oxide is formed on its surface which renders it passive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of these sources of water may likely contain the least concentration of Ca\\(^{2+}\\) and Mg\\(^{2+}\\)?<\/p>","options":["Spring water","River water","Tap water","Sea water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The conductivity of an acid solution depends on the<\/p>","options":["amount of ions present and their mobilities","mobilities of the ions present","amount of ions present","temperature of the solution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following metals cannot replace hydrogen from water or steam?<\/p>","options":["Sodium","Magnesium","Iron","Calcium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Elements P, Q, R, S have 6, 11, 15, 17 electrons respectively, therefore,<\/p>","options":["P will form an electrovalent bond with R","Q will form a covalent bond with S","R will form an electrovalent bond with S","Q will form an electrovalent bond with S"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>During the electrolysis of copper II sulphate between platinum electrodes, if litmus solution is added to the anode compartment<\/p>","options":["the litmus turns blue but no gas is evolved","the litmus turns blue and oxygen is evolved","the litmus turns blue and hydrogen is evolved","the litmus turns red and oxygen is evolved"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The derivative of benzene that can be used in making explosives is<\/p>","options":["aniline","xylene","phenol","toluene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In electrovalency, the oxidation number of the participating metal is always<\/p>","options":["decreasing","increasing","constant","neutral"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The ionic radii of metals are usually<\/p>","options":["greater than their atomic radii","unaffected by the charge on the ion","the same as their atomic radii","less than their atomic radii"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Calculate the percentage composition of oxygen in calcium trioxocarbonate(IV) [Ca=40, C=12, O=16]<\/p>","options":["16","48","40","12"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of these alloys contains copper?<\/p>","options":["solder","steel","permallory","bronze"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>If the molecular mass of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid is 98, calculate its vapour density.<\/p>","options":["196","49","106","82"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Sieving is a technique used to separate mixtures containing solid particles of<\/p>","options":["small sizes","large sizes","different sizes","the same size"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>3H\\(_{2(g)}\\)+ N2 &hArr; 2NH\\(_{3(g)}\\) ; H= -ve<br \/>\r\nIn the reaction above, lowering of temperature will<\/p>","options":["have no effect on the equilibrium position","increase the rate of both the forward and reverse reactions equally","favour the forward reaction","favour the reverse reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The situation obtained when a perfect gas expands into a vacuum is<\/p>","options":["\u0394H is positive and T\u0394 S is zero","\u0394H is positive and T \u0394 S is negative","\u0394H is negative and T\u0394 S is zero","\u0394H is zero and T \u0394 S is positive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The general formula of alkanones is<\/p>","options":["RCHO","R\\(_2\\)CO","RCOOH","RCOOR"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The alkanoic acid found in human sweat is<\/p>","options":["CH\\(_3\\)-COOH","CH\\(_3\\)\u2014CH\\(_2\\)\u2014COOH","H-COOH","CH\\(_3\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>The elements in the periodic table are listed in order of increasing<\/p>","options":["relative atomic number","atomic mass","relative isotopic mass","nuclear charge"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>H\\(_2\\) S\\(_{(g)}\\) + Cl\\(_{2(g)}\\) &rarr; 2HCl\\(_{(g)}\\) + S\\(_{(g)}\\) In the reaction above, the substance that is reduced is<\/p>","options":["H\\(_2\\)S","S","HCl","Cl\\(_2\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the compounds is composed of Al, Si, O and H?<\/p>","options":["Epson salt","Limestone","Clay","Urea"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>When large hydrocarbon molecules are heated at high temperature in the presence of a catalyst to give smaller molecules, the process is known as<\/p>","options":["disintegration","polymerization","cracking","degradation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the removal of water hardness, permutit is regenerated with a strong solution of<\/p>","options":["NaOH","Na\\(_3\\)SO\\(_4\\)","Na\\(_3\\)CO\\(_3\\)","NaCl"],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>A sample of hard water contains some calcium sulphate and calcium hydrogen carbonate. The total hardness may therefore be removed by<\/p>","options":["boiling the water","adding excess calcium hydroxide","adding a calculated amount of calcium hydroxide","adding sodium carbonate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following separation techniques can be employed in obtaining solvent from its solution?<\/p>","options":["Evaporation","Distillation","Filtration","Precipitation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"<p>In the upper atmosphere, the ultra-violet light breaks off a free chlorine atom from chlorofluorocarbon molecule. The effect of this is that the free chlorine atom will<\/p>","options":["be very reactive and will attack ozone","be non-reactive and will not attack ozone","not change the level of ozone in the atmosphere","increase the level of ozone in the atmosphere"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2018"},{"question":"The general formula of alkanones is","options":["RCHO","R<sub>2<\/sub>CO","RCOOH","RCOOR"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The constituent common to duralumin and alnico is","options":["Co","Mn","Al","Mg"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The shape of the S-orbital is","options":["elliptical","spiral","circular","spherical"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Aluminium hydroxide is used in the dyeing industry as a","options":["dye","dispersant","salt","mordant"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The tincture of iodine means iodine dissolved in","options":["ethanol","bromine chloride","chlorine water","water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Temporary hard water is formed when rain water containing dissolved carbon(IV) oxide flows over deposits of","options":["CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The acid anhydride that will produce weak acid in water is","options":["SO<sub>3<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The process that occurs when two equivalent forms of a compound are in equilibrium is","options":["Isotopy","Resonance","Isomerism","Reforming"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"In the laboratory preparation of ethyl ethanoate, the water present in the mixture is removed using a solution of","options":["an hydrous CaCl<sub>4<\/sub>","concentrated NaCO<sub>4<\/sub>","dilute NaOH","concentrated H<sub>4<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The constituent of air necessary in the rusting process are","options":["O<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Ar and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","O<sub>2<\/sub> and CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"For a general equation of the nature xP + yQ \u2192 mR + nS, the expression for the equilibrium constant is","options":["k [P]<sup>x<\/sup> [Q]<sup>y<\/sup>","\\(\\frac{[P]^x [Q]^y}{[R]^m [S]^n}\\)","\\(\\frac{[R]^m [S]^n}{[P]^x [Q]^y}\\)","\\(\\frac{m[R] n[S]}{x[P] y[Q] }\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"A given mass of gas occupies 2dm<sup>3<\/sup> at 300k. At what temperature will its volume be doubled, keeping the pressure constant?","options":["400k","480k","550k","600k"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The oxidation number of iodine in KIO<sub>3<\/sub> is","options":["+7","+3","+5","+6"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"An isomer of C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub> is","options":["2\u2013ethyl butane","butane","2\u2013methyl butane","2\u2013methyl propane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"When few drops of concentrated trioxonitrate(V) acid is added to an unknown sample and wanned an intense yellow colouration is observed. The likely functional group present in the sample is","options":["NH<sub>3<\/sub>\u2014C\u2014C=O","CHO","CO","CNH<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"A sample of orange juice is found to have a PH of 3.80. What is the concentration of the hydroxide ion in the juice?","options":["1.6 \\(\\times\\) 10<sup>-4<\/sup>","6.3 \\(\\times\\) 10<sup>-11<\/sup>","6.3 \\(\\times\\) 10<sup>-4<\/sup>","1.6 \\(\\times\\) 10<sup>-11<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p>Incomplete oxidation of ethanol yields<\/p>","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>OCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The salt formed from a weak acid and a strong base hydrolyzes in water to form","options":["A saturated solution","an acidic solution","a buffer solution","an alkaline solution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The ideal gas laws and equations are true for all gases at","options":["low pressures and lower temperatures","low temperatures and high pressures","high pressures and high temperatures","low pressure and high temperatures"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"When \u0394H is negative, a reaction is said to be","options":["endothermic","exothermic","reversible","ionic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"\\(^{226}_{88}Ra\\) \u2192 \\(^x_{86}Rn\\) + alpha particle","options":["226","220","227","222"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The shape of ammonia molecules is","options":["trigonal planar","octahedral","square planar","tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The mass of silver deposited when a current of 10A is passed through a solution of silver salt for 4830s is \u2013 (Ag = 108 F = 96500(mol<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["54.0g","27.0g","13.5g","108.0g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Tin is unaffected by air at ordinary temperature due to its","options":["Low melting point","Weak electropositive character","High boiling point","White lustrous appearance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Calculate the amount in moles of silver deposited when 9650C of electricty is passed through a solution of silver salt [= 96500 Cmol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.05","10.80","10.00","0.10"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The reaction of halogens in the presence of sunlight is an example of","options":["oxidation reaction","addition reaction","hydrogenation reaction","substitution reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The enzyme used in the hydrolysis of starch to dextrin and maltose is","options":["amylase","diastatse","invertase","zymase"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The alkyl group is represented by the general formula","options":["C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>n","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>n \u2212 2","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>n + 1","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>n + 2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"CH<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2Cn + SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nWhat is the change in the oxidation number of copper in the reaction?","options":["0 to + 2","0 to + 1","C + 1 to 0","+ 2 to + 1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"In the diagram above. X is","options":["SO<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","S","H<sub>2<\/sub>S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The diagram above. Y is","options":["fused CaO","H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NaOH","Concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Calculate the mass of copper deposited when a current of 0.5 ampere was passed through a solution of copper(II) chloride for 45 minutes in an electrolytic cell. [Cu = 64, F = 96500Cmol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.300g","0.250g","0.2242g","0.448g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub> - COH<sub>3<\/sub> =CH<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\nThe IUPAC nomenclature of the structure above is","options":["3-methybut-3-ene","2-methylbut-1-ene","2-ethylprop-1-ene","2-methylbut-2-ene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The reddish\u2013brown rust on ion roofing sheets consists of","options":["Fe<sup>3<\/sup> + (H<sub>2<\/sub>O)<sub>6<\/sub>","FeO.H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>.3H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Fe<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>.2H2<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The densities of two gases, X and Y are 0.5gdm<sup>-3<\/sup> and 2.0gdm<sup>-3<\/sup> respectively. What is the rate of diffusion of X relative to Y?","options":["0.1","0.5","2.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The carbon atoms on ethane are","options":["sp<sup>2<\/sup> hybridized","sp<sup>3<\/sup> hybridized","sp<sup>4<\/sup> hybridized","sp hybridized"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"According to Charle's law, the volume of a gas becomes zero at","options":["\u2212100\u00b0c","\u2212273\u00b0c","\u2212373\u00b0c","0\u00b0c"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"An oxide XO<sub>2<\/sub> has a vapour density of 32. What is the atomic mass of X?","options":["20","32","14","12"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The gas that can be collected by downward displacement of air is","options":["chlorine","sulphur (IV) oxide","carbon (IV) oxide","ammonia"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"In the laboratory preparation of trioxonitrate (V) acid the nitrogen(iv) oxide formed as a by-product is removed by","options":["further heating","adding concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","cooling the acid solution with cold water","bubbling air through the acid solution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"A particle that contains a protons, 10 neutrons and 10 electrons is","options":["positive ion","neutral atom of a metal","neutral atom of a non-metal","negative ion"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Ethene is prepared industrially by","options":["Reforming","Polymerization","Distillation","Cracking"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Calculate the amount in moles of a gas which occupies 10.5 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at 6 atm and 30<sup>o<\/sup>C [R = 082 atm dm<sup>3<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup> mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["2.536","1.623","4.736","0.394"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"If 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen pass through a porous plug is 50 seconds, the time taken for the same volume of hydrogen to pass through the same porous plug is? [O = 16, H = 1]","options":["10.0s","12.5s","17.7s","32.0s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Due to the high reactivity of sodium, it is usually stored under","options":["water","mercury","paraffin","phenol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"The furring of kettles is caused by the presence in water of","options":["calcium hydrogentrioxocarbonate (IV)","calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)","calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","calcium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Water for town supply is chlorinate to make it free from","options":["bad colour","bacteria","temporary hardness","permanent hardness"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"Ca(OH)<sub>2(s)<\/sub>  + 2NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CaCl<sub>2(s)<\/sub>  + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2(l)<\/sub>  + X. In the reaction above X is","options":["NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","NO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"X<sub>(g)<\/sub> + 3Y<sub>(g)<\/sub> ---- 2z<sub>(g)<\/sub> H = +ve. if the reaction above takes place at room temperature, the G will be","options":["negative","zero","positive","indeterminate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"In an electrochemical cell, polarization is caused by","options":["Oxygen","Hydrogen","Tetraoxosulphate(IV) acid","Chlorine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The condition required for corrosion to take place is the presence of","options":["Oxygen and Carbon (IV) oxide","Water and Oxygen","Water and Carbon (IV) oxide and Oxygen","Water and Carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The enzyme used in the hydrolysis of starch to dextrin and maltose is","options":["Zymase","Sucrase","Amylase","Lactase"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In the laboratory preparation of chlorine from concentrated hydrochloric acid in the presence of potassuim tetraoxomanganate(VII) the produced is dried by passing it through","options":["Concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","Anhydrous calcium chloride","Calcium oxide","Sodium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The monomer of nylon is","options":["Hydroxybenzene","Hexanedioic acid","Benzene -1,-4-dicarboxylic acid","Ethane-1,2-diol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The principle of column chromatography is based on th ability of the constituents to","options":["React with the solvent in the column","React with each other in the solvent in the column","Dissolve in each other in the column","Move at different speeds in the column"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Ammonium chloride can be separated from its mixture with common salt by","options":["Distillation","Evaporation","Decantation","Sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The ability of carbon to form long chains is referred to as","options":["Alkylation","Acylation","Carbonation","Catenation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The industrial preparation of hydrogen gas from water gas is referred to as","options":["Bosch process","Contact process","Haber process","Bayer Process"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The relative atomic mass of a naturally occurring lithium consisting of 90%\\(\\frac{7}{3}\\)Li and 10%\\(\\frac{6}{3}\\)Li is","options":["6.2","6.8","7.1","6.9"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The colour of litmus in an alkaline medium is","options":["Red","Yellow","Pink","Blue"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The compounds CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHO and CH<sub>3<\/sub>COCH<sub>3<\/sub> can be distinguished from each other using","options":["Dilute ammonia","Benedict's solution","Tollen's reagent","Sodium hydroxide solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true about 2-methylpropane and butane","options":["They have different number of carbon atoms","They are members of same homologous series","They have the same boiling points","They have the same chemical properties"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The process that requires the use of hardwater in its operation is","options":["Tanning","Bottling","Laundry","Dyeing"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"What is the concentration of a solution containing 2g of NaOH in 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of solution?<br>\r\n[Na=23, O=16, H=1]","options":["0.05 moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.30 moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.50 moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.40 moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The radioisotope used in industrial radiography for the rapid checking of faults in welds and casting is","options":["Phosphorus-32","Cobalt-60","Carbon-14","Iodine-131"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The compound produced when sodium peroxide is heated with excess sodium is","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>O","NaNO<sub>2<\/sub>","NaOH"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The pollutant that contributes to the depletion of the ozone layer is","options":["CFCs","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following properties is not peculiar to matter?","options":["Kinetic energy of particles increases from solid to gas","Random motion of particles increases from gas to solid","Orderliness of particles increases from gas to liquid","Random motion of particles increases from liquid to gas"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Cast iron is used in making","options":["Chains and agricultural implements","Iron sheets and retort stand","Nails and iron rods","Stoves and cookers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is used as a gaseous fuel?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub> -CH<sub>2<\/sub> -CHO<sub>2<\/sub> -COOH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> -C = CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> -CH<sub>2<\/sub> -CH<sub>2<\/sub> -CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub> -CH<sub>2<\/sub> -CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The product formed when propanol is heated over a copper catalyst in the absence of oxygen are","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHO and H<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CHO and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>COOH and H<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH and CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Alkanols have the general molecular formula","options":["C<sub>1<\/sub>H<sub>2n-2<\/sub>","C<sub>1<\/sub>H<sub>2n-1<\/sub>CHO","C<sub>1<\/sub>H<sub>2n-2<\/sub>OH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2n+1<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following is not an alkali?","options":["Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","NaOH","Al(OH)<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about the periodic table?","options":["Elements in the same group have the same number of electron shells","The non-metallic properties of the elements tend to decrease across each period","Elements in the same period have the same number of valence electrons","The valence electrons of  the elements increase progressively across the period"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The metal whose ore can be concentrated by passing it through a magnetic separator is","options":["Zn","Sn","Cn","Ca"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An example of an acidic oxide is","options":["NO","CO","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","CuO"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"What volume of 0.5 MH<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> will exactly neutralize 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 MNaOH Solution?","options":["2.0cm <sup>3<\/sup>","5.0cm <sub>3<\/sub>","6.8cm <sup>3<\/sup>","8.3cm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Diamond cannot be used","options":["In making bicycle chains","As abrasives","In cutting glass and metals","As dies for drawing wires"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Ethanol is soluble in water due to the presence of a","options":["Carbonyl group","Hydroxyl groupd","Phenyl group","Methyl group"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The number of electronic shells contained in an atom with electron configuration 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>6<\/sup>4s<sup>2<\/sup> is","options":["3","2","4","5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The drying agent suitable for drying ammonia is","options":["Calcium Chloride","Calcium Oxide","Phosphorus(V) Oxide","Concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The arrangement of particles in crystal lattices can be studied using","options":["X-rays","\\(\\beta\\)-rays","\\(\\alpha\\)-rays","\\(\\gamma\\)-rays"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"<p>In the extraction of iron, the waste gas from the furnace is a mixture of<\/p>","options":["PH<sub>3<\/sub> CO and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO and C","N<sub>2<\/sub> , CO and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","PH<sub>3<\/sub> and CO"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In a neutralization reaction involving HCI and NaOH using litmus as indicator, the colour at the end point is","options":["Blue","Red","Orange","Purple"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An example of a solid emulsion is","options":["Butter","Hair cream","Milk","Cod-liver oil"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An isotope has an atomic number of 15 and a mass number of 31. The number of proton it contains is","options":["16","15","31","46"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Calculate the volume in cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen evolved at s.t.p when a current of 5A is passed through acidified water for 193s?<br>\r\n[F = 96500 C <i>mol<\/i><sup>1<\/sup>. Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p = 22.4dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["0.056dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.224dm<sup>3<\/sup>","224.000dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56.000dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The gas that is used for the treatment of cancer is","options":["Neon","Radon","Xenon","Argon"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A chemical reaction in which the hydration energy is greater than the lattice energy is referred to as","options":["A reversible reaction","A spontenous  reaction","An endothermic reaction","An exothermic reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"MnO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + Y 5Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> <sub>(aq)<\/sub> \\(\\mapsto\\) Mn<sup>2+<\/sup> <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 5Fe <sup>2+<\/sup>  <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the equation above, Y is","options":["10H<sup>+<\/sup>  <sub>(aq)<\/sub>","5H<sup>+<\/sup>  <sub>(aq)<\/sub>","8H<sup>+<\/sup>  <sub>(aq)<\/sub>","4H<sup>+<\/sup>  <sub>(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The compound above exhibits","options":["Geometric isomerism","Positional isomerism","Structural isomerism","Optical isomerism"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"<i>n<\/i> monosaccharide \\( \\underset{Q}{\\stackrel{P}{\\rightleftharpoons}} \\) polysaccharide -<i>n<\/i> water.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the process above, P and Q respectively represent","options":["Condensation and hydrolysis","Fermentation and condensation","Polymerization and hydrolysis","Polymerization and condensation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The functional groups present in the compound above are","options":["Alkene and halo-group","Hydroxyl and chloro-group","Alkene and chloro-group","Hydroxyl and halo-group"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In the diagram above, X is the","options":["Enthalphy","Activated complex","Activation energy","Enthalphy change"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The diagram represents","options":["A spontaneous reaction","An exothermic reaction","A non-spontaneous","An endothermic reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The curve depicts titration between","options":["Strong acid and strong base","Strong acid and weak base","Weak acid and weak base","Weak acid and strong base"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"From the diagram above, an ideal gas can be represented by","options":["K","M","L","N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"CH<sub>4(g)<\/sub> + CI<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) CH<sub>2<\/sub>CI<sub>(s)<\/sub> + HCI<sub>g<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe major factor that influences the rate of the reaction above is","options":["Concentration","Catalyst","Temperature","Light"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> \\(\\rightleftharpoons\\) 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \\(\\bigtriangleup\\)H = +ve<br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, an increase in temperature will","options":["Increase the reactant production","Increase the value of the equilibrium constant","Shift the equilibrium to the left","Decrease the value of the equilibrium constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The filter in the cigarette reduce the nicotine construct by","options":["burning","absorption","evaporation","absorption"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of these require crystallization most?","options":["Drug making","Cement making","Paint making","Perfume making"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Iron is often galvanized in order to","options":["Make it more malleable","Remove the impurities unit","Protect it against corrosion","Render it passive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In the industrial production of H<sub>2<\/sub> is removed by (solution)","options":["washing under pressure","drying over phosphorus (V) oxide","passing the mixture to the limewater","using ammonical copper (I) chlorine"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The gas that is most useful in protecting humans against solar marathon is","options":["chlorine","ozone","carbon IV oxide","hydrogen sulphur"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Vulcanization involve the removal of","options":["monometer","the single bond","the double bond","a polymer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The acid in electrolysis of water is dilute","options":["HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub><\/sub>","HCl"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A small quantity of solid ammonium chloride (NH4Cl) texted gently in a test tube, the solid gradually disappear produce two gases. Later, a white cloudy deposit was absence on the cooler part of the test tube. The ammonium chloride is to have undergo","options":["distillation","sublimation","precipitation","evaporation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"When salt loses its water of crystallization to the atmosphere on exposure, the process is said to be","options":["efflorescence","d\u00e9liquescence","effervescence","fluorescence"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Atomicity of ozone is","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the noble gases has the greatest ionization energy","options":["He","Xe","Ar","Rr"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The weakest attractive force that can be observed between two molecules is","options":["ionic","covalent","co-ordinate covalent","vander Waals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An elements used in production of matches is","options":["nitrogen","aluminum","copper","sulphur"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Cathode rays cause an object placed behind a perforated anode to cast a shadow on the screen. This observation shows that the rays","options":["are positively charged","are negatively charged","Have mass","travel in straight lines"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Flow of current in electrolytes is due to the movement of","options":["electrons","Holes and electron","Ions","Charges"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A suitable reagent for distinguish between ethanoic and ethanol is","options":["bromine water","Fehling\u2019s solution","sodium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (iv)","Ammoniacal silver trioxonitrate(V)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In the discovery of protein, the instrument used is","options":["cathode ray tube","glass tube and discharge tube","discharge tube with terminal cathode","discharge tube with central cathode"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The above orbital diagram shown the electronic configuration of","options":["chlorine","nitrogen","calcium","neon"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following metals burns with brick red","options":["Pb","Ca","Na","Mg"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In the production of soap, concentrated sodium chloride solution is added to","options":["increase the solubility of soap","decrease the solubility of the soap","saponify the soap","emulsify the soap"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A liquid that will dissolve fat is","options":["hydrochloric acid","calcium hydrochloride","kerosene","water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Tartaric acid is used industrially to","options":["make baking powder","make fruit juice","remove rust","dry substance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"P1V1 = P2V2 supports ?","options":["Charles\u2019s law","Boyles\u2019s law","Graham\u2019s law","Avogadro\u2019s law"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A fixed mass of gas a volume of 92cm<sup>3<\/sup> at 3\u00b0C. When will be its volume at 18C if the pressure remains constant?","options":["15.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","87.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","97.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following ion\u2019s requires the quantity of electricity for discharge at an electrode","options":["2.0 mole of Q3<sup>+<\/sup>","2.5 mole of R2<sup>+<\/sup>","3.0 mole of T<sup>-<\/sup>","4.0 mole of Y<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Hydrogen can be displaced from a lot alkaline solution by","options":["Fe","Cu","Cn","Sn"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following types of alkanols undergo oxidation to produce alkanoic acids.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Primary alkanols<br>\r\nII. Secondary alkanols<br>\r\nIII. Tertiary alkanols","options":["I, II and III","I and II only","III only","I only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Rare gases are suitable because they","options":["are monoatomic","form ions easily","have duplet or octet electronic configuration in the outermost shells in their atoms","are volatile gases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A major source of oxide of oxygen is from the burning of","options":["coal","wood","fuel","chlorofluorocarbons"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the activities is commonly used as a nuclear fuel","options":["uranium","palladium","actium","thorium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The leachate of a certain ash is used in local soap because it contain","options":["sodium chloride and potassium hydroxide","sodium hydroxide","potassium hydroxide","soluble carbonates and hydrogen carbonate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"All these are electromagnetic waves except","options":["White light","Photon","X-ray","Infrared"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Cu<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>(s)<\/sub> + O2(g) = 2CU<sub>(s)<\/sub> + SO2<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","options":["+1 to 0","0 to +2","+2 to +1","0 to +1"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The number of isomers formed by C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>14<\/sub> is","options":["4","5","2","3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"There are basic particles from which matter called be made except","options":["Salt","Atom","Ion","Molecule"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The energy value of petrol can be determined by","options":["Bomb calorimeter","Catalytic cracker","Fractionating column","Thermometer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"What volume of 0.5mldm<sup>3<\/sup> H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> will exactly neutralize 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1moldm<sup>3<\/sup> NaOH Solution?","options":["2.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.8cm<sup>3<\/sup>","8.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A compound contains 40.0% carbon, 6.7% hydrogen and 53.3% oxygen. If the molar mass of the compound is 180, Find the molecular formula [H = 1, C = 12, O = 16)","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An oxidation state of or in K2CrO7","options":["7","6","5","4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The elements that belong to the third period of periodic table are","options":["Li, Be, Al and D","Na, P, O and Cl","B, C, N, and O","N2, Mg, S and Ar"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"When sugar is dissolve in ten, the reaction is accomplished by","options":["positive change","negative entropy change","no entropy change","a minimum entropy change"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + HCl<sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2192 NH <sub>4<\/sub>Cl <sub>(s)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe entropy change in the system above is","options":["positive","zero","negative","intermediate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Detergents are manufacture with strength hydrocarbon chains is to make them","options":["soluble","biodegradable","cheaper","foamy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following results in the fall of acid rain","options":["oxide of lead","particulate matter","oxides of carbon","gaseous hydrocarbon"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The fuming of kettles is caused by the presence in the water of","options":["calcium tetraoxosulphate (IV)","calcium hydrogentrionocarbonate (IV)","calcium hydroxide","calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A difference between chemical and physical change is that in a chemical change","options":["oxygen is consumed","heat is supplied","the reversible process occurs","a new substance is formed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"According to the kinetic theory an absence in temperature causes the kinetic energy of particles to","options":["decrease","increase","remain constant","be zero"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"PCL5(g)= PCL3(g) + Cl2(g)<br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, a decrease in pressure will","options":["Decelerate the reaction","Increase yield of Pcl3","Increase the yield of Pcl5","Accurate the reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following gives a precipitation when treated with NaOH Solution?","options":["AlCl<sub>3<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Electronic configuration of an elements 13x in the subsidiary energy level is","options":["\\( 1s^2 2s^2 2p^6 3s^2 3p^1 \\)","\\( 1s^22s^2 2p^4 3p^1 3s^1 \\)","\\( 1s^2 2s^2 2p^6 3s^2 3p^3 \\)","\\( 1s^1 2s^2 2p^6 3s^2 3p^4 \\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Alloys are best prepared by","options":["electroplating","Arc-welding","reducing and mixture of their metallic","cooking a molten of the metals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In countries where the temperature fall below 273k, salt always spilled on the ray road in order to","options":["increase the making point office","increase the density of the ice","make the ice impure","rinse the making point of the ice"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"What is the volume of energy required to burn 45cm3 of mixture at S.T.P","options":["135.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","150.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","45.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","90.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The substance that is used in the steel industry for the removal of carbon. Sulphur and phosphorus impurities from pig iron is","options":["oxygen","chlorine","nitrogen","hydrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"If glucose is heated on the concentration tetraoxosulphate(iv)acid, it will be dehydrated","options":["carbon","carbon(iv)oxide","ethane","ethanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Rare gases are suitable because they","options":["are monoatomic","form ions easily","have duplet or octet electronic configuration in the outermost shells in their atoms","are volatile gases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds can be represented by the molecular formula C2 H6O?","options":["propanal","ethanol","methanoic acid","glucose"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Two equal bulbs, one containing ammonia and the other one opened mouth-to mouth to each other at temperature the entropy in the mixture of gases is likely to","options":["remain unchanged","increase","decrease","charge"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"what is the pH of 0.00lmoldm<sup>3<\/sup> solution of sodium hydroxide","options":["14","13","12","11"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"According to the kinetic theory an absence in temperature causes the kinetic energy of particles to","options":["decrease","increase","remain constant","be zero"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub>\u2192 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the endothermic reaction above, more products formed will be favored by","options":["A constant values","an increase in pressure","a decrease pressure","a decrease volume"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Chlorine gas turns damp starch-iodide paper","options":["pink","colourless","red","dark blue"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Chlorine consisting of two isotope of mass number 35 and 37 in the ratio 3:1 has an atomic mass of 35.5. Calculate the relative abundance of the isotope of mass number 37","options":["20","25","60","75"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The principal constituent of natural gas is","options":["methane","ethane","propane","Butane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"One note of a hydrocarbon 36g of carbon and its density is 20. The structure of hydrocarbon is (organic chemical)","options":["CH3C = CH","CH3CH = CH2","CH3CH2C = CH","CH33CH2CH3"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of CuSo<sub>4(g)<\/sub> using platinum electrode the reaction at the anode is","options":["4H+ 4e - 2H<sub>2<\/sub>","4OH<sup>-<\/sup>- 4e = 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>","2OH - 2e<sub>-<\/sub> = 2OH","2OH<sup>-<\/sup> + 2OH = 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p>S block elements of the periodic table one made up of<\/p>","options":["groups 1, 2, 3","groups 1, and 2","group 3","group 3 to 7"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The oxidation state of oxygen on tetraoxosulphate iv acid is","options":["-4","-2","4","-8"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of brine the anode is","options":["platinum","copper","zinc","carbon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Calculate the relative molecular mass of Limestone CaCO3, (Ca = 40, C =12, O = 16)","options":["56","100","76","90"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"When stem is passed over red hot carbon the substances produced are","options":["hydrogen and trioxocarbonate (IV) acid","hydrogen, oxygen and carbon (IV) oxide","hydrogen and carbon (ii) oxide","hydrogen and carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A mixture is different from a compound because","options":["the properties of a compound are those of its individual constituents while those of a mixture differ from its constituents","a mixture is always homogeneous while a compound is not","the constituent of a compound are chemically bound together while those of a mixture are not","a mixture can be represented by a chemical formula while a compound cannot"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"What is the percentage of sulphur in sulphur (IV) oxide?","options":["66%","25%","40%","50%"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A gas X diffuses twice as fast as gas Y. if the relative molecular mass of X is 32, calculate the relative molecular mass of Y.","options":["128","8","16","64"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"200 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a gas at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C exerts a pressure of 700 mmHg. Calculate its pressure if its volume increase 350 cm<sup>3<\/sup> at 75<sup>o<\/sup>C.","options":["342.53 mmHg","1430.54 mmHg","467.11 mmHg","400.00 mmHg"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An element X has electron configuration 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>5<\/sup>. Which of the following statements is correct about the element?","options":["lt has a completely filled p-orbital","lt has 5 electrons in its outermost shell.","lt belongs to group ll on the periodic table","lt is a halogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Beryllium and aluminium have similar properties because they","options":["are both metals","belong to the same group","belong to the same period","are positioned diagonally to each other"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"If the difference in electronegativity of elements P and Q is 3.0. The bond that will be formed between them is","options":["metallic","covalent","co-ordinate","ionic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"How many protons, neutrons and electrons respectively are present in the element 60\/27 Co?","options":["27, 33 and 33","33, 27 and 27","27, 33, and 27","60, 33 and 60"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The radio active radiation used in studying the arrangement of particles in giant organic molecules is","options":["\\(\\gamma\\)- rays","\\(\\alpha\\)- particles","X-rays","\\(\\beta\\) - particles"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A silicon -containing ore has 92% <sup>28<\/sup>Si, 5% <sup>29<\/sup>Si and 3% <sup>30<\/sup>Si. Calculate the relative atomic mass of the silicon.","options":["14.00","29.00","28.11","28.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The nitrogen obtained from air has a density higher than the one from nitrogen-containing compounds because the one from air is contaminated with","options":["water vapour","oxgyen","rare gases","carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Water is said to be temporarily hard when it contains","options":["Ca (HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> and Mg (HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> salts","Ca (HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> and CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> SALTS","Mg(HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> and CaSO<sub>4<\/sub> salts","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub> and Ca(HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> salts"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"On exposure to the atmosphere, a hydrated salt loses its water of crystallization to become anhydrous. This phenomenon is referred to as","options":["efflorescence","diliquescence","hygroscopy","hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"16.55g of lead (ll) trioxonitrate (V) was dissolved in 100g of distilled water at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C, calculate the solubility of the solute in moldm-<sup>3<\/sup><br>\r\n<br>\r\n[Pb = 207, N = 14, O = 16]","options":["0.05 g","2.00 g","1.00 g","none of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The dispersion of a liquid in a liquid medium will give","options":["an emulsion","a fog","a gel","an aerosol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The major and most effective way of controlling pollution is to","options":["improve machinery so that the substances released from combustion are less harmful","pass strict laws against it by individuals and companies","educate people on the causes and effects of pollution","convert chemical wastes to harmless substances before releasing them into the environment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The basicity of CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH is","options":["4","1","2","3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The colour of litmus in a neutral medium is","options":["purple","pink","yellow","orange"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The mathematical expression of PH is","options":["log <sub>10<\/sub>[OH<sup>-<\/sup>]","log <sub>10<\/sub>1\/[H <sub>3<\/sub> O<sup>+<\/sup>]","log <sub>10<\/sub>[H <sub>3<\/sub> O<sup>+<\/sup>]","log <sub>10<\/sub>1\/[OH <sup>-<\/sup>]"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following salts will turn blue litmus red?","options":["Sodium tetrahydroxozincate (ll)","Potassium hydrogentetraoxosulphate (lV)","Sodium trioxocarbonate (lV)","Zinc chloride hydroxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Zn <sub>(s)<\/sub> + CuSO <sub>4<\/sub>(aq) \u2192 ZnSO <sub>4<\/sub>(aq) + Cu <sub>(s)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the oxidation number of the reducing agent changes from","options":["0 to + 4","0 to + 2","+ 1 to + 2","+ 1 to + 3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"H <sub>2<\/sub>O <sub>(g)<\/sub> + C <sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2192 H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + CO<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe oxidizing agent in the reaction above is","options":["CO<sub>(g)<\/sub>","C<sub>(s)<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub>","H<sub>(2)<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Calculate the quantity of electricity in coulombs required to liberate 10g of copper from a copper compound<br>\r\n<br>\r\n[Cu=64, F = 96500 Cmol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["32395.5","30156.3","60784.5","15196.5"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"How many faraday of electricity is required to produce 0.25 mole of copper?","options":["1.00F","0.01F","0.05F","0.50F"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"If the change in free energy of a system is -899 Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup> and the entropy change is 10Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup> at 250C, calculate the enthalpy change.","options":["+2081 Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-2081 Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-649 Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup>","+649 Jmol<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In an equilibrium reaction, which of the following conditions indicates that maximum yield of the product will be obtained?","options":["Equilibrium constant is very large","\u2206H - T\u2206S = O","\u2206 H > T \u2206 S","Equilibrium constant is less than zero"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In a chemical reaction, the change in concentration of a reactant with time is","options":["entropy of reaction","enthalpy of reaction","rate of reaction","order of reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Cr <sub>2<\/sub>O\\(\\frac{2 -}{7}\\) (aq) + H <sub>2<\/sub>O(1)\u21cc 2CrO \\(\\frac{2 -}{4}\\) (aq) + 2H<sup> +<\/sup> (aq)<br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhat happens to the reaction above when the hydrogen ion concentration is increased?","options":["more of the products will be formed","the reaction will not proceed","the equilibrium position will shift to the right","the equilibrium position will shift to the left."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following will shift to the left from dilute tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid?","options":["Lead","Magnesium","Cpper","Gold"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The gas that is removed by the water in the flask is","options":["O <sub>2<\/sub>","SO <sub>2<\/sub>","HCI","H <sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Fluorine does not occur in the free state in nature because","options":["it is a poisonous gas","it belongs to the halogen family","it is inert","of its high reactivity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In the extraction of sodium from fused sodium chloride, the anode is made of platinum because","options":["sodium is formed at the anode","chlorine is formed at the anode","sodium does not react with platinum","chlorine does not react with platinum"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In the electrolytic extraction of cacium from calcium chloride, the cathode is","options":["zinc","graphite","platinum","iron"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A compound that gives a brick-red colour to a non-luminous flame is likely to contain","options":["copper ions","sodium ions","calcium ions","aluminium ions"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A few drops of NaOH solution was added to an unknown salt forming a white precipitate which is insoluble in excess solution. The cation likely present is","options":["Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup>","Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Al<sup>3+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The general formula of haloalkanes where X represents the halide is","options":["C<sub>n<\/sub> H <sub>2n-1<\/sub>X.","C <sub>n<\/sub>H <sub>2n<\/sub>X.","C <sub>n<\/sub>H <sub>2n+2<\/sub> X","C <sub>n<\/sub>H <sub>2n+1<\/sub>X"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The alkanol obtained from the production of soap is","options":["propanol","ethanol","glycerol","methanol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Ethyne is passed through a hot tube containing organo-nickel catalyst to produce","options":["isoprene","polythene","ethanol","benzene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Due to the unstable nature of ethyne, it is stored by dissolving in","options":["ethane-1,2-diol","propanol","ethanoic acid","propanone"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The process of converting starch to ethanol is","options":["cracking","distillation","fermentation","oxidation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The polymer used in making car rear lights is","options":["perspex","bakeelite","polystyrene","polyacrylonitrile"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>(1) + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub> \u21cc CH <sub>3<\/sub>COOH <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + C <sub>2<\/sub>H <sub>5<\/sub>OH <sub>(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe purpose of H<sup>+<\/sup> in the reaction above is to","options":["increase the yield of products","maintain the solution at a constant PH","increase the rate of the hydrolysis","decrease the rate of the reverse reaction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A hydrocarbon has an empirical formula CH and a vapour density of 39. Determine its molecular formula.<br>\r\n<br>\r\n[C = 12, H = 1]","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Polystyrene is widely used as packaging materials for fragile objects during transportation because of its","options":["ligjtness","low density","high density","high compressibility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The process of converting linear alkanes to branched chain and cyclic hydrocarbons by heating in the presence of a catalyst to improve the quality of petrol is referred to as","options":["refining","craching","reforming","blending"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The petroleum fraction that is used in heating furnaces in industries is","options":["diesel oil","gasoline","kerosene","lubricating oil"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of the compound above is","options":["2-bromo-3-chlorobutanol","3-bromo-2-chlorobutanol","3-chloro-2-bromobutanol","2-chloro-3-bromobutanol"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In the diagram, the function of the concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> is to","options":["purify the gas","dry the gas","liquefty the gas","remove odour"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The gas that is removed by the water  in the flask  is","options":["O<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","HCI.","H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Z in diagram above represents","options":["heat of reaction","activation energy","free energy","entropy of reaction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The presence of an impurity in substance will cause the melting point to","options":["be zero","reduce","increase","be stable"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"What volume of carbon (ll) oxide is produced by reacting excess carbon with 10 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen?","options":["5 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","20 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","15 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","10 dm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The rate of diffusion of a gas Y is twice that of Z If the relative molecular mass of Y is 64 and the two gases diffuse under the same conditions, find the relative molecular mass of Z","options":["32","4","8","16"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The radioisotope used in industrial radiography for the rapid checking of faults in welds and casting is","options":["carbon-14","phosphorus-32","cobalt-60","iodine-131"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The  shape of the carbon (lV) oxide molecule is","options":["pyramidal","linear","angular","tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following molecules is held together by hydrogen bond?","options":["CH<sub>4<\/sub>","HBr","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","HF"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The bond formed between two elements with electron configurations 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>4<\/sup> is","options":["metallic","covalent","dative","ionic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The constituent of air that acts as a diluent is","options":["nitrogen","carbon (IV) oxide","noble gases","oxygen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Steam changes the colour of anhydrous cobalt (ll) chloride from","options":["white  to red","blue to white","blue to pink","white to blue"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"An example of a hygroscopic substance is","options":["CuO <sub>(S).<\/sub>","MgCL<sub>2(S).<\/sub>","CaCL<sub>2(S).<\/sub>","NaOH<sub>(S).<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"If 24.4 g of lead (ll) trioxonitrate (V) were dissolved in 42 g of distilled water at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C; calculate the solubility of the solute in gdm<sup>-3<\/sup>.","options":["581.000.","0.581","5.810","58.100"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The solvent used for removing grease stain is","options":["turpentine","ammonia solution","ethanol","solution of borax in water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"In a water body, too much sewage leads to","options":["a decrease in the temperature of the water which cause in death of aquatic animals","an increase in the number of aquatic animals in the water","an increase in the bacterial population which reduces the level of oxygen in the water","a decrease in the bacterial population which increases the level of oxygen in the water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"10.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of water was added to 2.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of 2.5dm<sup>3<\/sup> solution of HCl. What is the concentration of the final solution in mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>?","options":["0.4","8.0","2.0","0.5"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Three drops of a 1.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> solution of HCl was added to 20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a solution of pH6.4. The pH of the resulting solution will be","options":["close to that of pure water","less than 6.4","greater than 6.4","unaltered"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is not a salt?","options":["Aluminium oxide","Sodium hydrogentrioxosulphate (V)","Sodium trioxocarbonate (V)","Zinc chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"An insoluble salt can be prepared by","options":["the reaction of trioxocarbonate (V) with an acid","double decomposition","the action of dilute acid on an insoluble base","the reaction of metals with an acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"2H<sub>2<\/sub>O <sub>(l)<\/sub> + 2F<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 4HF<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>.<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the substance that is being reduced is","options":["O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub>","F<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","HF<sub>(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"In an electrochemical cell, polarization is caused by","options":["chlorine","oxygen","tetaoxsulphate (Vl) acid","hydrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Calculate the volume in cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen evolved as s.t.p. when a current of 5 A is passed through acidified water for 193s<br>\r\n{F = 96500 Cmol<sup>-1<\/sup>, Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p. = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>}","options":["224.000 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.056 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.224 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56.000 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"In an endothermic reaction, if there is a loss in entropy the reaction will","options":["be indeterminate","be spontaneous","not be spontaneous","be at equilibrium"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"the minimum amount of energy required for a reaction to take place is","options":["lattice energy","ionization energy","activation energy","kinetic energy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is a neutral oxide?","options":["Carbon (IV) oxide","Sulphur (Vl) oixide","Sulphur (IV) oxide","Carbon (ll) oxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"In the laboratory preparation of ammonia, the flask is placed in a slanting position so as to","options":["prevent condensed water from breaking the reaction flask","enable the proper mixing of the reactions in the flask","enhance the speed of the reaction","prevent formation of precipitate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the gases is employed as an anaesthesia?","options":["N <sub>2<\/sub>O","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","NO"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Sulphur (IV)oxide is a strong reducing agent in the presence of water due to the formation of","options":["hydroxide ion","sulpgur (Vl)oxide","hydrogen sulhide","trioxosulphate (IV) salt"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A metal that forms soluble trioxosulphate (IV) ion is","options":["barium","potassium","manganese","aluminium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Copper is displaced from the solution of its salts by most metals because it","options":["is a transition element","is at the bottom of the activity series","is very reactive","has completely filled 3d-orbitals"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The coloured nature of transition metal ions are associated with their partially filled","options":["f- orbital","s- orbital","p-orbital","d-orbital"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Aluminium containers are frequently used to transport trioxonitrate (V) acid because aluminium","options":["has a silvery-white appearance","has a low density","does not react with the acid","does not corrode"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"2- methylbutan- 2ol is an example of a","options":["dihydric alkanol","tertiary alkanol","secondary alkanol","primary alkanol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The reaction between ammonia and ethyl ethanoate produces","options":["propanol and ethanamide","propanol and propanamide","ethanol and propanamide","ethanol and ethanamide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The decarboxylation of ethanoic acid will produce carbon (IV)oxide and","options":["methane","ethane","propane","butane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A primary amide is generally represented by the formula","options":["RCOOR","RCONH <sub>2<\/sub>","RCONHR","RCONR <sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following fraction is used as raw material for the cracking process?","options":["kerosine","lubricating oil","bitumen","diesel oils"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"An organic compound contains 60% carbon, 13.3% hydrogen and 26.7% oxygen. Calculate the empirical formula<br>rn(C=12,H =1, O=16)","options":["C <sub>5<\/sub>H <sub>12<\/sub>O","C <sub>3<\/sub>H <sub>8<\/sub>O","C <sub>6<\/sub>H <sub>13<\/sub>O <sub>2<\/sub>","C <sub>4<\/sub>H <sub>9<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"From the diagram above, an ideal gas is represented by","options":["Z","W","X","Y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"In the graph above, the activation energy of the catalyzed reaction is","options":["100KJ","300KJ","250KJ","200KJ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Choose the correct option from the graph above . 3Fe<SUB>(S)<\/SUB> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u21cc Fe<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>4(s)<\/sub>  + 4H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>. The equilibrium constant, K, of the reaction above is represented as","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature for the compound above is","options":["4-methylpent-1-ene","3-methylpent-2-ene","2-methylpent-1ene","2-methylpent-4-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Use the above option to answer this question. The dehydration of ammonium salt of alkanoic acids produces a compound with the general formula","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Use the following option above to answer  this question. Which of the following compounds in solution will turn red litmus paper blue?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The compound above is an","options":["alkanone","alkanoate","alkanal","akanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"How many unpaired electron are in the p-orbitals of a fluorine atom?","options":["3","\\( 0 \\)","1","2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The radioactive emission with the least ionization power is","options":["\\( \\alpha - particles \\)","X-rays","\\( \\gamma -rays \\)","\\( \\beta - rays \\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub> + CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> \\( \\to \\) ZnSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the oxidizing agent is","options":["CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>","ZnSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>","Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>","Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \\( \\iff \\)2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\n\\( \\bigtriangleup H = -395.7kJmol^{-1} \\)<br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the concentration of 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub> can be in creased by","options":["decreasing the pressure","decreasing the temperature","the addition of catalyst","increasing the temperature"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following methods can be used to obtain pure water from a mixture of sand, water and methanoic acid?","options":["netralization with NaOHfoolowed by filtration","neutralization with NaOH followed by distillation","fractional distillation","filtration followed by distillation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"How many atoms are present in 6.0g of magnesium?<br>\r\n[Mg = 24, N<sub>A<\/sub> = 6.02 x 10<sup>23<\/sup> mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["1.20 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>","2.41 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>","1.51 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>","3.02 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of gas was collected over water at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C and 765 mm Hg. Calculate the volume of the gas at s.t.p. if the saturated vapour pressure of water at 10 <sup>o<\/sup>C is 5mm Hg","options":["49.19 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","48.87 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","48.55 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","48.23 cm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An increase in the pressure exerted on gas at a constant temperature results in","options":["a decrease in the number of effective collisions","a decrease in volume","an increase in the average intermolecular distance","an increase in volume"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"2H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub> O<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, what volume of hydrogen would be left over when 300 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen and 1000 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen are exploded in a sealed tube?","options":["200 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","400 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","600 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","700 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"l . Evaporation. ll. Sublimation. lll. Diffusion. IV. Brownian motion.<br>\r\nWhich of the above can correctly be listed as evidences for the particulate nature of matter?","options":["I and lll only","ll and lV only","l, ll and lll only","l, ll, lll and lV"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"If the elements X and Y have atomic numbers 11 and 17 respectively, what type of bond can they form?","options":["Dative","Covalent","Lonic","Metallic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A hydrogen atom which has lost an electron contains","options":["one proton only","one neutron only","one proton and one neutron","one proton, one electron and one neutron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The electronic configuration of Mg <sup>2+<\/sup> is","options":["ls <sup>2<\/sup>2s <sup>2<\/sup>2P <sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3P<sup>2<\/sup>","Is<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2P<sup>6<\/sup>","ls<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>","ls<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2P<sup>4<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Group VII elements are","options":["monoatmic","good oxidizing agents","highly electropositive","electron donors"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following is used to study the arrangement of particles in crystal lattices?","options":["Alpha-particles","Beta-particles","Gamma-rays","X-rays"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"I. It has a varied composition from one place to another. ll. it constituents can be separated by physical means<br>\r\nlll. It contains unreactive noble gases<br>\r\nwhich of the above shows that air is a mixture?","options":["I and ll only","ll and lll only","l and lll only","l,lll and lll"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The chemicals used to soften hard water involves the addition of","options":["insoluble sodium compounds which from soluble solutions of calcium and magesium","solube soudium compounds which from soluble solutions of calcium and magnesium ions","solube sodium compounds which from insoluble precipitates of calcium and magnesium ions","insoluble precipitates of calcium and magnesium ions"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Chlorination of water for town supply is carried out to","options":["make the water colourless","remove germs from the water","make the water tastedful","remove odour from the water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The solubilites  of different solutes in a given solvent can be compared by","options":["plotting their solubility curves on separete axes","plotting their solubility curves on the same axes","plotting some of the solubility curves on the x-axis and others on the y-axis","plotting their solubility curves on the x-axis only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Potassium trioxochlorate (V)has a solubility of 1.5 mol dm <sup>-3<\/sup> at 45 <sup>o<\/sup>C.On cooling this solution to a temperature of 20  <sup>o<\/sup>C, the solubility was found to be 0.5 mol dm <sup>-3<\/sup>. What mass of KCIO <sub>3<\/sub> was crystalized out?<br>\r\n[K = 39, Cl = 35.5 O =16]","options":["1.00g","10.00g","12.25g","122.50g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following pollutants is associated with brain damage?","options":["Carbon (ll) oxide","Radioactive fallout","Biodegradable waste","Sulphus (lV) oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following will produce a solution with pH less than 7 at equivalent point?","options":["HNO <sub>3<\/sub> +NaOH","H <sub>2<\/sub>SO  <sub>4<\/sub> + KOH","HC +Mg (OH) <sub>2<\/sub>","HNO <sub>3<\/sub> + KOH"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The number of hydroxonium ions produced by one molecule of an acid in aqueous solution is its","options":["basicity","acid strength","pH","concentration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"During a titration experiment, 0.05 moles of carbon (lV) oxide is liberated. What is the volume of gas liberated?","options":["22.40 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","11.20 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","2.24 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","1.12 dm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A major factor considered in selecting a suitable method for preparing a simple salt is its","options":["Crystalline from","melting point","reactivity with dilute acids","solubility in water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The oxidation number of boron in NaBH <sub>4<\/sub> is","options":["-3","-1","+1","+3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"2Na <sub>2<\/sub> O <sub>2(s)<\/sub> + 2H <sub>2<\/sub> O <sub>2(1)<\/sub> \u2192 4 NaOH<sub>(s)<\/sub> +O<sub>2(s)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe substance that is oxidized in the reaction above is","options":["2NaO<sub>2(s)<\/sub>","NaOH(aq)","H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub>","O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p>What number of moles of Cu 2+ will be deposited by 360 coulombs of electricity?<br \/>\r\n[f = 96500 C mol -1]<\/p>","options":["5.36 x 10 <sup>-4<\/sup> mole","1. 87 x 10 10 <sup>-3 <\/sup> mole","9. 35 x 10  <sup>-4<\/sup> mole","3. 73 x 10 <sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A metal M displaces zinc from ZnCl, solution, solution<br>\r\nThis shows that","options":["electrons flow from zinc to M","M is more electropositive than zinc","M is more electonegative than zinc","zinc is more electropositive than M"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub> O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nCalculate the standard heat change of the reaction above, if the standard enthalpies of formation of CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> and CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> and CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> in KJ mol <sup>-1<\/sup> are - 394 -242 and - 110 respectively.","options":["+ 262 KJ mol <sup>-1<\/sup>","- 262 KJ mol <sup>-1<\/sup>","+ 42 KJ mol <sup>-1<\/sup>","- 42 KJ mol <sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An increase in entropy can best be illustrated by","options":["mixing of gases","freezing of water","the condensation of vapour","solidifying candle wax"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The highest rate of production of carbon (lV) oxide can be achieved using","options":["0.05 mol  <sup>-3<\/sup>HCI and 5g powdered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","0.05 mol  <sup>-3<\/sup>HCI and 5g lump CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","0.10 mol  <sup>-3<\/sup>HCI and 5g powdered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","0.025 mol  <sup>-3<\/sup>HCI and 5g powdered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A piece of filter paper moistened with lead (ll) ethanoate solution turns black when the paper is dropped into a gas likely to be","options":["sulphur (VI) oxide","hydrogen chloride","sulphur (VI) oxide","hydrogen sulphide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following gases has a characteristic pungent smell, turns red litmus paper blue and forms dense white fumes with hydrogen chloride gas?","options":["N<sub>2<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","CI<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Commercial bleaching can be carried out using","options":["sulphur (IV) oxide and ammonia","hydrogen sulphide and chlorine","chlorine and sulphur (IV) oxide","ammonia and chlorine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Mineral acids are usually added to commercial hydrogen peroxide to","options":["oxidize it","decompose it","minimize its decomposition","reduce it to water and oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will burn with a brick-red colour in a non-luminous Bunsen flame?","options":["LiCI","NaCl","CaClN<sub>2<\/sub>","MgClN<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The purest from of iron which contains only about 0.1% carbon is","options":["pig iron","wrough iron","cast iron","iron pyrite"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A common characteristic between zinc and the other transition elements is the ability to","options":["have variable oxidation states","from complex ions","act as a catalyst","from coloured ions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following metals is the least reactive?","options":["Pb","Sn","Hg","Au"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Geometric isomerism can exist in","options":["hex-3-ene","hexane","prop-l-ene","3-methyl but -l-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Alkanals can be distinguished from alkanones by the reaction with","options":["sudan lll stain","starch iodide paper","lithium tetrahydrido aluminate (lll)","fehling's solution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The isomers of C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>O ARE","options":["1 - propanol and 2 - propanol","1 - propanol and 1 - propanol","2 - propanol and 2 - propanone","2 - propanol and 1 - propanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Carbohydrates are large molecules with the molecular formula C <sub>x<\/sub> (H<sub>2<\/sub>O)<sub>y<\/sub>. In which of the following pairs is x not equal to y?","options":["glucose and starch","maltose and starch","sucrose and fructose","maltose and starch"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A compound contains 40.0% C, 6.7% H 53.3% O. If the molecular mass of the compound is 180, its molecular formula is [C =12, H =1,O]","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The saponification of an alkanoate to produce soap and alkanol involves","options":["dehydration","esterification","hydrolysis","oxidation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"2 - methyl propan -2- ol is an example of a","options":["primary alkanol","secondary alkanol","tertiary alkanol","quartenary alkanol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Ethanol reacts with concentrated tetraoxosulphate (V) acid at a temperature above 170  <sup>o<\/sup>C to form","options":["ethanone","ethene","ethyne","ethanal"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An example of oxidation - reduction enzyme is","options":["amylase","protease","lipase","dehydrogenase"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"What is the concentration of a solution containing 2g of NaOH in 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of solution?<br>\r\n[Na = 23, O = 16, H = 1]","options":["0.40 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.50 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.05 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.30 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following properties is <b>NOT<\/b> peculiar to matter?","options":["kinetic energy of particles increase from solid to gas","Random motion of particles increases from liquid to gas","Orderliness of particles increases from gas to liquid","Random motion of particles increases from gas to solid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"From the diagram above, an ideal can be represented by","options":["M","N","K","L"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following questions is correct about the periodic table?","options":["The non-metallic properties of the elements tend to decrease across  each period","The valence electrons of the elements increase progressively across the period","Elements in the same group have the same numbeer of electron shells","Elements in the same period have the number of valence electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The relative atomic mass of a naturally occurring lithium consisting of 90% Li and 10% Li is","options":["6.9","7.1","6.2","6.8"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An isotope has an atomic number of 15 and a mass number of 31. The number of protons it contain is","options":["16","15","46","31"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The molecular lattice of iodine is held together by","options":["dative bond","metallic bond","hydrogen bond","van der Waal's forces"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The arrangement of particles in crystal lattices can be studied using","options":["X - rays","\u03b3 - rays","\u03b1 - rays","\u03b2 - rays"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"From the diagram above, find the amount of solute deposited when 200 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of the solution is cooled from 55<sup>o<\/sup>C to 40<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["0.10 mole","0.20mole","0.01 mole","0.02 mole"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The importance of sodium aluminate (III) in the treatment of water is to","options":["cause coagulation","neutralize acidity","prevent goitre and tooth decay","kill germs"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"What type of bond exits between an element X with atomic number 12 and Y with atomic number 17?","options":["Electrovalent","Metallic","Covalent","Dative"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Hardness of water is mainly due to the presence of","options":["calcium hydroxide or magnesium hydroxide","calcium trioxocarbonate (IV) or calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","sodium hydroxide or magnesium ydroxide","calcium chloride or sodium chloride salts"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A suitable solvent for iodine and nephthalene is","options":["carbon (IV) sulphide","ethanol","water","benzene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p>Which of the following noble gases is commonly found in the atmosphere?<\/p>","options":["Xenon","Neon","Helium","Argon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u0394H = +ve<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, an increase in temperature will","options":["increase the value of the equilibrium constant","decreases the value of the equilibrium constant","increase in the reactant production","shift the equilibrium to the left"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + OH<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2194 CH<sub>3<\/sub>COO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above ,CH<sub>3<\/sub>COO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> is","options":["conjugate base","acid","base","conjugate acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"How many cations will be produced from a solution of potassium aluminium tetraoxosulphate (VI)?","options":["3","4","1","2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following is <b>NOT<\/b> an alkali?","options":["NH<sub>3<\/sub>","Mg(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","NaOH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An effect of thermal pollution on water bodies is that the","options":["volume of water reduces","volume of chemical waste increase","level of oxides of nitrogen increase","level of oxygen reduces"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following is a deliquescent compound?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","CuO","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>.10H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A chemical reaction which the hydration energy is greater than the lattice energy is referred to as","options":["a spontaneous reaction","an endothermic reaction","an exothermic reaction","a reversible reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The function of zinc electrode in a galvanic cells is that it","options":["undergoes reduction","serves as the positive electrode","production electons","uses up electrons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"CH<sub>4(g)<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CH<sub>3<\/sub> Cl<sub>(s)<\/sub> + HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe major factor that influence the rate of the reaction above is","options":["catalyst","temperature","concentration","light"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The condition required for corrosion to take place is the presence of","options":["water and carbon (IV) oxide","water, carbon (IV) oxide and oxygen","oxygen and carbon (IV) oxide","water and oxygen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The diagram above best illustrates the effect of decrease in","options":["concentration","temperature","surface area","pressure"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"MnO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + Y + 5Fe<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 Mn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 5Fe<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sup>(l)<\/sup><br>\r\nIn the equation above, Y is","options":["5H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>","4H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>","10H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>","8H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Given that M is the mass of a substance deposited during electrolysis and Q is the quantity of electricity consumed, then Faraday's first law can be written as<br>\r\n[Electrochemical equivalent]","options":["M = E\/Q","M = EQ","M = Q\/E","M = E\/2Q"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The impurities formed during the laboratory preparation of chlorine gas are removed by","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","HCl"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The effect of the presence of impurities such as carbon and sulphur on iron is that they","options":["give it high tensile strenght","make it malleable and ductile","increase its melting point","lower its melting point"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A few drops of concentrated HNO<sub>3<\/sub> is added to an unknown solution and boiled for a while. If this produces a brown solution, the cation presents is likely to be","options":["Pb<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The bleaching action of chlorine gas is effective due to the presence of","options":["hydrogen chloride","water","air","oxygen"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"In the laboratory preparation of oxygen, dried oxygen is usually collected over","options":["hydrochloric acid","mercury","calcium chloride","tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The property of concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> that makes it suitable for preparing HNO<sub>3<\/sub> is its","options":["boiling point","density","oxidizing properties","dehydrating properties"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Bronze is preferred to copper in the making of medals because it","options":["is stronger","can withstand low temperature","is lighter","has low tensile strength"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The constituents of baking powder that makes the dough to rise is","options":["NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaOH","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaCl"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The ability of carbon to form long chains is referred to as","options":["alkylation","acylation","catenation","carbonation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will undergo polymerization reaction?","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The compound above exhibits","options":["geometric isomerism","optical isomerism","structural isomerism","positional isomerism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An organic compound has an empirical formula CH<sub>2<\/sub>O and vapour density of 45.<br>\r\nWhat is the molecular formula?<br>\r\n[C = 12, H = 1, O = 16]","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"At 25<sup>o<\/sup> and zymase as catalyst, <br>\r\nC<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub><sub>6<\/sub> \u2192 2C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH + 2CO<sub>2<\/sub> + energy<br>\r\nThe reaction above represented by the equation above is useful in the production of","options":["propanol","butanol","methanol","ethanol"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The number of isomers that can be obtained from C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> is","options":["3","4","1","2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The functional groups present in the compound above are","options":["alkene and halo-group","hydroxyl and chloro-group","alkene and chloro-group","hydroxyl and halo-group"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Two organic compounds K and L were treated with a few drops of Fehling's solutions respectively . K formed a brick-red precipitate while L, remains unaffected. The compound K is an","options":["alkanol","alkane","alkanal","alkanone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true about 2-methylpropane and butane","options":["They are members of the same homologous series","They have the same boiling point","They have different number of carbon atoms","They have the same chemical properties"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"with conc H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> as catalyst<br>\r\nCH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH + C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH \u2192 CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","options":["esterification","Condensation","saponification","neutralization"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"In the diagram above , X is the ``","options":["enthalpy","enthalpy change","activation energy","activated complex"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The compound above exhibits","options":["geometric isomerism","optical isomerism","structural isomerism","positional isomerism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"choose the correct answer in the option above. Which of the following is a primary amine?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The principle of column chromatography is based on the ability of the constituents to","options":["move at different speeds in the column","dissolve in each other in the column","react with the solvent in the column","react with each other in the column"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following is an example of a mixture?","options":["Common salt","Blood","Sand","Washing soda"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Calculate the percentage by mass of nitrogen in calcium trioxonitrate (V) <br>\r\n[Ca = 40, N = 14, O = 16]","options":["8.5%","13.1%","17.1%","27.6%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The droplets of water observed around a bottle of milk taken out of the refrigerator is due to the fact that the","options":["water vapour in the air around the bottle gains some energy from the bottle","temperature of the milk drops as it loses heat into the surroundings","saturated vapour pressure of the milk is equal to the atmospheric pressure","water vapour in the air around the bottle loses some of its energy to the bottle"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The volume of a given gas is <i>V<\/i> cm<sup>3<\/sup> <i>P<\/i> mm Hg. what is the new volume of the gas if the pressure is reduced to half at constant temperature","options":["4 <i>V<\/i> cm<sup>3<\/sup>","2 <i>V<\/i> cm<sup>3<\/sup>","<i>V<\/i>\/2 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","<i>V<\/i> cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Moving from left to right across a period, the general rise in the first ionization energy can be attributed to the","options":["decrease in nuclear charge","increase in nuclear charge","decrease in screening effect","increase in screening effect"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"How many unpaired electron(s) are there in the nitrogen sub-levels\/","options":["3","2","1","none"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The stability of the noble gases is due to the fact that they","options":["have no electron in their outermost shells","have duplet or octet electron configurations","belong to group zero of the periodic table","are volatile in nature"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The maximum number of electrons in the L shell of an atom is","options":["2","8","18","32"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Elements in the same period in the periodic table have the same","options":["number of shells","atomic number","chemical properties","physical properties"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<sub>1<\/sub><sup>2<\/sup>D + <sub>1<\/sub><sup>3<\/sup>T \u2192 <sub>2<\/sub><sup>4<\/sup>He + <sub>0<\/sub><sup>1<\/sup>n + energy<br>\r\nThe reaction above illustrates","options":["alpha decay","artificial transmutation","nuclear fussion","nuclear fission"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A noble gas with a high power of fog penetration used in aerodrome beacons is","options":["krpton","argon","helium","neon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Permanent hardness of water can be removed by","options":["filtration","adding slaked lime","adding caustic soda","boiling"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Substance employed as drying agents are usually","options":["amphoteric","hydroscopic","efflorescent","acidic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Calculate the solubility in mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of 40g of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> dissolved in 100g of water at 120<sup>o<\/sup>C.<br>\r\n[Cu = 64, S = 32, O = 16]","options":["4.00","2.50","0.40","0.25"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Coffee stains can best be removed by","options":["Kerosine","turpentine","a solution of borax in water","ammonia solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Carbon (II) oxide is considered dangerous if inhaled mainly because it","options":["can cause injury to the nervous system","competes with oxygen in the blood","competes with carbon (IV) oxide in the blood","can cause lung cancer"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The acid that is used to remove rust is","options":["boric","hydrochloric","trioxonitrate (V)","tetraoxosulphate (VI)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Calculate the volume of 0.5 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> H<sub>2<\/sub>So<sub>4<\/sub> that is neutralized by 25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> NaOH","options":["5.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.5 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.4 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.1 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The colour of methyl orange in alkaline medium is","options":["yellow","pink","orange","red"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following salts is slightly soluble in water?","options":["AgCl","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","PbCl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"6AgNO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + PH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 6Ag<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + 6HNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the above reaction, the reducing agent is","options":["HNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub>","PH<sub>3(g)<\/sub>","AgNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of the compound LiAlH<sub>4<\/sub> is","options":["lithiumtetrahydridoaluminate (III)","aluminium tetrahydrido lithium","tetrahydrido lithium aluminate (III)","lithium aluminium hydride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Iron can be protected from corrosion by coating the surface with","options":["gold","silver","copper","zinc"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"What quantity  of aluminium is deposited when a current of 10A is passed through a solution of an aluminium salt for 1930s?<br>\r\n[Al = 27, F = 96500 C mol <sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.2 g","1.8 g","5.4 g","14.2 g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In which of the following is the entropy change positive?","options":["Thermal  dissociation of ammonium chloride","Reaction between an acid and a base","Addition of concentrated acid to water","Dissolution of sodium metal in water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"If a reaction is exothermic and there is a great disorder, it means that","options":["the reaction is static","the reaction is in a state of equilibrium","there will be a large increase in free energy","there will be a large decrease in free energy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In the preparation of oxygen by heating KClO<sub>3<\/sub> in the presence of MnO<sub>2<\/sub>, only moderate heat is needed because the catalyst acts by","options":["lowering the pressure of the reaction","increasing the surface area of the reactant","increase the rate of the reaction","lowering the energy barrier of the reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The graph above demonstrate the effect of","options":["surface area on the rate of reaction","catalyst on the rate of reaction","pressure on the rate reaction","concentration on the rate of reaction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"2H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u0394H = -ve<br>\r\nwhat happens to the equilibrium constant of the reaction above if the temperature is increased?","options":["it is unaffected","it becomes zero","it decrease","it increase"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"To a solution of an unknown compound, a little dilute tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid was added with some freshly prepared iron (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI) solution. The brown ring observed after the addition of a stream of concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid confirmed the presence of","options":["CO<sup>-<\/sup>","Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","SO<sup>-<\/sup>","NO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following is used in rocket fuels?","options":["HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","HCl"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A constituent common to bronze and solder is","options":["lead","silver","copper","tin"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"When iron is exposed to moist air, it gradually rusts. This is due to the formation of","options":["hydrate iron (III) oxide","anhydrous iron (III) oxide","anhydrous iron (II) oxide","hydrate iron (II) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A compound gives an orange-red colour to non-luminous flame. This compound is likely to contain","options":["Na<sup>+<\/sup>","Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Stainless steel is used for making","options":["magnets","tools","coins and medals","moving parts of clocks"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The residual solids from the fractional distillation of petroleum are used as","options":["coatings of pipes","raw materials for the cracking process","fuel for the driving tractors","fuel for jet engines"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of the compound above is","options":["4 - ethyloctane","5 - ethyloctane","5 - propylheptane","3 - propylheptane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following is used as fuel in miners' lamp?","options":["Ethanal","Ethyne","Ethene","Ethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following organic compounds is very soluble in water?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Benzene reacts with hydrogen in the presence of nickel catalyst at 180<sup>o<\/sup>C to give","options":["xylene","toluene","cyclopentane","cyclohexane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following is used to hasten the ripening of fruit?","options":["Ethene","Ethanol","Ethyne","Ethane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The final products of the reaction between methane and chlorine in the presence of ultraviolet light are hydrogen chloride and","options":["tricloromethane","dichloromethane","tetrachloromethane","chloromethane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The correct order of increasing boiling points of the following compounds C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH, C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub> and C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> is","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH \u2192 C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH","C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH \u2192 C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>OH \u2192 C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"One of the major uses of alkane is","options":["as domestic and industrial fuel","in the hydrogenation of oils","in the textile industries","in the production of plastics"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The haloalkanes used in dry-cleaning industries are","options":["trichloromethane and tetrachloromethane","chloroethene and dichloroethene","trichloroethene and tetrachloroethene","chloroethane and dichloroethene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Two hydrocarbons X and Y were treated with bromine water. X decolorised the solution and Y did not not. Which class of compound does Y belong?","options":["Benzene","Alkynes","Alkenes","Alkanes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The compound that is used as an anaesthetic is","options":["CCl<sub>4<\/sub>","CH Cl<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>Cl"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In the diagram above, the purpose of the asbestos to","options":["absorb impurities","catalyze the reaction","solidify the gas","dry the gas"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In the diagram above, the gas produced is","options":["NO","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A mixture of sugar and sulphur can be separated by","options":["dissolution in water, evapouration and filtration","filtration, evaporation and dissolution in water","dissolution in water, filtration and evaporation","evaporation, dissolution in water and filtration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following is a physical change?","options":["Freezing ice cream","dissolving calcium in water","burning kerosene","Exposing white phosphorus to air"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The percentage of water of crystallization in ZnSO<sub>4<\/sub>.7H<sub>2<\/sub>O is<br>\r\n[Zn = 65, S = 32, O = 1, H = 1]","options":["33%","44%","55%","87%"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"0.0075 mole of calcium trioxocarbonate (IV) is added to 0.015 mole of a solution of hydrochloric acid. The volume of gas evolved at s.t.p is <br>\r\n[Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["224cm<sup>3<\/sup>","168cm<sup>3<\/sup>","112cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A gas exerts pressure on its container because","options":["the molecules of a gas collide with the walls of the container","some of the molecules are moving faster than others","of the collisions of the molecules with each other","of the mass of the molecules of the gas"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The basic assumption in the kinetic theory of gases that the collisions of the gaseous molecules are perfectly elastic implies that the","options":["forces of attraction and repulsion are in equilibrium","gaseous molecules can occupy any available space","gaseous molecules will continue their motion indefinitely","gases can be compressed"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"If an atom is represented as \\( _{11}^{23}X \\), which of the following deduction is correct?","options":["it contains 12 protonic","it forms a covalent chloride","its atomic number is 23","it is an alkali metal"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Cathode rays causes an object placed behind a perforated anode to cast a shadow on the screen. This observation shows that the rays","options":["are positively charged","are negatively charged","have mass","travel in straight lines"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which quantum number divides shells into orbitals?","options":["principal","Arzimuthal","Magnetic","Spin"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The type of bonding in {Cu(NH<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>4<\/sub>}<sup>2+<\/sup> is","options":["coordinate","electrovalent","metallic","covalent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The mixture of gases used in a photographer's flash tube is","options":["argon and krypton","krypton and xenon","helium and argon","argon and xenon"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"When sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) decahydrate loses its water of crystallization to the atmosphere, the process is","options":["deliquescence","efflorescence","hygroscopic","effervesecence"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Water can be obtained as the only product during the","options":["combustion of hydrocarbons","neutraliization of an acid by base","combustion of hydrogen","electrolysis of brine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"If 10.5g of lead (II) trioxonitrate (V) is dissolved in 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of distilled water at 18<sup>o<\/sup>C, the solubility of the solute in mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> is<br>\r\n[Pb = 207, N = 14, O = 16]","options":["1.60","5.25","16.00","525.00"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"For a given solute, the concentration of its saturated solution in different solvents are","options":["the same at the same temperature","different at the same temperature","the same at different temperature","constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The major source of oxides of nitrogen is from the burning of","options":["coal","wood","fuel","chlrofluorocarbons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The acid used in electrolysis of water is dilute","options":["HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","HCl"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"What volume of 1.5M solution of KOH would contain 0.045 moles","options":["67.50 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","30.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.75 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","3.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The salt formed from a reaction between citric acid and sodium hydroxide in solution will be","options":["acidic","basic","complex","neutral"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The colour changes observed when testing for reducing agents using acidified potassium heptaoxodichromate (IV) solution is","options":["yellow to purple","orange to green","green to orange","purple to yellow"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The oxidation state of Cr in K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> is","options":["+7","+6","+5","4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following metals is purified commercially by electrolysis?","options":["Zn","Fe","Sn","Cu"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"What current will deposit 3.25g of zinc in 2hrs?<br>\r\n[Zn = 65, F = 96500 mol<sup>-<\/sup>]","options":["3.25A","2.00A","1.34A","0.67A"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n\u0394G for the reaction above at 1300k is -43KJ. At this temperature, the reaction is","options":["not feasible","at equilibrium","feasible","exothermic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Two equal bulbs, one containing ammonia and the other nitrogen are opened mouth - to - mouth to each other at room temperature. The entropy in the mixture of gases is likely to","options":["remain unchange","increase","decrease","change"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"In the diagram above, which of the curves represents the evolution of oxygen with time in the equation 2KClO<sub>3(s)<\/sub> \u2192 2KCl<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 3O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>?","options":["X","Y","Z","R"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A catalyst increase the rate of a chemical reaction by providing a path that","options":["raise the activiation energy","increase the temperature","lowers the activation energy","increase the concentration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"CuO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub><br>\r\nWhat is the effect of increasing the pressure on the equilibrium reaction above?","options":["The equilibrium is shifted to the left","The equilibrium is shifted to the right","There is no effect","More H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> is produced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The equilibrium of an endothermic reaction which proceeds with an increase in volume can be shifted in the reverse direction by","options":["increasing the temperature and decreasing the pressure","increasing the pressure and increasing the temperature","decreasing the temperature and increasing the pressure","decreasing the pressure and decreasing the temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The oxidation of ammonia in excess air produces","options":["NO","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Hydrogen sulphide gas can act as","options":["an oxidizing agent","a dehydrating agent","a bleaching agent","a precipitating agent"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The gasification of coke is used for the manufacturing of","options":["producer gas","natural gas","synthetic gas","industrial gas"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The gas that is most useful in protecting humans against solar radiation is","options":["chlorine","ozone","carbon (IV) oxide","hydrogen sulphide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following allotrope of carbon is a constituent of a lead pencil?","options":["Graphite","Diamond","Lampblack","Soot"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"which of the following metals will show the highest metallic character?","options":["Zinc","Copper","Barium","Calcium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Copper metal dissolves in concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid with the resultant evolution of","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The type of iron that is best suited for welding, making nails, chains and iron rods is","options":["pig iron","wrought iron","cast iron","iron pyrites"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"In the electrolytic extraction of aluminum, the function of the molten cryolite is to","options":["precipitate aluminium hdroxide","lower the melting point of aluminium oxide","act as a raw materials","act as a solvent"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"One of the products of the thermal decomposition of sodium trioxonitrate (V) is","options":["sodium","nitrogen","sodium dioxonitrate (III)","sodium oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A cracking process in petroleum refining can be represented by","options":["heptane to heptene","heptane to 3-methylhexane","heptane to propene and butane","heptane to 2,3,3-trimethybutane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following molecules has two other positional isomers?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>Br","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CHBrCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CBr<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHBrCH<sub>2<\/sub>Br"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following class of compounds can exist as dipolar ions in solution?","options":["Alkanoic acid","Fatty acids","Dialkanoic acids","Amino acids"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Lucas reagent is used to test for","options":["alkanes","alkanoic acids","alkanols","amines"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A compound commonly used for sterilization and preservation of specimens and food is","options":["ethanol","benzene","ether","ammonia"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An organic compound reacted with bromine water to give a colourless solution. The compound is probably an","options":["alkene","alkanal","alkyne","alkanone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following hydrocarbons is mainly used as fuel?","options":["Methylene","Ethylene","Methane","Ethyne"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The molecular formula of a common organic laboratory anaesthetic is","options":["CHCl<sub>3<\/sub>","CHI<sub>3<\/sub>","CCl<sub>4<\/sub>","CHF<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The simplest branched-chain hydrocarbon is","options":["ethane","ethene","propane","butane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Organic molecules that have the suffix-ene are unsaturated hydrocarbons that have","options":["a single bond","a double bond","a triple bond","an ionic bond"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"If the relative molecular mass of an element is not a whole number, it can be deduced that the element is","options":["Naturally radioactive","abundant in nature","a transition metal","an isotopic mixture"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Chlorophyll obtained from given leaves of plant can be shown to be composed of more than one coloured component by the technique of","options":["crystallization","hydrolysis","chromatography","sublimation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In countries where the temperature falls below 273K, salt is always sprinkled on the icy road in order to","options":["lower the melting point of the ice","increase the density of the ice","make the ice impure","raise the melting point of the ice"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"2Na<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192  2NaOH<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nFrom the equation above, calculate the mass of sodium hydroxide produced by 2.3g of sodium.<br>\r\n[H = 1, O = 16, Na = 23]","options":["0.40g","0.80g","4.00g","8.00g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"16.8 g of sodium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (IV) is completely decomposed by heat. Calculate the volume of carbon(IV) oxide given off s.t.p <br>\r\n[Na 23, C = 12, O = 16, H = 1, Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["22.40 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.20 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.24 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.12 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"300 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of gas has a pressure of 800 mmHg. If the pressure is reduced to 650 mmHg, find its volume","options":["243.75 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","369.23 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","738.46 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1733.36 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Diffusion is slowest in solid particles than in particles of liquid and gases because","options":["solid particles have more kinetic energy than the particles of liquid and gases","solid particles have less kinetic energy than the particles of liqiud and gases","solid particles have less restriction in their movement than liquid and gas particles","the particles in solids are far apart and the cohesive forces between them are negligible"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The experiment that showed that atoms have tiny positively charged nucleus was first carried out by","options":["Moseley","Rutherford","Millikan","Dalton"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The atom of an element X is represented as <sub>z<\/sub><sup>y<\/sup>X. The basic chemical properties of X depends on the value of","options":["Y","Z","Y - Z","Z - Y"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The diagram above represent the electron sub-level for","options":["carbon","nitrogen","oxygen","flourine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In the periodic table, the electrical and thermal conductivities are properties of elements that","options":["decrease across the period and increase down the group","increase across the period and decrease down the group","decrease across the period and down the group`","increase acrosss the period and down the group"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"\\( _{11} ^{11}Na + _0^1n \u2192 _{11}^{24}Na \\)<br>\r\nThe reaction above is an example of","options":["nuclear fission","nuclear fusion","artificial transmutation","beta decay"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Air boiled out of water as steam is richer in","options":["nitrogen and oxygen","carbon (IV) oxide and oxygen","noble gases and carbon (IV) oxide","oxygen and noble gases"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In the course of purifying water for town supply the water is passed through large settlings tanks, containing sodium aluminate (III) to remove","options":["large particles","germs","fine particles","odour"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"When a few drops of water is added to a blue anhydrous cobalt (II) chloride, the colour changes to","options":["white","pink","red","blue"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The vulcanizer's solution is prepared by dissolving rubber in","options":["ethanol","kerosine","benzene","petrol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"117.0g of sodium chloride was dissolved in the solubility in 1.0dm<sup>3<\/sup> of distilled water at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C. Determine the solubility in mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of sodium chloride at that temperature <br>\r\n[Na = 23, Cl = 35.5]","options":["1.0","2.0","3.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The uncovered raw food that is sold along major roads is likely to contain some amounts of","options":["Pb","Cu","Ag","Na"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"What is the pH of 0.001 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> solution of sodium hydroxide","options":["14","13","12","11"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The basicity of CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH is","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"0.05 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> HCl is neutralized by 25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> NaOH. If the volume of acid used is 32.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>, what is the concentration  of the base","options":["0.016 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.032 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.039 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.064 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Insoluble salts can be prepared by","options":["titrating an alkali against an appropriate acid","reacting an acid with trioxocarbonatr (IV) salt","directing combination of the elements which make up the salt","mixing two soluble compounds containing the metallic radical and the acidic radical"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The oxidation state of carbon in HCOOH is","options":["-1","+2","+3","zero"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"What is the IUPAC nomenclature of the compound NaCIO?","options":["sodium oxochlorate (I)","sodium chloro (I) oxide","sodium monooxochlorate (II)","sodium chloro (I) monoxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In recharging a lead-acid accumulator, the reaction at the cathode can be represented as","options":["Pb<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + SO<sup>2-<\/sup><sub>4(aq)<\/sub> \u2192PbSO<sub>4(s)<\/sub>","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 2e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192Pb<sub>(s)<\/sub>","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 PbO<sub>2(s)<\/sub> + 4H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4e<sup>-<\/sup>","Pb<sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2192 Pb<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 2e<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"If a given quantity of electricity liberates 0.65g of Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>, what amount of Hg<sup>2+<\/sup> would be liberated by the same quantity of current?<br>\r\n[Zn = 65, Hg = 201]","options":["1.00g","2.10g","4.02g","8.04g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + HCl<sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2192 NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl<sub>(s)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe entropy change in the system above is","options":["positive","zero","negative","indeterminate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following reaction is endothermic?","options":["C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","CaO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 Ca(OH)<sub>2(s)<\/sub>","C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + NaOH<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 NaCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A catalyst speeds up the rate of chemical reaction by","options":["taking part in the reaction","increasing the activation energy of the reaction","lowering the activation energy of the reaction","increasing the heat content"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The rate of a reaction usually decrease in the concentration of reactants because","options":["kinetic energy decrease","temperature increase","speed increases","reactants collision decrease"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The substance that is used in  the steel industry for the removal of carbon, sulphur and phosphorus impurities from pig iron is","options":["oxygen","chlorine","nitrogen","hydrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds of trioxonitrate (V) will decomposes to give dinitrogen (i) oxide and water when heated?","options":["NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","Zn(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","Cu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>NO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"When a solution of ammonium trioxocarbonate (IV) is added to a solution of an unknown salt, a white precipitate which is soluble in dilute hydrochloric acid but insoluble in ethanoic acid is formed. This indicates the presence of","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Na<sup>+<\/sup>","Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>","K<sup>+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Leads is used for making bullets and lead shots because of its","options":["resistance to corrosion","low melting point","high density","flexibility"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"which of the following gives a precipitate when treated with NaOH solution?","options":["AlCl<sub>3<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The most common ores of iron include","options":["haematite, malachite and limonite","chalcolite, calamine and bornite","magnetite, haematite and bornite","magnetite, chalcolite and bornite"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The type of isomerism shown by cis- and trans- isomers is","options":["optical isomerism","positional isomerism","functional isomerism","geometrical isomerism"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"If the silver mirror test is positive, it indicates the presence of an","options":["alkyne","alkanol","alkanone","alkanal"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"If glucose is heated with concentration tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid, it will be dehydrated to","options":["carbon","carbon (IV) oxide","ethene","ethanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature for the structure above is","options":["2, 3 - dichloro - 4, 4, 5 - trimethyl pent - 2 - ene","4, 5 - dichloro - 2, 3 - dimethyl hex - 2 - ene","2, 3 - dichloro - 4, 4 - dimethyl hex - 2- ene","2, 3 dichloro - 2, 2 - dimethyl hex - 2 - ene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A hydrocarbon X with a molar mass of 26 consists of 92.3% carbon. What is its molecular formular","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A red precipitate of copper (I) carbide is formed when ammonium solution of copper (I) chloride is introduced into","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CH - CH<sub>2<\/sub> - CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> - C \u2261 CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> - C  C - CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Reduction of  nitroalkanes, nitrites and amides is a route for the preparation of","options":["amines","alkenes","polymers","detergents"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Reduction of alkanonoes with LialH<sub>4<\/sub> produces","options":["primary alkanols","secondary alkanols","tertiary alkanols","polyhydric alkanols"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The product obtained when a mixture of benzene vapour and hydrogen are passed over nickel catalyst at 180<sup>o<\/sup>C is","options":["cyclohexane","cyclopentane","n- hexane","n - pentane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Polyvinyl chloride is used in the production of","options":["glass","alloy","pipes","ceramics"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Detergents are manufactured with straight hydrocarbon chains so as to make them","options":["soluble","biodegradable","cheaper","foamy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Use the diagram to answer this question. The gas that can be used to demonstrate the experiment is","options":["hydrogen chloride","hydrogen sulphide","nitrogen(ll) oxide","dinitrogen (l) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Use the diagram to answer this question.The colour of the fountain water is","options":["blue","orange","red","yellow"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Choose the correct option from the structure above","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Trioxonitrate (V) acid is not used for preparing hydrogen gas from metals because it","options":["is strongly oxidizing","is volatile","renders the metal passive","forms a layer of oxide on the metal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"An element used in the production of matches is","options":["nitrogen","aluminium","copper","sulphur"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"When calcium oxide is heated with carbon, the oxide will","options":["be converted to carbide","be converted to the trioxocarbonate (IV) salt","decompose to the metal","melt,producingg carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A solution which on treatment with hydrochloric acid produces a colourless, odourless gas which turns lime water milky is most likely to be a","options":["trioxonitrate (V)","chloride","trioxocarbonate (IV)","hydroxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The soft solder used for welding and plumbing is alloy of","options":["lead and tin","iron and tin","lead and zinc","iron and zinc"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The reddish-brown rust on iron roofing sheets consists of","options":["Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>(H<sub>2<\/sub>O)<sub>6<\/sub>","FeO.H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>.3H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Fe<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>.2H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Na<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(aq)<\/sub> + 2HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 2NaCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub><br>\r\nWhich of the following would introduce the greatest increase in the rate of the chemical reaction above?","options":["An increase in temperature and decrease in the concentration of the reactant","A decrease in the volume and increase in the pressure of the reactant","A decrease in the temperature and an incease in the concentration of the reactant","An increase in temperature and an increase in the concentration of the reactant"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The tincture of iodine means iodine dissolved in","options":["ethanol","bromine chloride","chlorine water","water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Cu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> \u2194 [Cu(NH<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>4<\/sub>]<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, what is the effect of precipitating Cu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> as CuS<sub>(s)<\/sub>?","options":["NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> concentration will decrease","more NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub will be generated","The equilibrium will shift to the right","There will be no effect"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Copper and silver metals are commonly use as coin because they are","options":["easily reduced","not easily reduced","easily oxidized","not easily oxidized"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following sets of metals dissolves in dilute HCl?","options":["Fe, Sn and Cu","Mg, Fe and Cu","Mg, Sn and Fe","Cu, Mg and Sn"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"If chlorine is bubbled into water and the resulting yellowish-green  solution is exposed to bright sunlight for a while, the solution will decompose giving out","options":["oxygen and leaving behind aqueous hydrochloric acid","chlorine and oxygen","oxygen, hydrogen and chlorine","oxygen, thereby producing hypochlorous acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2194 H<sub>2<\/sub>PO<sub>4<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> <br>\r\n\u0394H = -13kJ at 298K<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, an increase in temperature would","options":["slow downthe reverse reaction","have no effect on the reaction","favour the reverse reaction","favour the forward reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The reaction that takes place in Daniell cell is","options":["direct combination","redox","double decomposition","neutralization"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"What happens when zinc rod is immersed in copper (II) tetraoxosulphate  (VI) solution\/","options":["The blue colour of the solution disappears","Electrons flow from copper to zinc","The zinc rod remain undissolved","The copper generate more copper ions"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6(g)<\/sub> \u0394H = -137kJ mol<sub>-1<\/sub><br>\r\nThe reaction represented above is","options":["exothermic","spontaneous","endothermic","in equilibrium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"How long would it take to deposit 0.08g of copper from CuCl<sub>2<\/sub> solution by passing a current of 0.5A?<br>\r\n[Cu = 64, F = 96500 C mol<sub>-1<\/sub>]","options":["6 mins","8 mins","24 mins","48 mins"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"tartaric acid is used industrially to","options":["make baking powder","make fruit juices","remove rust","dry substance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The salt formed from strong acid and a strong base is","options":["complex","neutral","basic","acidic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Dissolving some pellets of NaOH in water would result in","options":["a decrease in the free energy of the solution","a decrease in the entropy of the solution","a lowering of the temperature of te solution","an increase in the entropy of the solution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Calculate the number of moles of HCl present in 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 0.75M solution of the acid","options":["0.015 mole","0.038 mole","3.800 moles","1.500 moles"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The oxidation state of oxygen in tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid is","options":["-4","-2","+4","-8"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"MnO<sub>2(s)<\/sub> + <i>x<\/i>HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 MnCl<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + <i>y<\/i>H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> + <i>z<\/i>Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn theequation above, what are the values of <i>x<\/i>, <i>y<\/i> and <i>z<\/i> respectively","options":["2, 1, 2","4, 1, 2","4, 2, 1","1, 2, 1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Calculate the mass of chlorine gas which occupies a volume of 1.12dm<sup>3<\/sup> at s.t.p<br>\r\n[Cl = 35.5, molar volume of gas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","options":["15.50 g","7.10 g","3.55 g","1.80 g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which experiment led to the measurement of the charge on an electron?","options":["Mass spectrometric experiment","Oil-drop experiment","Scattering \u03b1 - particles","Discharge-tube experiment"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"What is the volume of oxygen required to burn complete 45 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of methane at s.t.p?","options":["135.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","180.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","45.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","90.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"How many electrons are in the L shell of <sup>31<\/sup><sub>15<\/sub>P?","options":["5","8","18","2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"If the electron configuration of a element is p1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2P<sup>5<\/sup>, how many unpaired electron are there?","options":["2","8","1","4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following decrease when a given mass of gas is compressed to half its initial volume?","options":["Atomic radius of each","Average intermolecular distance","Frequency of collisions","Number of molecules presents"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"the elements that belong to the third period of the periodic table are","options":["Li, Be, Al and P","Na, P, O and Cl","B, C, N and O","Nz, Mg, S and Ar"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A metal <b>X<\/b> forms two bromides with the formulae XBr<sub>2<\/sub> and XBr<sub>3<\/sub>. What type of bonding exists between <b>X<\/b> and bromine in the bromide?","options":["Ionic bonding","Metallic bonding","Dative bonding","Covalent bonding"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A mixture of petrol and water can be separated through","options":["centrifugation","distillation","the use of separating funnel","the use of filter paper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following represents an aromatic compound?","options":["C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>9<\/sub>OH","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>Cl + KCN \u2192 CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CN + KCl<br><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the cyanide is","options":["hydrophobic","hydrophilic","nucleophilic","electrophilic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is the best possible anti-knock agent for petrol?","options":["(CH<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>CH - CH(CH<sub>3<\/sub>)CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>(CH<sub>3<\/sub>)CHCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>(CH<sub>3<\/sub>)CHCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","(CH<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>C - CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The hydrocarbon used in the production of styrene is","options":["ethyne","propyne","ethane","ethene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"How many structural isomers of chlorobutane are possible?","options":["4","3","2","1"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The conversion of open chain alkanes into cycloalkanes and aromatic compounds is called","options":["cracking","reforming","isomerization","polymerization"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following alkanes has the highest boiling point?","options":["Pentane","Ethane","Propane","Methane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Certain useful waxes are composed mainly of","options":["amino acids","glycerols","alkanols","alkanoates"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of compound CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>COOCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub> is","options":["propyl ethanoate","ethyl butanoate","ethyl propanoate","methyl butanoate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"When temporary hard water is boiled for sometime in a kettle, the inner surface of the kettle becomes coated with a deposit of","options":["calcium tetraoxosulphate(VI)","calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)","calcium hydrogentrioxocarbonate (IV)","aluminium trioxocarbonate (IV)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A supersaturated solution is said to contain","options":["more solute than it can dissolve at that temperature in the presence of undissolved solute","as much solute as it can dissolve at that temperature  in the presence of undissolved solute","as much solute as it can dissolve at that temperature","more solute than it can dissolve at that temperature"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The presence of nitrogen in air is to slow down","options":["respiration and combustion","combustion and corrosion","corrosion and respiration","respiration and transpiration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A good drying agent should be","options":["deliquescent","effervescent","hygroscopic","efflorescent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Smog usually occurs over cities which","options":["burn a lot of fossil fuels","have very few plants","are surrounded by water","are overpopulated"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"What weight of NaCl is needed to make 2.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 1.5M solution? <br>\r\n[Na = 23, Cl = 35.5]","options":["116 g","175 g","87 g","58 g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The raw materials used for the smelting of iron ore in a furnace is","options":["CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>","Zn(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"On heating, which of the following compounds will decompose to the free metal, nitrogen (IV) oxide and oxygen?","options":["Ca(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","Cu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub","AgNO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The group IA metals are not found free in nature because they","options":["are very reactive and unstable","are malleable and ductile","have high  melting and boiling point","conduct heat and electricity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Carbon exist naturally in the combined state as","options":["graphite","coal","diamond","wood"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The efficiency of a solid catalyst to increase reaction rates depends on its","options":["surface area","solubility","concentration","quantity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Dynamic equilibrium describes a situation where","options":["a reaction gives back the reactant","te concentration of the reactant and products is equal","both forward and and reverse reactions proceed at the same rate","reactants are converted to products"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The ion that will give a white precipitate with aqueous NaOH and soluble in excess of the base is","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs of substance will react further with oxygen to form a higher oxide?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NO and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and NO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The characteristic colour of the flame shown when a copper sail moistened with concentrated hydrochloric acid on a platinum wire is put on bunsen burner is","options":["lilac","green","yellow","brick-red"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In the industrial production of H<sub>2<\/sub> from natural gas the CO<sub>2<\/sub> produced along with the H<sub>2<\/sub> is removed by","options":["washing under pressure","drying over phosphorus (V) oxide","passing the mixture into lime water","using ammonical copper (I) chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The sulphide which is insoluble in dilute hydrochloric acid is","options":["FeS","CuS","ZnS","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following typically represents a photochemical reaction?","options":["Formation of water from hydrogen and oxygen molecules","Conversion of dinitrogen (IV) oxide to nitrogen (IV) oxide","Decomposition of calcium hydroxide to its oxide","Conversion of silver halides to grey metallic silver"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The gas obtained as a product of anaerobic action on organic matter buried in the earth is","options":["ethene","methane","carbon (IV) oxide","nitrogen (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Nigerian crude oil is described as light crude because of its","options":["low sulphur content","high natural gas content","high octane number","low aliphatic-hydrocarbon content"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An example of aliphatic unsaturated hydrocarbon is","options":["pentane","butanol","propene","benzene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following has an isomer?","options":["C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub> - CH<sub>2<\/sub> - C CH<br>\r\nThe hybridization in the compound above is","options":["Sp<sup>2<\/sup>","sp","sp<sup>3<\/sup> and sp<sup>2<\/sup>","sp<sup>3<\/sup> and sp"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"One mole of a hydrocarbon contains 36g of carbon and its vapour density is 20. The structure of the hydrocarbon is","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>C \u2261 CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH = CH<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>C \u2261 CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An emulsion may be produced by shaking a detergent solution with","options":["palm wine","ethanoic acid","palm oil","water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The products of the combustion of candle wax are","options":["hydrogen and water","oxygen and water","carbon (IV) oxide and water","carbon (II) oxide and water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"When 50cm<sup>2<\/sup> of a saturated solution of sugar of molar mass 342 g at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C was evaporated to dryness, 34.2g of dry solid was obtained. The solubility of sugar at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C is","options":["2.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.5 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","7.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","10.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following results in the fall of acid rain?","options":["Oxides of lead","Particulate matter","Oxides of sulphur","Gaseous hydrocarbon"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Water has the ability to dissolve almost all substance because its molecules has a structure with","options":["one positive end and one neutral end","one positive end and one negative end","two negative ends","two positive ends"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"When a crystal was added to the clear solution of its salt, the crystal did not dissolve and the solution remained unchange. This showed that the solution was","options":["supersaturated","concentrated","unsaturated","saturated"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A particle that contains 11 protons, 12 neutrons and 10 electrons is probably a","options":["neutral non-metal","metallic ion","non-metallic ion","neutral metal"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A difference between chemical and physical change is that in a chemical change","options":["oxygen is consumed","heat is supplied","a reversible process oocurs","a new substance is formed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The volume of 2.5 moles of oxygen at s.t.p is<br>\r\n[Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["50.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","84.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","28.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Nuclear fission involves the splitting of a heavy element into two nuclei of","options":["nearly equal masses with a relaese of energy and radiaton","equal masses with a relaese of energy","equal masses with a release of energy and radiation","unequal masses without any relaese of energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"What is the molar mass of a substance, if 0.4 mole of the substance has a mass of 25.0g?","options":["62.5 g","40.0 g","6.3 g","2.5 g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The element with the electron configuration 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>3<\/sup> is","options":["calcium","chlorine","oxygen","nitrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A decrease in atomic size and an increase in nuclear charge across a period lead to","options":["an increase in the tendency to lose electron","an increase in chemical reactivity","a decrease in electropositivity","a decrease in covalency in bond formation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The order in which a mixture of sand, ammonium chloride and sodium chloride can be separated is","options":["dissolution \u2192 dryness \u2192 filtration \u2192 evaporation","filtration \u2192 sublimation \u2192 evaporation \u2192 dryness","sublimation \u2192 dissolution \u2192 filtration \u2192 evaporation","dissolution \u2192 filtration \u2192 sublimation \u2192 evaporation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The idea of planetary electron was that of","options":["Rutherford","Thompson","Bohr","Dalton"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"If 30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of gas at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C is warmed to 80<sup>o<\/sup> at a fixed pressure, the fractional increase in volume is","options":["0.009","0.093","0.910","1.090"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"2C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + 5O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 4CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the mass of carbon(IV)oxide produced on burning 78 g of ethyne is<br>\r\n[C =12, O = 16, H = 1]","options":["264 g","39 g","352 g","156 g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The ion that can be used as an oxidizing agent is","options":["Au<sup>3+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","F<sup>-<\/sup>","Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + Br<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2HBr<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe above reaction is carried out at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C. \u0394H is -72 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup> and \u0394S is - 106 J mol<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>, the reaction will","options":["not proceed spontaneously at the given","proceed spontaneously at the given temperature","proceed in the reverse direction at the given temperature","proceed spontenously at lower temperature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Zinc and carbon rods are used as anode and cathode respectively in a","options":["Leclanche cell","lead accumulator","Daniel cell","voltaic cell"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The solution that will conduct the highest amount of electricity is","options":["0.5 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of hydrochloric acid","2.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of hydrochloric acid","0.5 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> ethanoic acid","2.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In which of the following is the oxidation number of sulphur equal to -2?","options":["SO<sub>3<\/sub>","S<sub>8<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S","SO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of CuSO<sub>4(g)<\/sub> using platinum electrodes, the reaction at the anode is","options":["4H<sup>+<\/sup> + 4e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>","4OH<sup>-<\/sup> - 4e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>","2OH - 2e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 2OH","2OH<sup>-<\/sup> + 2OH<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + 2HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 2NaCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nHow many moles of sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) are there in a 25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> solution which required 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.05 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> hydrochloric acid solution to neutralize it?","options":["1.000 mole","0.100 mole","0.010 mole`","0.111 mole"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"If the heat of combustion of hydrogen is -285.8kJ, <br>\r\nWhat is the heat of formation of water?","options":["+571.6 kJ","-571.6 kJ","-285.8 kJ","+285.8 kJ"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"5SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + 2KMnO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2MnSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, the products give a","options":["purple solution","purple precipitate","colourless precipitate","colourless solution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In the diagram above, gas X is","options":["hydrogen","chlorine","oxygen","hydrogen chloride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In the diagram above, mixture Y is","options":["NH<sub>4<\/sub>NO<sub>3(s)<\/sub>  + CaSO<sub>4(s),\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>CL<sub>(s)<\/sub> + NaNO<sub>2(s)<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>NO<sub>2(s)<\/sub> + Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(s)<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>CL<sub>(s)<\/sub> + Ca(OH)<sub>2(s)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The oxidation of the compound above produces","options":["2-butanone","2-butanal","3-butanal","3-butanone"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"2-methylbut-2-ene has the structure","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following functional groups will give gas bubbles when treated with a saturated solution of sodium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (IV)?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following equimolar solutions will have the highest pH?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOHa","NaOH","HCl","NH<sub>4<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following ions require the largest quantity of electricity for discharge at an electrode?","options":["4.0 moles of Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","3.0 moles of Na<sup>+<\/sup>","2.5 moles of Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>","2.0 moles of Al<sup>3+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Phenolphthalein in acidic solution is","options":["red","orange","colourless","yellow"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When iron is exposed to moisture and it rusts, the value of \u0394G for the reaction is","options":["neutral","zero","positive","negative"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In which of the following reactions can the oxidation number of the nitrogen be said to have increased?","options":["2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 NOCl<sub>2(l)<\/sub>","FeSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 Fe(NO)SO<sub>4(s)<\/sub>","NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Br<sub>2(l)<\/sub> \u2192 NOBr<sub>2(l)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"2H<sub>2<\/sub> + O<sub>2<\/sub>2 \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>+O \u0394H = -571kJ<br>\r\nIn the equation above, how much heat will be liberated if 12.0g of hydrogen is burnt in excess oxygen?","options":["-1142 kJ","-571 kJ","+1142 kJ","-1713 kJ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A concentrated solution containing H<sup>+<\/sup>, Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>, OH<sup>-<\/sup> and Cl<sup>-<\/sup> was electrolyzed using platinum electrodes.<br>\r\nThe ion that will be discharged at the cathode is","options":["Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sup>+<\/sup>","OH<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When sulphur (IV) oxide is passed into a solution of sodium hydroxide for a long time, it eventually produces a solution of","options":["NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaHSO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"What is the correct IUPAC name for NO<sub>2<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>?","options":["Dioxonitrate (IV) ion","Trioxonitrate (III) ion","Trioxonitrate (IV) ion","Dioxonitrate (II) ion"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"What will happen if an aluminium spoon is used to stir a solution of iron (II) trioxonitrates (V)?","options":["The spoon will be oxidized while the iron (II) ions will be reduced to the metal","The spoon will increase in size","The spoon will be reduced while the iron (II) ions will be oxidized","The spoon will be reduced"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The enzymes responsible for converting sucrose into two simple isomeric sugars is","options":["maltase","amylase","invertase","lactase"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The decolourization of purple colour of tetraoxomanganate (VII) ion is a test for","options":["alkenes","alkanols","alkanals","alkanes"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following are structural isomers?","options":["propanoic acid and propan-1, 2-diol","Propanal and propanone","Ethanoic acid and propanoic acid","Ethan-1, 2-diol and ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In the purification of impure samples of ethyl ethanoate synthesized by esterification, concentrated sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) solution is used to remove","options":["water","basic impurities","acidic impurities","ethoxyethane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"How many hydrogen atoms does a single ring cycloalkane have less than the corresponding open-chain alkane?","options":["Two","Three","Four","One"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Equal moles of ethyne and hydrogen iodide react to give","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CH<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub> - CHI","CH<sub>3<\/sub> - CI","CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CHI"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A substance that is used as a ripening agent for fruits is","options":["ethene","propene","methane","butane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When water boilers are used for long period of time, the solid substances left behind as scale are","options":["magnesium trioxosilicate (IV) and rust","magnesium trioxosilicate (IV) and calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","clay and magnesium troxosulphate (IV)","clay and rust"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a mixture of nobel gases was obtained from air after the removal of other constituents. What was the original volume of air","options":["2,500 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1250 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","125 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","80 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The solubility curve shows the variation of solute concentration with","options":["volume","temperature","vapour density","pressure"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The air around smelting industries is likely to contain","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S, CO and N<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>, SO<sub>3<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>, SO<sub>2<\/sub> and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>, N<sub>2<\/sub> and CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Kerosine is commonly used to remove the red colour stain of palm oil from cloths because it","options":["helps to spread the oil over a larger surface area","react with the oil to form an odourless compound","makes the oil evaporate easily by dissolving it","helps to dilute the oil and reduce its colour"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The gas that is the most dangerous pollutant to human is","options":["sulphur (IV) oxide","carbon (IV) oxide","nitrogen (II) oxide","hydrogen sulphide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Natural water collected from rivers and ponds contain oxygen, carbon (IV) oxide and","options":["nitrogen","hydrogen","chlorine","sulphur","oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"How many moles of limestone will be required to produce 5.6g of CaO?<br>\r\n[Ca = 40, C = 12, O= 16]","options":["0.20 mol","0.10 mol","1.12 mol","0.56 mol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The shape of the hydrocarbon compound CH<sub>4<\/sub> is","options":["square planar","planar","linear","tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of these properties gives a solid its definite shape?","options":["strong intermolecular attraction","high melting point","high boiling point","weak intermolecular attraction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Sugar is separated from its impurities by","options":["precipitation","crystallization","distillation","evaporation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The component of an atom that contributes least to its mass is the","options":["proton","nucleus","neutron","electron"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An element wil readily form an electrovalent compound if it electron configuration is","options":["2, 8, 1","2, 8, 4","2, 8, 8","2, 8, 5"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A heterogenous mixture can be defined as any mixture","options":["of a solute nd a solvent","whose cmposition is uniform","whose composition is not uniform","formed by solids and liquids"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The pressure of 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen at 35<sup>o<\/sup>C is 750mmHg. What will be the volume of gas if the pressure is reduced to 100mmHg without changing the temperature?","options":["650 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","850 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","580 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","750 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<b> I. Treatment of cancer<\/b><br>\r\n<b> II. Detection of leakages in water mains<\/b><br>\r\n<b> III. Detection of the ages of ancient tools<\/b><br>\r\n<b> IV. Preparation of drugs<\/b><br>\r\nWhich combination of the above refers to the uses of radioactive isotopes?","options":["<b>I<\/b> and <b>III<\/b>","<b>I<\/b> and <b>II<\/b>","<b>I<\/b>, <b>II<\/b> and <b>III<\/b>","<b>I<\/b>, <b>II<\/b>, <b>III<\/b> and <b>IV<\/b>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"What is the valence shell electron configuration of the element with atomic number 17?","options":["1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>4<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>5<\/sup>","2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup>","3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>5<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The density of a certain gas is 1.98gdm<sup>-3<\/sup> at s.t.p. What is the molecular mas of the gas?","options":["44.0 g","54.0 g","26.0 g","31.0 g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When pure aluminium metal is heated to red hot in the presence of nitrogen gas, the compound formed is","options":["Al<sub>2<\/sub>N","Al<sub>2<\/sub>N<sub>2<\/sub>","AlN","Al<sub>2<\/sub>N<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A dense white fume is formed when ammonia gas reacts  with","options":["O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> \u0394H = -90 kJ<br>\r\nIn the equation above, the yield of ammonia can be decreased by","options":["increasing the pressure","removing the ammonia as it is formed","increase the temperature","adding a catalyst"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The gas that can be dried using concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid is","options":["hydrogen bromide","Sulphur (IV) oxide","hydrogen sulphide","ammonia"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl<Sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2194 NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + HCL<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe reaction above can only attain equilibrium if","options":["a gaseous reactant is added","one of the products is removed","it is in a closed system","it is an open system"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The most suitable metal that can be used as lightning conductor is","options":["silver","copper","iron","aluminium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In the diagram above which of the cures illustrates Arrhenius' law?","options":["Y","Z","R","X"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The most abundant element on the earth's crust is","options":["nitrogen","hydrogen","oxygen","flourine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Metalliods are also referred to as","options":["semi-metals","metals","colliods","non-metals"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The ores that can be concentrated by flotation are","options":["nitride ores","sulphide ores","oxide ores","non-metals"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The property used in the industrial preparation of nitrogen and oxygen from air is","options":["rate of diffusion","density","boiling point","solubility"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In a flame test for calcium, the flame appears","options":["green when viewed through a blue glass","blue when viewed through a blue glass","orange -red when viewed through a blue glass","brick-red when viewed through a blue-glass"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following alloys contain iron?","options":["Duralumin and steel","Brass and bronze","Steel and permalloy","Soft solder and duralumin"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"To obtain pure carbon (II) oxide from its mixture with carbon (IV) oxide, the mixture should be","options":["passed over heated copper (II) oxide","bubbled through water","bubbled through concentrated tetroxosulphate (VI) acid","bubbled through sodium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When a solid substance disappears completely as a gas on heating, the substance is said to have undergone","options":["evaporation","distillation","crystallization","sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A chemical reaction is always associated with","options":["an increase in the composition of one of the substance","a change in the volume of the reactants","a change in the nature of the reactants","the formation of new substance"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"If a solution contains 4.9g of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid, calculate the amount of copper (II) oxide that will react with it<br>\r\n[Cu = 64, O = 16, S = 32, H = 1]","options":["0.8g","4.0g","40.0g","80.0g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"What volume of gas is evolved at S.t.p if 2g of calcium trioxocarbonate (IV) is added to a solution of hydrochloric acid?<br>\r\n[Ca = 40, C = 12, O = 16, Cl = 35.5, H = 1 Molar volume of agas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","options":["112 cm<sup>2<\/sup>","224 cm<sup>2<\/sup>","448 cm<sup>2<\/sup>","2240 cm<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"According to charles' law, the volume of a gas becomes zero at","options":["0 <sup>o<\/sup>C","-100 <sup>o<\/sup>C","-273 <sup>o<\/sup>C","-373 <sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"It is difficult to achieve an orderly arrangement of the molecules of a gas because they","options":["have no definite shape","have little force of attraction between them","can collide with one another in the container","are too small in size"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A given volume of methane diffuses in 20s. How long will it take the same volume of sulphur (IV) oxide to diffuse under the same conditions?<br>\r\n[C = 12, H = 1, S = 32, O = 16","options":["5s","20s","40s","60s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An electron can be added to a halogen atom to form a halide ion with","options":["2 valence electrons","3 valence electrons","7 valence electrons","8 valence electrons"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The shape of s-orbitals is","options":["spherical","elliptical","spiral","circular"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"<sup>226<\/sup><sub>88<\/sub>Ra \u2192 <sup>x<\/sup><sub>86<\/sub>Rn + \u03b1 - particle<br>\r\nWhat is the value of x in the nuclear reaction above?","options":["220","222","226","227"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The property of chlorine which causes hydrogen chloride to be more ionic than the chlorine molecules is its","options":["electrovalency","electron affinity","electropositivity","electronegativity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Chlorine consisting of two isotopes of mass number 35 and 37 in the ratio 3:1 has an atomic mass of 35.5. Calculate the relative abundance of the isotopes of mass number 37","options":["20","25","60","75"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following mixture of gases is likely to burn in flame","options":["neon and hydrogen","nitrogen and helium","helium and neon","neon and nitrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Hardness of water is caused by the presence of ions of","options":["magnesium and silver","cacium and magnesium","sodium and potassium","calcium and sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Pollution of underground water by metal ions is very likely in the soil that has high","options":["acidity","alkalinity","chloride content","nitrate content"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A carcinogenic substance is","options":["asbestos dust","sawdust","nitrogen (II) oxide","carbon (II) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The solubility in mol dm\/<sup>-3<\/sup> of 20g of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> dissolved in 100g of water at 180<sup>o<\/sup> is<br>\r\n[Cu = 64, S = 32, O =16]","options":["0.13","0.25","1.25","2.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI) dissolves in water only sparingly to form a","options":["solution","suspension","precipitate","colloid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following compound is a normal salt?","options":["NaHS","NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub>","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"What volume of 0.5 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> will exactly neutralize 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> NaOH solution?","options":["2.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.8 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","8.3 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The oxidation state of chlorine in HClO<sub>4<\/sub> is","options":["-5","-1","+1","+7"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"ZnO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, Zinc has been","options":["decomposed","displaced","oxidized","reduced"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following acts as both reducing and oxidized agent?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S","CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of brine, the anode is","options":["platinum","copper","zinc","carbon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The mass of silver deposited when a current of 10a is passed through a solution of silver salt for 4830s is<br>\r\n[Ag = 108, F = 96500 c mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["108.0g","54.0g","27.0g","13.5gq"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"2CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nGiven that \u0394H[CO]is -110.4 kJmol<sup>-1<\/sup> and \u0394H[CO<sub>2<\/sub>] is -393.0 kJmol<sup>-1<\/sup>, the energy change for the reaction above is","options":["-503.7 kJ","-282.6 kJ","+282.6 kJ","+503.7 kJ"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following hydrogen halides the highest entropy value?","options":["HF","HCl","HBr","HI"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the endothermic reaction above, more product formation will be favoured by","options":["a constant volume","an increase in pressure","a decrease in pressure","a decrease in volume"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following shows little or no net reaction when the volume of the system is decreased?","options":["H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + I<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2HI<sub>(g)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub>","PCl<sub>5(g)<\/sub> \u2194  PCl<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2O<sub>3(g)<\/sub> \u2194 3O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The allotropy of carbon used in the decolourization of sugar is","options":["Graphite","Soot","Charcoal","Lampblack"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following gases can be collected by the method of downward delivery?","options":["Chlorine","Oxygen","Ammonia","Hydrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"When steam is passed over red-hot carbon, the substances produced are","options":["Hydrogen and trioxocarbonate (IV) acid","Hydrogen, oxygen and carbon (IV) oxide","Hydrogen and carbon (II) oxide","Hydrogen and carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Sulphur (IV) oxide bleaches by","options":["Reduction","Oxidation","Hydration","Adsorption"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Carbon is tetravalent because","options":["The electrons in both the 2s and 2p orbitals are equivalent","The electrons in all the orbitals of carbon are equivalent","The 2s and 2p atomic orbitals hybridize","All the atomic orbitals of carbon hybridize"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Aluminium hydroxide is used in the dyeing industry as a","options":["Salt","Dye","Mordant","Dispersant"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Alloys are best prepared by","options":["Electroplating","Arc-welding","Reducing and mixture of their metallic oxide","Cooling a molten mixture of the metals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Transition metals possess variable oxidation states because they have","options":["Electrons in the d orbitals","Electron in the s orbitals","A variable number of electrons in the p orbitals","Partially filled p orbitals"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Sodium metal is always kept under oil because it","options":["Readily reacts with water","Is reduced by atmospheric nitrogen","Reacts vigorously on exposure to air","Reacts with oxygen and carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Oxyacetylene flame is used for iron-welding because it","options":["Makes the iron metals solidify very quickly","Combines with oxygen to give a pop sound","Evolves a lot of heat when burnt","Dissociates to produce carbon (IV) oxide and oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The alkyl group can be represented by the general formula","options":["C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n+1<\/sub>","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n+2<\/sub>","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n-2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An isomer of C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub> is","options":["Butane","2 \u2013 methylbutane","2 \u2013 methylpropane","2 \u2013 ethylbutane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A characteristic of the alkane family is","options":["Addition reaction","Elimination reaction","Substitution reaction","Neutralization reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of these reagents can confirm the presence of a triple bond?","options":["Bromine water","Acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub>","Copper (I) chloride","Bromine gas"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Vulcanization involves the removal of","options":["A monomer","The single bond","The double bond","A polymer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 H<sub>4(g)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe reaction above is","options":["Carboxylation","Decarboxylation","Acidification","Esterification"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 Y<br>\r\nIf the above reaction takes place in conc. H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> at 180<sup>o<\/sup>, Y represents","options":["CH<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>OCH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Alkanol + Alkanoic \u2194 Ester + Water<br>\r\nThe reverse reaction above is known as","options":["Hydrolysis","Saponification","Hydration","Fermentation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In the production of soap, concentrated sodium chloride solution is added to","options":["Increase the solubility of soap","Decrease the solubility of the soap","Saponify the soap","Emulsify the soap"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In the experiment above, X is a mixture of nitrogen, carbon (IV) oxide and","options":["water","impurities","inert gas","oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of the compound above is","options":["2-ethylpentane","3,4-dimethylhexane","2,3-dimethylhexane","2-ethylhexane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"What volume of oxygen is produced from the decomposition of 2 mole of KCIO<sub>3<\/sub> at s.t.p?<br>\r\n[Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","33.6 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","44.8 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","67.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following is physical change?","options":["Burning kerosene","Freezing ice cream","Exposing white phosphorus","Dissolving calcium in water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"What is the percentage by mass of oxygen in Al<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>. 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O?<br>\r\n[Al = 27, S = 32, H = 1, O = 16]","options":["14.29%","25.39%","50.79%","59.25%"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The filter in the cigarette reduces the nicotine content by","options":["Burning","Adsorption","Evaporation","Absorption"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"3Cu + pHNO<sub>3<\/sub> \u21923Cu(NO<sub3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub> O + xNO<br>\r\nIn the equation above, the values of p and x respectively are","options":["1 and 3","2 and 3","6 and 2","8 and 2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Neutral atoms of neon with atomic number 10 have the same number of electron as","options":["O<sup>2+<\/sup>","Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","K<sup>+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The noble gases owe their inactivity to","options":["Octet configuration","Cyclic shape","Hexagonal shape","Obtuse configuration"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"According to the kinetic theory, an increase in temperature causes the kinetic energy of particles to","options":["Decrease","Increase","Remain constant","Be zero"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"<b>I. H = 1s<sup>1<\/sup> II. N = 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> p<sup>3<\/sup> III. O = 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> p<sup>4<\/sup> IV. Zn = 1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>6<\/sup> 4s<sup>2<\/sup> 3d<sup>10<\/sup><\/b><br>\r\nFrom the above, which of the following pairs is like to be paramagnetic?","options":["<b>I<\/b> and <b>II<\/b>","<b>I<\/b> and <b>III<\/b>","<b>I<\/b> and <b>IV<\/b>","<b>III<\/b> and <b>IV<\/b>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A gas exerts pressure on its container because","options":["some of its molecules are moving faster than others","of the collision of the molecules with each other","of the mass of the molecules of gas","the molecules of a gas colide with the walls of the container"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"When cathode rays are deflected onto the electrode of an electrometer, the instrument becomes","options":["negatively charged","positvely charged","neutral","bipolar"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The weakest attractive force that can be observed between two molecules is","options":["ionic","covalent","coordinate covalent","van der Waals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A consequence of global warming is","options":["air pollution","water pollution","increased humudity","flooding"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following ions is acidic?","options":["K<sup>+<\/sup>","KNO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>","S<sup>2-<\/sup>","H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The structural component that makes detergent dissolve more quickly in water than soap is","options":["-SO<sub>3<\/sub>- Na<sup>+<\/sup>","-COO-Na<sup>-<\/sup>","-SO<sub>4<\/sub>- Na<sup>+<\/sup>","-COO-K<sup>+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A liquid that will dissolve fat is","options":["Hydrochloric acid","Calcium hydroxide","Kerosene","Water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"What mass of K<sub>2<\/sub>CrO<sub>4<\/sub> is required to prepare 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.020 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup> solution?<br>\r\n[K<sub>2<\/sub>CrO<sub>4<\/sub> = 194.2g mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.97g","9.70g","19.42g","97.10g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Farmlands affected by crude-oil spillage can be decontaminated by","options":["Adding acidic solution","Using aerobic bacteria","Pouring water on the affected water area","Burning off the oil from the area"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"When 10g of sodium hydroxide is dissolved in 1000cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water, the sodium formed is approximately <br>\r\n[Na = 23, H = 1, O = 16]","options":["0.01 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.10 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.25 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.50 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A change in temperature of a saturated solution disturb the equilibrium between the","options":["Dissolved solute and the solvent","Solvent and undissolved solute","Dissolved solute and undissolved  solute","Dissolved solute and the solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"If an equilibrium reaction has \u0394H > 0, the reaction will proceed favourably in the forward direction at","options":["High temperature","Any temperature","Low temperature","Minimum temperature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The commonest feature of reactions at the anode is that","options":["electrons are consumed","oxidation is involved","ions are reduced","electrode dissolves"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following will change when a catalyst is added to a chemical reaction?","options":["The activation energy","The potential energy of the reactants","The heat of the reaction","the potential energy of the product"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"If y is an oxidizing agent that reacts with a reducing agent, Z, which of the following is correct?","options":["Y increases in oxidation number","Y becomes reduced","Z loses protons","Z gains protons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"When at equilibrium, which of the reactions below will shift to the right if the pressure is increased and the temperature is kept constant?","options":["2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2194 N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of a concentrated solution of sodium chloride using electrodes, which of the following ions are discharged at the cathode and anode respectively?","options":["Na<sup>+<\/sup> and Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","Na<sup>+<\/sup> and OH<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sup>+<\/sup> and OH<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sup>+<\/sup> and Cl<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nFrom the reaction above, calculate the standard enthalpies of formation of CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub> and CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> in kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup> are -394, -242, and -110 respectively.","options":["-262 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-42 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","+42 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","+262 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"When sugar is dissolved in tea, the reaction is always accomplished by","options":["positive change","negative entropy change","no entropy change","a minimum entropy change"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following is an electrolyte?","options":["Alcohol","Sodium acetate solution","Solid potassium hydroxide","Mercury"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Chlorine gas is prepared in the laboratory by","options":["adding concentrated hydrochloric acid to solid manganese (IV) oxide","aciding concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid to solid sodium chloride","dropping concentrated hydrochloric acid onto potassium tetraoxomanganate (VI) crystals","aciding concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid to hydrochloric acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Metals of the first transition series have special properties which are different from those of groups I and II elements because they have partially filled","options":["s orbitals","p orbitals","d orbitals","f orbitals"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Hydrogen can be displaced from a hot alkaline solution by","options":["Fe","Cu","Ca","Sn"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true of sulphur (IV) oxide?","options":["It forms tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid with water","It is an odourless gas","It is an acid hybride","It forms white precipitate with acidified barium chloride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The salt that will form a precipitate soluble in excess ammonia solution is","options":["Ca(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","Cu(NO<sub>3<sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","Mg(NO<sub>3<sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","Al(NO<sub>3<sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The metal that liberates hydrogen from cold water in bubbles only is","options":["Na","K","Ca","Al"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Chlorine gas turns a damp starch-iodide paper","options":["pink","colourless","red","dark blue"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The modern process of manufacturing steel for iron is by","options":["treatment with acids","oxidation","blast reduction","treatment with alkanal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Ethene reacts with hydrogen bromide to give","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>Br<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>Br","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>Br<sub>2<\/sub>","CHBr<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"How many isomers does pentane have?","options":["6","5","4","3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The leachate of a certain plant ash is used in local soap making because it contains","options":["sodium chloride and potassium hydroxide","sodium hydroxide","potassium hydroxide","soluble carbonates and hydrogen carbonates"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The formula for ethyl butanoate is","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOC<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>9<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOC<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>9<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The type of reaction that is peculiar to benzene is","options":["addition","hydrolysis","polymerization","substitution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Ethanol reacts with excess acidified K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O to produce","options":["ethanedioic acid","ethanal","ethylethanoate","ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A compound contains 40.0% carbon 6.7% hydrogen and 53.3% oxygen. If the molar mass of the compound is 180, find the molecular formula.<br>\r\n[H = 1, C = 12, O = 16]","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The process by which atoms are rearranged into different molecular structure in the petroleum refining process is referred to as","options":["catalytic cracking","hydrocracking","polymerization","reforming"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following is found in cotton","options":["Starch","Cellulose","Fat","Oil"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The principal constituent of natural gas is","options":["methane","ethane","propane","butane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"2HCI<sub>(ag)<\/sub> + CaCO<sub>3(s) \u2192 CaCl<sub>2(s)<\/sub> + CO <sub>2(g)<\/sub> +H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub> From the reaction above, which of the curves in the diagram represents the production of carbon (IV) oxide as dilute HCI is added?","options":["L","M","N","P"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A compound contains 31.91% potassium, 28.93% chlorine and the rest oxygen. What is the chemical formula of the compound?<br>\r\n[K = 39, Cl = 35.5, O = 16]","options":["KClO<sub>4<\/sub>","KClO","KClO<sub>2<\/sub>","KClO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The formula CH<sub>2<\/sub> for ethanoic acid is regarded as its","options":["Molecular formula","General formula","Empirical formula","Structural formula"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A little quantity of trichloromethane (b.pt 60,<sup>o<\/sup>C) was added to a large quantity of ethanol (b.pt 78,<sup>o<\/sup>C). The most probable boiling point of the resultant mixture is from","options":["69 <sup>o<\/sup>C - 70 <sup>o<\/sup>C","70 <sup>o<\/sup>C \u2013 74 <sup>o<\/sup>C","82 <sup>o<\/sup>C \u2013 84 <sup>o<\/sup>C","60 <sup>o<\/sup>C \u2013 78 <sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The chromatography separation of ink is based on the ability of the components to","options":["React with solvent","React with each other","Dissolve in each other in the column","Move at different speeds in the column"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In the reaction E+F \u2194 G+H, the backward reaction is favoured if the concentration of","options":["F is increased","E is increased","E is reduced","G is reduced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"What amount of mercury would be liberated if the same quantity of electricity that liberates 0.65g of zinc is applied?","options":["2.01g","1.00g","4.02g","8.04g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following equations show that a reaction is in equilibrium?","options":["\u0394G < O","\u0394G = \u0394H \u2013 T\u0394S","\u0394G > O","\u0394G = O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"PCl<sub>5(g)<\/sub> \u2194 PCl<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, a decrease in pressure will","options":["Decelerate the reaction","Increase the yield of PCl<sub>3<\/sub>","Increase the yield of PCl<sub>5<\/sub>","Accelerate the reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"When H<sub>2<\/sub>S is passed into a solution of iron (III) chloride, the solution turns","options":["Pale green","Pale red","Brown","Colourless"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Arrhenius equation expresses the relationship between the speed of a reaction and its","options":["Molecular collision","Heat of reaction","Catalyst","Activation energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"When dissolved in water, NaOH flakes show","options":["An endothermic  change","An exothermic change","A slow reaction","A rapid reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"CU<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>(s)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2CU<sub>(s)<\/sub> + SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nWhat is the change in the oxidation number of copper in the reaction above?","options":["+1 to 0","0 to +2","+2 to +1","0 to +1"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The product of the electrolysis of dilute sodium hydroxide using platinum electrodes are","options":["Hydrogen and oxygen gases","Water and hydrogen gas","Water and sodium metal","Sodium metal and oxygen gas"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The solubility of a salt of molar mass 101g at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C is 0.34 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>. If 3.40g of the salt is dissolved completely in 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water in a beaker, the resulting solution is","options":["A suspension","Saturated","Unsaturated","Supersaturated"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid burns the skin by","options":["Hydrolysis","Hydration","Heating","Dehydration"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"When a salt loses its water of crystallization to the atmosphere on exposure, the process is said to be","options":["Efflorescence","Deliquescence","Effervescence","Fluorescence"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Three drops of a 1.0 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> solution of NaOH are added to 20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a solution of pH 8.4. The pH of the resulting solution will be","options":["Close to that of pure water","Unaltered","Greater than 8.4","Less than 8.4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 0.2 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup> solution of Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> requires 20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a solution of HCl for neutralization. The concentration of the HCl solution is","options":["0.5 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.6 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.2 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.4 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The substance least considered as a source of environmental pollution is","options":["Lead compounds","Organophosphorous compounds","Silicate minerals","Uranium"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The fuming of kettles is caused by the presence in the water of","options":["Calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Calcium hydrogentrioxocarbonate (IV)","Calcium hydroxide","Calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The property which makes alcohol  soluble in water is the","options":["boiling point","hydrogen bonding","ionic character","covalent nature"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Steam changes the colour of anhydrous cobalt  (II) chloride from","options":["blue to pink","white to red","white to green","blue to white"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The gas that gives brown colouration in brown ring test is","options":["NO","CO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Ethanol can easily be produced by","options":["fermentation of starch","distillation of starch solution","catalytic oxidation of methane","destructive distillation of wood"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following gives a precipitate when treated with NaOH solution?","options":["AlCl<sub>3<\/sub>","NH<sub>4<\/sub>CL","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An example of element that can catenate is","options":["bromine","nitrogen","chlorine","carbon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The reaction of an alkene with hydrogen in the presence of catalyst is","options":["a substitution reaction","an oxidation reaction","a nucleophilic reaction","an addition reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The number of isomers formed by C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>14<\/sub> is","options":["4","5","2","3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of these pairs are synthetic and natural macromolecules respectively?","options":["Haemoglobin and nylon, creatine and polyethylene","Nylon and polyethlene, creatine and Haemoglobin","Nylon and creatine, polyethylene and haemoglobin","Polyethylene and creatine, nylon and haemoglobin"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Ordinary glass is manufactured from silica, CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> and","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A red precipitate of copper (I) carbide is formed when ammonium solution of copper (I) chloride is introduced into","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CH - CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub> - C = CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> - C = C - CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The boiling of fat and aqueous caustic soda is referred to as","options":["hydrolysis","esterification","acidification","saponification"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The most important use of hydrogen is in the","options":["manufacture of ammonia","manufacture of methyl alcohol","manufacture of ethyl alcohol","hydrogenation of oils"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"which of the following polymers is suitable for packaging and electrical insulation?","options":["polyamide","polyethene","polycarbonate","polystyrene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Hydrogen is readily released when dilute hydrochloric acid reacts with","options":["Cu","Na","Au","Ag"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The intermediate product formed when ethanol is progressively oxidized to ethanoic acid with potassium heptaoxodichromate (IV) is","options":["butanal","ethanal","methanal","propanal"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A rock sample was added to cold dilute HNO<sub>3<\/sub>. The gas evolved was passed into a solution of acidified K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> and the solution turned green. The sample contains","options":["Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","NO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>","SO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>","SO<sub>4<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is true of a proton?","options":["The mass of a proton is 1840 times the mass of electron","the total mass of the protons in a particular nucleus is always half the nuclear size","The mass of a proton is one - twelfth the molar mass of carbon","The mass of a proton is 1.0008g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following chloride would exhibit the least ionic character?","options":["MgCl<sub>2<\/sub>","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","LiCl","AlCl<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A fixed mass of gas has a volume of 92cm<sub>3<\/sub> at 3 <sup>o<\/sup>C. When will be its volume at 18 <sup>o<\/sup>C if the pressure remains constant","options":["15.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","87.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","552.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","97.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The processes which return carbon (IV) oxide to the atmosphere include","options":["respiration, decay and combustion","photosynthesis, respiration and transpiration","ozone depletion, combustion and decay","photosynthesis, decay and respiration"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The postulate of Dalton's atomic theory which still holds is that","options":["atoms can neither be created nor destroyed","the particles of the same element are exactly alike","particles of different elements combine in simple whole number ratio","all elemets are made of small indivisible particles"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"<sup>14<\/sup><sub>6<\/sub>C \u2192 X + B<br>\r\nX in the equation above represents","options":["<sup>12<\/sup><sub>6<\/sub>C","<sup>12<\/sup><sub>5<\/sub>B","<sup>14<\/sup><sub>7<\/sub>N","<sup>13<\/sup><sub>6<\/sub>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"If 0.75 mole of cyclopropane and 0.66 mole of oxygen are mixed in vessel with a total pressure of 0.7 atmosphere, what is the partial pressure of oxygen in the mixture","options":["0.44 atmosphere","0.22 atmosphere","0.55 atmosphere","0.33 atmosphere"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In the diagram above, the curve that represents the production of oxgyen gas from the decomposition of KCIO<sub>3<\/sub> in the presence of MnO<sub>2<\/sub> catalyst is","options":["R","P","S","Q"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The major product of the dehydration of the compound above is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The compound above is","options":["glycol","primary alkanol","secondary alkanol","tertiary alkanol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a gas <b>X<\/b> contains <b>Z<\/b> molecules at 15<sup>o<\/sup>C and 75 mmHg. How many molecules will 25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of another gas <b>Y<\/b> contain at the same temperature and pressure?","options":["2 <b>Y<\/b>","2 <b>Z<\/b>","<b>Z<\/b>","<b>Y<\/b>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What mass of water is produced when 8.0g of hydrogen reacts with excess oxygen?<br>\r\n[H = 1, O = 16]","options":["36.0g","8.0g","72.0g","16.0g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A particle that contains 9 protons, 10 neutrons and 10 electrons is a","options":["negative ion","positive ion","neutral atom of non-metal","neutral atom of a metal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Cancerous growths are cured by exposure to","options":["\u03b3 - rays","\u03b2 - rays","\u03b1 - rays","x - ray"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An oxide <b>X<\/b>O<sub>2<\/sub> has a vapour density of 32. What is the atomic mass of <b>X<\/b>?","options":["32","20","14","12"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Millikan's contributions to the development of atomic theory is the determination of","options":["charge on electron","positive rays","charge to mass ratio","cathode rays"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Four elements <b>W<\/b>, <b>X<\/b>, <b>Y<\/b> and <b>Z<\/b> have atomic number 2,6,16 and 20 respectively. Which of these elements is a metal?","options":["<b>X<\/b>","<b>W<\/b>","<b>Z<\/b>","<b>Y<\/b>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An elements <b>X<\/b> with relative atomic mass 16.2 contains two isotopes <sup>16<\/sup><sub>8<\/sub>X with relative abundance of 90% and <sup>m<\/sup><sub>8<\/sub>X with relative abundance of 10%. The value of m is","options":["16","18","12","14"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about the average kinetic energy of the molecules of a gas?","options":["It increase with increase in pressure","It increase at constant temperature","It increase with increase in temperature","It increase with increase in volume"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The pollution from petroleum spillage in rivers and lakes can best be dispersed by","options":["Pouring detergents","Passing of ships through the area","Pouring organic solvents","Evaporation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Deliquescent substance are used for","options":["Cooling","Wetting","Melting","Drying"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Pure  solvents are obtained by","options":["Distillation","Condensation","Extraction","Evaporation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What is the decrease in volume of air when pyrogallol  is shaken with 30.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air ?","options":["15.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.30cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.63cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.06cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Environmental  pollution is worsened by the release from automobile exhausts  of","options":["Water vapour","Steam","Smoke","Heavy metals"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The chemical used for coagulation in water purification is","options":["Aluminium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Copper tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Sodium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Calcium tetraoxosulphate (VI)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Phosphorus is stored under water to prevent it from","options":["Dehydrating","Becoming inert","Smelling","Catching fire"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"In which of the following reactions does reduction takes place","options":["Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>  - e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192  Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","2O<sup>2-<\/sup> \u2192O<sub>2<\/sub> + 4e<sup>-<\/sup>","Cr \u2013 2e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192  Cr<sup>2+<\/sup>","2H<sup>+<\/sup> + 2e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"<b>P<\/b><sub>(g)<\/sub>  + <b>Q<\/b><sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2194  <b>3R<\/b><sub>(s)<\/sub>  + <b>S<\/b><sub>(g)<\/sub>   \u0394H is negative <br>\r\n Which of the following will increase the yield of <b>R<\/b>?","options":["Using a larger close vessel","Increasing the temperature","Removing some <b>S<\/b>","Adding a positive catalyst"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A metal  <b>M<\/b> displaces zinc from zinc chloride solution. This shows that","options":["<b>M<\/b>  is more electronegative than zinc","Zinc is above hydrogen in the series","<b>M<\/b>  is more electropositive than zinc","Electrons flow from zinc to <b>M<\/b>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following  best  explains the increase in the rate of a chemical reaction as the temperature rises?","options":["The bonds in the reacting molecules are more readily broken","The molecular collisions become more violent","A lower proportion of the molecules has the necessary minimum energy to react","The collision frequency of the molecules increase"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What current in amperes will deposit 2.7g of aluminium in 2 hours?<br>\r\n[Al = 27, F = 96 500 C mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["32","8","4","16"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Ethanoic acid is","options":["tribasic","unionizeable","monobasic","dibasic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2S<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192  CS<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n\u0394H = +89 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup><br>\r\nThe chemical equation above implies that","options":["each of carbon and sulphur has 89 kJ of energy","both carbon and sulphur contribute 89 kJ of energy","89 kJ of energy is released","89 kJ of energy is absorbed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n\u0394H = -189 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup><br>\r\nThe equilibrium constant for the reaction above is increased by","options":["Increasing the temperature of the system","Increase the pressure of the system","The addition of a catalyst to the system","Increasing the surface area of the vessel"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"3Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 8HNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub> 3Cu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> + 2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the equation above, copper is","options":["an electron acceptor","a base","an oxidizing agent","a reducing agent"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"When \u0394H is negative, a reaction is said to be","options":["ionic","reversible","exothermic","endothermic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"As the concentration of an electrolyte reduces, the conductivity","options":["reduces to zero","decreases","increase","is unaffected"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"In which of the following reactions has the oxidation number of nitrogen increased?","options":["2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Br<sub>2(l)<\/sub> \u2192 2NOBr<sub>(l)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","FeSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 Fe(NO)SO<sub>4(s)<\/sub>","2NO(g) + Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 2NOCl(l)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl<sub>(s)<\/sub><br>\r\nThe entropy change in the system above is","options":["negative","indeterminate","positive","zero"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Fermentation is the","options":["breaking down of carbohydrate to glucose","conversion of sugar to alcohol in the presence of yeast","breaking down of sugar to carbohydrate","conversion of alcohol to sugar in the presence of yeast"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The general formula for the alkanals is","options":["ROH","R<sub>2<\/sub>CO","RCOOR<sup>1<\/sup>","RCHO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The main impurity in iron ore during the extraction of iron is","options":["Silicon (IV) oxide","Carbon (IV) oxide","Calcium trioxosilicate","Sulphur (II) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"During the vulcanization of rubber, sulphur is added to","options":["Break down rubber polymer","Lengthen the chain of rubber","Bind rubber molecules together","Act as a catalyst"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Catalytic hydrogenation of benzene produces","options":["Oil","Cyclohexene","Cyclohexane","Margarine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A trihydric alkanol is","options":["Glycerol","Phenol","Glycol","Ethanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"When chlorine Is passed into water and the resulting solution exposed to sunlight, the product formed are","options":["Chlorine gas and hydrogen","Oxygen and oxochlorate (I) acid","Chlorine gas and oxochlorate (I) acid","Hydrochloric acid and oxygen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Proteins in acid solution undergo","options":["Polymerization","Substitution","Fermentation","Hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A characteristic reaction of the compounds with the general formula C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub> is","options":["Esterification","Polymerization","Decarboxylation","Substitution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The pair of organic compounds that are isomers is","options":["Benzene and methylbenzene","Trichloromethane and tetrachloromethane","Ethanol and propane","But-1-ene and but-2-ene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A burning candle produces water and","options":["Carbon (II) oxide","Carbon (IV) oxide","Oxygen","Hydrogen"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The gas that can best be collected by downward displacement of air is","options":["Chlorine","Sulphur (IV) oxide","Ammonia","Carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following metals burn with brick red flame?","options":["Pb","Ca","Na","Mg"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following represent hybridization in ethyne?","options":["Sp<sup>2<\/sup>","Sp<sup>2<\/sup>d","Sp<sup>3<\/sup>","Sp"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"C<sub>12<\/sub>H<sub>22<\/sub>O<sub>11(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> 12C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 11H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid function as","options":["A dehydrate agent","An oxidizing agent","A reducing agent","A catalyst"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"When sodium reacts with water, the resulting solution is","options":["Weakly acidic","Neutral","Acidic","Alkaline"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following gases contains the least number of atoms at s.t.p?","options":["1 mole of butane","3 mole of ozone","4 mole of chlorine","7 mole of argon"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question.If the gas is cooled, at what temperature will it start to condense?","options":["125 <sup>o<\/sup>C","150<sup>o<\/sup>C","175<sup>o<\/sup>C","250<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question.How long does it take all the solid to melt?`","options":["2.5 mins","6.0 mins","1.0 min","3.0 mins"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The diagram above represents the formation of","options":["a metallic bond","an electrovalent bond","a covalent bond","a coordinate covalent bond"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Use the solubility curves below to answer questions. If 1 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of a saturated solution of L at 60<sup>0<\/sup>C is cooled to 25<sup>0<\/sup>C, what amount in mole will separate out?","options":["0.75","0.25","1.00","0.50"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A mixture of iodine and sulphur crystals can be separated by treatment with","options":["Water to filter off sulphur","carbon (IV) sulphide to filter off iodine","ethanoic acid to filter off sulphur","methanol to filter off iodine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Sieving is a technique used to separate mixture containing solid particles of","options":["small sizes","large sizes","differents sizes","the same sizes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is composed of Al, Si, O and H?","options":["Epsom salt","Limestone","Clay","Urea"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of carbon (II) oxide was exploded with 150 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air containing 20% oxygen by volume. Which of the reactants was in excess?","options":["Carbon (II) oxide","Carbon (IV) oxide","Oxygen","Nitrogen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"<p>How many moles HCL will be required to react with potassium heptaoxodichromate (VI) to produce 3 moles of chlorine?<\/p>","options":["14","12","11","10"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The ratio of the initial to final pressure of a given mass of gas is 1:1.5. Calculate the final volume of the gas if the initial volume was 300 cm<sup>3<\/sup> at the same temperature","options":["120 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","200 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","450 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","750 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The partial pressure of oxygen in a sample of air is 452 mm Hg and the total pressure is 780 mm Hg. What is the mole fraction of oxygen?","options":["0.203","0.579","2.030","5.790"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The fundamental difference between the three states of matter is the","options":["shape of their particles","number of particles in each state","shape of the container they occupy","degree of movement of their particles"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is correct about the periodic table?","options":["Elements  in the same period have the same number of valency electron","The valence electron of the elements in the same period increase progressively across the period","Elements in the same group have the same number of electron shells","The non-metallic properties of the elements tend to decrease across each period"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The electron configuration of  <sub>22<\/sub>X <sup>2+<\/sup> ion is","options":["1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>6<\/sup> 4s<sup>2<\/sup> 3d<sup>2<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>6<\/sup> 4s<sup>2<\/sup> 3d<sup>1<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>6<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>6<\/sup> 4s<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following types of bonding does not involve the formation of new substance?","options":["Metallic","covalent","Co-ordinate","Electrovalent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The knowledge of half-life can be used to","options":["create an element","detect an element","split an element","irradiate an element"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The shapes of CO<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O and CH <sub>4<\/sub> respectively are","options":["bent, linear and tetrahedral","bent, tetrahedral and linear","linear, bent and tetrahedral","tetrahedral, linear and bent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The distance between the nuclei of chlorine atoms in a chlorine molecule is 0.194 mm. The atomic radius of chlorine atom is","options":["0.097 mm","0.194 mm","0.388 mm","2.388 mm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The noble gas, argon,is used for","options":["electric arc welding","welding brass","underwater welding","steel welding"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A side effect of soft water is that","options":["it gives offensive taste","excess calcium is precipitated","it attcaks lead contained in pipes","it encourages the growth of bacteria"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Water molecule can be ligands especially when they are bonded to","options":["alkaline earth metals","alkali metals","transition metals","group VII elements"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The air pollutant unknown in nature is","options":["NO","CO","HCHO","DDT"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"1.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of distilled water was used to wash 2.0g of a precipitate of AgCl. If the solubility product of AgCl is 2.0 * 10<sup>-10<\/sup>mol<sup>2<\/sup>dm<sup>-6<\/sup>, what quantity of silver was lost in the process?","options":["2.029 * 10<sup>-3<\/sup>mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","1.414 * 10<sup>-3<\/sup>mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","2.029 * 10<sup>-5<\/sup>mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","1.414 * 10<sup>-5<\/sup>mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Hydration of ions in solution is associated with","options":["absorption of heat","reduction of heat","conduction of heat","liberation of heat"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"HCL<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Cl<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, Cl<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> is the","options":["conjugate acid","acid","conjugate base","base"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"In which order are the following salts sensitive to light?","options":["Agl > AgCl > AgBr","AgCl > Agl > AgBr","AgBr > AgCl > Agl","AgCl > AgBr > Agl"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The pOH of a solution of 0.25 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> of hydrochloric acid is","options":["12.40","13.40","14.40","14.60"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"MnO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 8H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Y \u2192 Mn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub><br>\r\nY in the equation above represents","options":["2e<sup>-<\/sup>","3e<sup>-<\/sup>","5e<sup>-<\/sup>","7e<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"(1\/2)Zn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 (1\/2) Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub> <br>\r\nIn the reaction above, calculate the quantity of electricity required to discharge zinc.<br>\r\n[F = 96 500 C mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.965 * 10<sub>4<\/sub>C","4.820 * 10<sub>4<\/sub>C","9.650 * 10<sub>4<\/sub>C","48.200 * 10<sub>4<\/sub>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Given that <b>M<\/b> is the mass of substance deposited in an electrolysis and <b>Q<\/b> the quantity of electricity consumed, then Faraday's law can be written as","options":["M = Z\/Q","M = Q\/Z","M = Z\/2Q","M = QZ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"0.46g of ethanol when burned raised the temperature of 50g of water by 14.3K. Calculate the heat of combustion of ethanol.<br>\r\n[C = 12, O = 16, H = 1, Specific heat capacity of water = 4.2 jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["+3000 KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","+300  KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-300  KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-3000  KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Powdered marble reacts faster with hydrochloric acid solution than the granular form because the powdered form has","options":["more molecules","more atoms","larger surface area","relatively large mass"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub>; \u0394H = + 180.6 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup><br>\r\nIn the reaction above, increase in temperature will","options":["increase the quantity of N<sub>2<\/sub>","increase in the yield of NO","decrease the yield of NO","decrease the quantity of O<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"For a reaction in equilibrium, the species involved in the equilibrium constant expression are","options":["gaseous and solid species","liquid and solid species","solid and dissolved species","gaseous and dissolved species"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A phenomenon where an element exist in different forms in the same physical state is known as","options":["isomerism","amorphism","allotropy","isotopy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The substance often use for vulcanization of rubber is","options":["chlorine","hydrogen peroxide","sulphur","tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A gas that is not associated with global warming is","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>4<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The refreshing and characteristic taste of soda water and other soft drinks is as a result of the presence  in them of","options":["carbon (IV) oxide","carbon (II) oxide","soda","glucose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A form of carbon used for absorbing poisonous gases and purification of noble gases is","options":["wood charcoal","animal charcoal","carbon fibres","carbon black"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Synthesis gas is a mixture of","options":["CH<sub>4<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CH<sub>4<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>","CO and H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Potassium vapour burns with a","options":["blue flame","brick-red flame","violet flame","golden-yellow flame"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A common characteristics of copper and silver in their usage as coinage metals is that they","options":["have high metallic lustre","are not easily oxidized","are easily oxidized","are not easil reduced"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Haematite is an ore of","options":["zinc","lead","iron","copper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The least easily oxidized of the metals below is","options":["Ca","Na","Zn","Al"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The repeating unit in natural rubber is","options":["alkyne","isoprene","n-propene","peoprene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Unsaturated organic compounds are identified  by decolourization of","options":["silver bromine and potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solutions","bromine water and acidified potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solution","silver bromide solution and bromine water","bromine water and alkaline potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The conditions necessary for the extraction of a water molecule from two molecules of ethanol are","options":["less acid and lower temperature","excess acid and a lower temperature","excess acid and a higher temperature","less acid and a higher temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The chlorinated alkane often used industrially to remove grease is","options":["tetrachloromethane","chloromethane","trichloromethane","dichlorometane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The reaction of carbide with water gives","options":["ethyne","ethene","ethane","ethanal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Alkanones are generally obtained by the oxidation of","options":["primary alkanols","secondary alkanols","tertiary alkanols","alkanoic acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Sucrose is made up of","options":["glucose and glucose","glucose and fructose","fructose and fructose","galactose and glucose"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The diagram above is the solubility curve of a solute, X. Find the amount of X deposited when 500cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a solution of X is cooled from 60<sup>o<\/sup>C to 20<sup>o<\/sup>C.","options":["0.750 mole","0.950 mole","2.375 moles","4.750 moles"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Use the option above to answer this question. The graph that describes a zero order reaction is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The compound above is an","options":["ether","ester","alkanal","alkanol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"200cm<sup>3<\/sup> each of 0.1M solutions of lead (II) trioxonitrate (V) and hydrochloric acid were mixed. Assuming that lead (II) chloride is completely insoluble, calculate the mass of lead (II) chloride that will be precipitated.<br>\r\n[Pb = 207, Cl= 35.5, N = 14, O = 16]","options":["2.78g","5.56g","8.34g","11.12g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"56.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a gas at S.T.P. weighed 0.11g. What is the vapour density of the gas?<br>\r\n[Molar volume of a gas at S.T.P = 22.4dm<sup>3<\/sup>]","options":["11.00","22.00","33.00","44.00"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following gases will diffuse fastest when passed through a porous plug?<br>\r\n[H = 1, C = 12, N = 14, O = 16]","options":["Propane","Oxygen","Methane","Ammonia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which is the temperature of a given mass of a gas initially at 0\u00b0C and 9 atm, if the pressure is reduced to 3 atm at constant volume?","options":["91K","182K","273K","819K"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following will have its mass increased when heated in air?","options":["Helium","Magnesium","Copper pyrites","Glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Mg<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 MgCl<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nFrom the equation above, the mass of magnesium required to react with 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.5M HCl is<br>\r\n[Mg = 24]","options":["0.3g","1.5g","2.4g","3.0g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A gaseous metallic chloride MCl<sub>x<\/sub> consists of 20.22% of M by mass. The formula of the chloride is <br>\r\n[M = 27, Cl = 35.5]","options":["MCl","MCl<sub>2<\/sub>","MCl<sub>3<\/sub>","M<sub>2<\/sub>Cl<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"In which of the following are water molecules in the most disorderly arrangement?","options":["Ice at -10\u00b0C","Ice at 0\u00b0C","Water at 100\u00b0C","Steam at 100\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"In order to remove one electron from a 3S orbital of gaseous sodium atom, about 496KJMol<sup>-1<\/sup> of energy is required. This energy is referred to as","options":["electron affinity","ionization energy","activation evergy","electronegativity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Nitrogen obtained from the liquefaction of air has a higher density than that obtained from nitrogen containing compounds because the former contains","options":["water vapour","oxygen","carbon (IV) oxide","rare gases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The method that can be used to convert hard water to soft water is","options":["chlorination","passage over activated charcoal","the use of an ion-exchange resin","aeration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"1s<sup>2<\/sup>, 2s<sup>2<\/sup>, 2p<sup>6<\/sup>, 3s<sup>2<\/sup>, 3p<sup>6<\/sup>, 3d<sup>7<\/sup>, 4s<sup>2<\/sup><br>\r\nAn element with the electronic configuration above is a","options":["non-metal","metal","transition element","group two element"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Given that electronegativity increases across a period and decreases down a group in the periodic table, in which of the following compounds will the molecules be held together by the strongest hydrogen bond?","options":["HF<sub>(g)<\/sub>","NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub>","CH<sub>4(g)<\/sub>","HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"0.25 mole of hydrogen chloride was dissolved in distilled water and the volume made up of 0.50 dm<sup>3<\/sup>. If 15.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of the solution requires 12.50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of aqueous sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) for neutralization, calculate the concentration of the alkaline solution","options":["0.30 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.40 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.50 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.60 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The correct order of increasing oxidation number of the transition metal ions for the compounds K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub>, V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> and KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> is","options":["V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < KMnO<sub>4<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>","KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>","KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The set of pollutants that is most likely to be produced when petrol is accidentally spilled on plastic materials and ignited is","options":["CO, CO<sup>2<\/sup> and SO<sup>2<\/sup>","CO, HCL and SO<sup>2<\/sup>","CO, CO<sup>2<\/sup> and HCL","SO<sup>2<\/sup>, CO<sup>2<\/sup> and HCL"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"What is observed when aqueous solutions of each of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid, potassium trioxoiodate (V) and potassium iodide are mixed together?","options":["A white precipitate is formed","A green precipitate is formed","The mixture remains colourless","The mixture turns reddish brown"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The solution with the lowest pH value is","options":["5 ml of (m\/10) HCL","10 ml of (m\/10) HCL","15  ml of (m\/5) HCL","20  ml of (m\/8) HCL"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The solubility product of Cu(IO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> is 1.08 * 10<sup>-7<\/sup>. Assuming that neither ions react appreciable with water to form H<sup>+<\/sup> and OH<sup>-<\/sup>, what is the solubility of this salt?","options":["2.7 * 10<sup>-8<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","9.0 * 10<sup>-8<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.0 * 10<sup>-3<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","9.0 * 10<sup>-3<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The entropy and enthalpy of a system are a measure of","options":["degree of disorderlinesss and heat content respectively","heat content and degree of disorderliness respectively","heat content of a system only","degree of disorderliness  only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub>. In the chemical reaction above, the substance that will increase the rate of production of sulphur (VI) oxide is","options":["manganese (IV) oxide","finely divided iron","vanadium (V) oxide","nickel"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>. Increase in total pressure of the equilibrium reaction above will","options":["produce more of NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> in the mixture","convert all of N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub> to NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","have no effect on the concentrations of NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>and N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub>","produce more of N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub> in the mixture"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"What quantity of electricity will liberate 0.125 mole of oxygen molecules during the electrolysis of dilute sodium chloride solution?<br>\r\n[ F = 96 5000 C mol<sup>-1<\/sup> ]","options":["24 125 coulombs","48 250 coulombs","72 375 coulombs","96 500 coulombs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"X + Y \u2192 Z. The rate equation for the chemical reaction above is ((-\u0394[x])\/\u0394t) = K[X]<sup>2<\/sup>[Y].<br>\r\nThe overall order of the reaction is","options":["0.0","1.0","2.0","3.09"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"When a current I was passed through an electrolyte solution for 40 minutes, a mass X g of a univalent metal was deposited at the cathode. What mass of the metal will be deposited when a current 2I is passed  through the solution for 10 minutes?","options":["X\/4 g","X\/2 g","2X g","4X g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"RS<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + HF<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 RF<sub>(s)<\/sub> + HS<sub>(aq)<\/sub> <br>\r\n\u0394H = -65.7 kj mol<sup>(-1)<\/sup>. <br>\r\nFrom the equation above, it can be deduced that","options":["the heat content of the reactants is lower than that of the products","the heat content of the reactants is higher than that of the products","the reaction is slow","a large amount of heat is absorbed"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is true of the electrochemical series?","options":["Electropositivity of metals increase down the series","Electropositivity of non-metals decrease down the series","Electronegativity of non-metals decrease down the series","Electropositivity of metals decreases down the series"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The gas that will form a white precipitate with acidified silver trioxonitrate (v) is","options":["NH<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>","HCL"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Chlorine, bromine and iodine resemble one another in that they","options":["dissolve in alkalis","react violently with hydorgen without heating","are liquids","displace one another from solutiions of their salts"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The salt that reacts with dilute hydrochloric acid to produce a pungent smelling gas which decolourizes acidified purple potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solution is","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A pair of compounds that can be used to generate a gas which has physiological effect on human beings is","options":["sodium trioxonitrate (V) and calcium chloride","sodium dioxonitrate (III) and ammonium chloride","sodium trioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","sodium dioxonitrate (III) and potassium chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Hydrogen is used in oxy-hydrogen flames for melting metals because it","options":["evolves a lot of heat when burnt","combines explosively with oxygen","is a very light gas","is a rocket fuel"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"What properties of duralumin make it more useful than its constituent metals?","options":["It is heavy with a high melting point","It is malleable and has high density","It is strong and light","It is hard and ductile"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The pair of metals in the reactivity series that are usually extracted by the electrolysis of their ores is","options":["magnesium and zinc","magnesium and calcium","copper and zinc","lead and calcium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A metal that can be extracted from cassitertite is","options":["cacium","magnesium","tin","copper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following metals is passive to concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid?","options":["Iron","Tin","Copper","Zinc"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The hydrocarbon that burns in air with a sooty flames is","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"2-methylprop-1-ene is an isomer of","options":["but-2-ene","pent-1-ene","2-methylbut-2-ene","2-methylbut-1-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following is a solvent for perfumes?","options":["C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"When excess ethanol is heated to 145<sup>o<\/sup>C in the presence of concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>, the product is","options":["ethyne","diethyl sulphate","diethyl ether","acetone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"POlyvinyl chloride is used to produce","options":["bread","pencils","ink","pipes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"An organic compound that does not undergo a reaction with both hydrogen cyanide and hydroxylamine can be","options":["alkene","alkanal","alkanone","alkanoic acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"When the two end alkyl groups ethyl ethanoate are interchange, the compound formed is known as","options":["methyl ethanoate","ethyl propanaote","methyl propanoate","propyl ethanoate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"From the diagram above the mass of crystals deposited when 1 dm <sup>3<\/sup> of a saturated solution of NaCl is cooled from 80 <sup>o<\/sup>C to 60<sup>o<\/sup>C is<br>\r\n[Na = 23, Cl = 35.5]","options":["117.00 g","58.50 g","11.70 g","5.85 g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"In the diagram above, Y is a mixture of","options":["calcium hydroxide and ammonium chloride","calcuim hydroxide and sodium chloride","sodium chloride and ammonuim trioxonitrate (V)","sodium dioxonitrate (lll) and ammouium chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Use the table above to answer this question . The element that is likely to participate in covalent rather than ionic bonding is","options":["Z","Y","X","W"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Use the table above to answer this question .The least reactive element is","options":["W","X","Y","Z"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"In the diagram above, the mixture of the solids P and Q can be separated by","options":["distillation","fractional distillation","crystallization","fractional crystallization"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the compounds above would react to take up two molecules of bromine durng bromination?","options":["l only","lll only","l and ll only","ll and lll only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The addition of water to calcium oxide leads to?","options":["a physical change","a chemical change","the formation of a mixture","an endothermic change"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A mixture of iron and sulphur can be separated by dissolving the mixture in?","options":["steam","dilute hydrochloric acid","dilute sodium hydroxide","benzene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A given amount of gas occupies 10.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at atm, and 273\u00b0C. The number of moles of the gas present is?<br>\r\n(Molar volume of a gas at s.t.p. = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>)","options":["0.89 mol","1.90 mol","3.80 mol","5.70 mol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"8.0 g of an element X react with an excess of copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (lV) solution to deposit 21.3 g of copper. The correct equation for the reaction is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Cu = 64).","options":["X<sub>(s)<\/sub>  + CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>   \u2192   Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  XSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>","X<sub>(s)<\/sub>  + 2CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>   \u2192   2Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  X(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2(aq)<\/sub>","2X<sub>(s)<\/sub>  + CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>   \u2192   Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  X<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>","2X<sub>(s)<\/sub>  + 3CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>   \u2192   3Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  X<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8(g)<\/sub> + 50<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  4H<sub>2<\/sub>O + 3CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>. Form the equation above the volume of oxygen at s.t.p. required to burn 50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of propane is?","options":["250 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","150 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","50 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen was collected over water at 27\u00b0C and 780 mm Hg. If the vapour pressure of water at the temperature of the experiment was 10 mm Hg, calculate the volume of the gas at 760 mm Hg and 7\u00b0C?","options":["40.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","35.7 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","28.4 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","25.2 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"If sulphur (IV) oxide and methane are released simultaneously at the opposite ends of a narrow tube, the rates of diffusion Rso<sub>2<\/sub> and Rch<sub>4<\/sub> will be in the ratio? <br>\r\n<br>\r\n(S = 32, O = 16, C = 12, H = 1)","options":["4:1","2:1","1:2","1:4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A solid begins to melt when?","options":["constituent particles acquires a greater kinetic energy","energy of vibration of particles of the solid is less than the intermolecular forces","constituent particles acquires energy above the average kinetic energy","energy of vibration of particles of the solid equals the intermolecular forces"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Which of the following electron configurations indicates an atom with the highest ionization energy?","options":["2,8,7","2,8,8,1","2,8,8,2","2,8,8,7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The line observed in the sample hydrogen spectrum are due to emission of?","options":["electrons from the atoms","energy by proton transition","energy by electron transition","neutron from the atom"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The property used in obtaining oxygen and nitrogen industrially from air is the?","options":["boiling point","density","rate of diffusion","solubility"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) is often added to impure water to?","options":["reduce organic impurities","reduce inorganic impurities","destroy bacteria and algae","remove permanent hardness"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The soil around a battery manufacturing factory is likely to contain a high concentration of?","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup> salts","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup> salts","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup> salts","Al<sup>3+<\/sup> salts"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Excess phosphorus was burnt in a gas jar and the residual gas passed successively over concentrated KOH solution and concentration H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> before being collected in a flask. The gases collected are?","options":["carbon (IV) oxide, nitrogen and the rare gases","nitrogen and the rare gases","carbon (IV) oxide, nitrogen (IV) oxide and the rare gases","carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"If an element X of an atomic number Z and mass number Y is irradiated by an intense concentration of neutrons, the relevant nuclear equation is?","options":["<sup>y<\/sup><sub>z<\/sub>X  +  <sup>1<\/sup><sub>0<\/sub>n  \u2192  <sup>y - 1<\/sup><sub>z + 1<\/sub>X","<sup>y<\/sup><sub>z<\/sub>X  +  <sup>1<\/sup><sub>0<\/sub>n  \u2192  <sup>y + 1<\/sup><sub>z<\/sub>X","<sup>y<\/sup><sub>z<\/sub>X  +  <sup>1<\/sup><sub>0<\/sub>n   \u2192   <sup>y<\/sup><sub>z + 1<\/sub>X","<sup>y<\/sup><sub>z<\/sub>X  +  <sup>1<\/sup><sub>0<\/sub>n  \u2192  <sup>y + 1<\/sup><sub>z - 1<\/sub>X"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"90.0g of MgCI<sub>2<\/sub> was placed in 50.0cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water to give a saturated solubility of the salt is 8.0 mol dm<sup>3<\/sup> at the same temperature, what is the mass of the salt left undissolved at the given temperature?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Mg = 24, Cl = 35.5)","options":["52.0g","58.5g","85.5g","88.5g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Soap lather is an example of a colloid in which a?","options":["liquid is dispersed in gas","solid is dispersed in liquid","gas is dispersed in liquid","liquid is despersed in liquid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The pH of a solution obtained by mixing 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 0.2M solution of NaOH is?","options":["1.3","7.0","9.7","12.7"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Mg<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +   2e<sup>-<\/sup>><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  Mg<sub>(s)<\/sub>E\u00b0<sub>(volts)<\/sub> = 2.370<br>\r\n<br>\r\nZn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +   2e<sup>-<\/sup>><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub>E\u00b0<sub>(volts)<\/sub> = -0.763<br>\r\n<br>\r\nCds<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 2e<sup>-<\/sup>><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  Cd<sub>(s)<\/sub>E\u00b0<sub>(volts)<\/sub> = 0.403<br>\r\n<br>\r\nCu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +   2e<sup>-<\/sup>><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>E\u00b0<sub>(volts)<\/sub> = 0.340<br>\r\n<br>\r\nIn the electrochemical series above, the strongest reducing agents is?","options":["Cu <sub>(s)<\/sub>","Cd<sub>(s)<\/sub>","Znsub>(s)<\/sub>","Mg<sub>(s)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"2Cl<sup>2(g)<\/sup> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub>    4HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub>  + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  <br>\r\n\u2206H\u00b0 = +115KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>. In the above equilibrium reaction, a decrease in temperature will?","options":["favour the reverse reaction","favour the forward reaction","have no effect on the equilibrium state","double the rate of the reverse raection"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"2X<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Y<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192  Z<sub>(g):<\/sub> In the equation above, The rate of formation of Z is found to be independent of the concentration of Y and to quadruple when the concentration of X is doubled. The correct equation for the reaction is?","options":["R = k (X)(Y)","R = K (X) \u00b0 (Y)","R = K (X) \u00b0 (Y) <sub>2<\/sub>","R = K (X) <sub>2<\/sub>(Y)\u00b0"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A gas that turns a filter  paper previously soaked in lead ethanoate solution black is?","options":["hyrogen chloride","hydrogen sulphide","sulphur (IV) oxide","sulphur (VI) oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"3CuO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  3Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub> N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> (i).<br>\r\n<br>\r\n2NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + 3Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  6HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub> + N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> (ii).<br>\r\n<br>\r\n4NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub> + 3O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  6H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub> + 2N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> (iii).<br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe reactions represented by the equations above demonstrate the?","options":["basic properties of ammonia","acidic properties of ammonia","reducing properties of ammonia","oxidizing properties of ammonia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A solution containing chloride ions gives white precipitate with silver trioxonitrate(V) Solution. The precipitate will be insoluble in dilute?","options":["HNO <sub>3<\/sub> but soluble in ammonia solution","HNO<sub>3<\/sub> and ammonia solution","HCl but soluble in ammonia solution","HCl and in ammonia solution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The oxide that remains unchanged when heated in hydrogen is?","options":["CuO","Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","PbO<sub>2<\/sub>","ZnO"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Which of the following is observed when a solution of iron (III) chloride is mixed with a solution of sodium hydroxide?","options":["A gas is evolved","A deep blue precipitate is formed","The resultant solution turns green turns","A brown precipitate is formed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The metal that will react with water only in the form of steam to librate hydrogen gas is?","options":["calcium","aluminium","iron","zinc"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A common characteristic shared by iron and aluminium is that both?","options":["are extracted by reduction methods","form only basic oxides","show oxidation states of +2 and +3","form soluble hydroxides"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Alloys are often used in preference to pure metals because?","options":["metals are too hard","merals are ductile","metallic properties are improve in alloys","alloys are a mixture of metals"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"One mole of hydrocarbon contains 6g of hydrogen. If the molecular weight is 54, the hydrocarbon is an?","options":["alkanone","alkane","alkene","alkyne"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"On cracking medicinal paraffin, a gas is evolved which gives a pop sound with a lighted splinter and an oily liquid which decolourizes bromine solution is also obtained. The products of the cracking are ?","options":["carbon (IV) oxide and alkyne","carbon (ll) oxide and alkene","hydrogen gas and alkene","hydrogen gas and alkane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"How many structural isomers can be drawn for the non-cyclic alkanol with molecular formula C <sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>O?","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An example of aromatic compound is?","options":["C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>13<\/sub>OH","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>13<\/sub>CI","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>14<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Terylene is synthesized from ethane- 1, 2-diol and benzene - 1, 4-dicarboxylic acid by?","options":["addition reaction","condensation reaction","elimination reaction","substitution reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Which of the following is true concerning the properties of benzene and hexane?","options":["Both undergo substitution reaction","Both undergo addition reaction","Both are solids","Both can decolourized bromine water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The diagram above represents an atom that can combine with chlorine to form","options":["a covalent bond","an electrovalent bond","a hydrogen bond","a co-ordinate bond"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"In the diagram above , the activation energy for the backward reaction is","options":["+5kJ","+15KJ","+25KJ","+30KJ"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"In the experiment above, X could be a solution of","options":["sodium trioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","sodium trioxonitrate (lll) and ammonium chloride","lead (ll) trioxonitrate (V) and copper turnings","potassium trioxonitrate (V) and copper turnings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"35 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen was sparked with 12 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen at 110\u00b0C and 760mm Hg to produce steam. What percentage of the total volume of gas left after the reaction is hydrogen?","options":["11%","31%","35%","69%"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"2.85g of an oxide of copper gave 2.52g of copper on reduction and 1.90g of another oxide gave 1.52g of copper on reduction. The data above illustrates the law of?","options":["constant composition","conservation of mass","reciprocal proportions","multiple proportions"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"An element, X, forms a volatile hydride XH<sub>3<\/sub> with a vapour density of 17.0. The relative atomic mass of X is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(H = 1)","options":["34.0","31.0","20.0","14.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A mixture of 0.20 mole of Ar, 0.20 mole of N<sub>2<\/sub> and 0.30 mole of He exerts a total pressure of 2.1  atm. The partial pressure of He in the mixture is?","options":["0.90 atm","0.80 atm","0.70 atm","0.60 atm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The temperature of a body decreases when drops of liquid placed on it evaporate because?","options":["the atmospheric vapour pressure has a cooling effect on the body","a temperature gradient exists between the drops of liquid and the body causing the latter to vaporate","the heat of vapourization is drawn from the body causing it to cool","the random motion of the liquid molecules causes a cooling effect on the body"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The electron configuration of two elements with similar chemical properties are represented by?","options":["1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>5<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>4<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>4<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>1<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>1<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>1<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>4<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"In the periodic table,  what is the property that decreases along the periodic and increases down the group?","options":["Atomic number","Electron affinity","Ionization potential","Atomic radius"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Two elements, P and Q with atomic numbers 11 and 8 respectively , combine chemically to form the compound P<sub>x<\/sub>Q<sub>Y<\/sub>. The respective values of x and y are?","options":["1 and 1","1 and 2","2 and 1","3 and 1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Oxygen is a mixture of two isotopes O and O with relative abundances of 90% and 10% respectively. The relative atomic mass of oxygen is?","options":["16.0","16.2","17.0","18.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"If 30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen diffuses through porous plug in 7s, how long will it take 60 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of chlorine to diffuse through the same plug?","options":["12s","14s","21s","30s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"200 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air was passed over heated copper in a syringe several times to produce copper (II) oxide.<br>\r\nWhen cooled, the final volume of air recorded was 158cm<sup>3<\/sup>. Estimate the percentage of oxygen in the air?","options":["31%","27%","21%","19%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"On recrystallization, 20g of magnesium tetraoxosuphate (IV) forms 41 g of magnesium tetraoxosulphate (IV) crystals, MgSO<sub>4<\/sub>. yH<sub>2<\/sub>O. The value of y is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Mg = 24, S = 32, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["1","3","5","7"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following gases is the most dangerous pollutant?","options":["Hydrogen sulphide","Carbon (lV) oxide","Sulphur (lV) oxide","Carbon (ll) oxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A major process involved in the softening of hard water is the?","options":["conversation of a soluble calcium salt to its trioxoncarbonate (lV)","decomposition of calcium rioxocarbonate (lV)","conversion of an insoluble calcium salts to its trioxocarbonate (lV)","oxidation of calcium atoms to its ions"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A saturated solution of AgCl was found to have a concentration of 1.30 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>. The solubility product of AgCl therefore is?","options":["1.30 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup> mol<sub>2<\/sub> dm<sup>-6<\/sup>","1.30 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> mol<sub>2<\/sub> dm<sup>-6<\/sup>","1.69 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup> mol<sub>2<\/sub> dm<sup>-6<\/sup>","2.60  x 10<sup>-12<\/sup> mol<sub>2<\/sub> dm<sup>-6<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The hydroxyl ion concentrated, (OH<sup>-<\/sup>), in a solution of sodium hydroxide of pH 10.0 is?","options":["10<sup>-10<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","10<sup>-6<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","10<sup>-4<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","10<sup>-2<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the aqueous solutions with the pH values below will liberate hydrogen when it react with magnesium metals?","options":["13.0","7.0","6.5","3.0"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Given that 15.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of H<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\nSO<sub>4<\/sub> was required to completely neutralize 25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.125 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup> NaOH, calculate the molar concentration of the acid solution:","options":["0.925 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.156mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.104 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.023 mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"When platinum electrodes are used during the electrolysis of copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (lV) solution, the solution gets progressively?","options":["acidic","basic","neutral","amphoteric"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"How many Faraday of electricity are required to deposit 0.20 mole of nickel, if 0.10 Faraday of electricity deposited 2.98g of nickel during electrolysis of its aqueous solution?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Ni = 58.7, 1F = 96 500 C mol<sup>-<\/sup>)","options":["0.20","0.30","0.40","0.50"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"What is the oxidation number of Z in K<sub>3<\/sub>ZCl<sub>6<\/sub>?","options":["-3","+3","-6","+6"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"2H<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>(g)<\/sub> + SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>  \u2192  3S<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>..........(i) 3CuO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  3Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub> + N<sub>2(g)<\/sub>.........(II) In the equations above, the oxidizing agent (I) and the reducing agent in (II) respectively are?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub> and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and CuO","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub> and CuO"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>     2SO<sub>3<\/sub>. In the reaction above, the standard heats of formation of SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> and SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub> are -297 KJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup> respectively. The heat change of the reaction is?","options":["-99 kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","-198 kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+198 kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+683kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"If the rate law obtained for a given reaction is rate = k(X)<sup>n<\/sup> (Y)<sup>m<\/sup>, what is the overall order of the reaction?","options":["nm","n\/m","n + m","n - m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"One method of driving the position of equilibrium of an endothermic reaction forward is to?","options":["increase temperature at constant pressure","dcrease pressure at constant temperature","cool down the apparatus with water","decreases temperature at constant  pressure"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Oxidation of concentrated hydrochloric acid with manganese (IV) oxide liberates a gas used in the?","options":["manufacture of tooth pastes","treatment of simple golitre","vulcanization of rubber","sterilization of water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"mE + nF  \u2192  pG + qH. In the equation above, the equilibrium constant is given by?","options":["(E)<sup>m<\/sup>(F)<sup>n<\/sup>\/ (G)<sup>n<\/sup>(H)<sup>q<\/sup>","(E)(F) \/ (G)(H)","(G)<sup>p<\/sup>(H)<sup>q<\/sup> \/ (E)<sup>m<\/sup>(F)<sup>n<\/sup>","(G)(H) \/ (E)(F)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A compound that will NOT produce oxygen  on heating is?","options":["potasium dioxonitrate (III)","lead (IV) oxide","potassium trioxochlorate (V)","potassium trioxonitrate (V)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Coal gas is made up of carbon (II) oxide, hydrogen and?","options":["nitrogen","air","argon","methane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"2X<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + MnO<sub>2(s)<\/sub> + 4H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  X<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + Mn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O.<br>\r\nThe reaction above can be used for the laboratory preparation of all halogens except fluorine because it is?","options":["a poisionous gas","an oxidizing agent","electronegative in nature","highly reactive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The removal of rust from iron by  treatment with tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid is based on the?","options":["hydrolysis of the iron","reaction of acid with base","oxidationof the rust","dehydration of the iron"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the additives could improve the quality of steel?","options":["Silicon","Sulphur and phosphorus","Carbon","Chromium and nickel"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Sodium hydroxide is prepared commercially from sodium chloride solution by?","options":["electrolysis using mercury as cathode","hydrolysis in steam using a catalyst","electrolysis using iron as anode","treating sodium chloride with ammonia and carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A sample of a substance containing only C and H burns in excess O<sub>2<\/sub> to yield 4.4g of CO<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\n and 2.7 g of H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The empirical formula of a substance is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(C = 12, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>24<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"An undesirable paraffin in the petroleum industry which is particularly prone to knocking is?","options":["iso-octane","n-heptane","iso-heptane","n-octane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The reaction of an alkanol with an alkanoic acid in the presence of concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> will produce an?","options":["alkanal","alkanoate","alkanone","alkyne"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The final product of the reaction of ethyne with hydrogen iodine is?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>\u2014CHI<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>l\u2014CH<sub>2<\/sub>I","CH<sub>3<\/sub>\u2014CI<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CHI"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Synthetic rubber obtained by the polymerization of chlorobutadiene in the presence of sodium is called?","options":["teflon","isoprene","polythene","neoprene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The synthetic detergents are preferred to soap for laundry using hard water because?","options":["detergents are water soluble while soap is not","the calcium salts of detergents are water soluble","the magnesium salt of soap is soluble in hard water","soap does not have a hydrocarbon terminal chain"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.02 M KOH neutralized 0.03 g of a monobasic organic acid having the general formula C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n + 1<\/sub> COOH. The molecular formula of the acid is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(C = 12, H = 1, O = 16)","options":["HCOOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>COOH"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"(1 \/(2) N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + (1) \/ (2)O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2206H\u00b0 89 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>. If the entropy change for the reaction above at 25\u00b0C is 11.8 J mol<sup>-<\/sup>, calculate the change in free energy. \u2206G\u00b0, for the reaction at 25\u00b0C?","options":["88.71 KJ","85.48 KJ","-204.00 KJ","-3427.40 KJ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question. A sample, X, solid at room temperature, was melted, heated to a temperature of 358 K and allowed to cool as shown in OPQR. The section PQ indicates that X is","options":["a mixture of salts","a hydrated salt","an ionic salt","a pure compound"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question. A sample, X, solid at room temperature, was melted, heated to a temperature of 358 K and allowed to cool as shown in OPQR.The section OP suggests that X is in the","options":["liquid sate","solid\/liquid state","solid state","gaseous state"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"In the diagram above the gas Y could be","options":["hydrogen chloride","oxygen","carbon (IV) oxide","chlorine"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature of the organic compound with the above structural formula is","options":["3-ethyl-2,5-dimethylhexane","4-ethyl-2,5-dimethylhexane","3-ethyl-2,5,5 - trimethylpentane","3-ethyl, 1,1,4-trimethylpentane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"How many more isomers of the compound above can be obtained ?","options":["5","4","3","2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Choose the correct answer from the options above. When Fehling is solution is added to two isomeric carbonyl compounds X and Y with the molecular formula C <sub>5<\/sub>H <sub>10<\/sub>O, compound X gives a red precipitate while Y does not react. It can be inferred that X is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The compound above contains","options":["Sp <sup>3<\/sup> hybridized carbon atoms only","Sp <sup>2<\/sup> hybridized carbon atoms only","Sp <sup>3<\/sup> and Sp hybirdized carbon atoms","Sp <sup>3<\/sup> and Sp <sup>2<\/sup hybridized carbon atoms>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The compound above is the product of the oxidation of","options":["2-methlbutan-2-ol","2-methylbutan -1- ol","2, 3-dimethylprop 1-ol","Pentan -2- ol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Chromatography is used to separate components of mixtures which differ in their rates of?","options":["diffusion","migration","reaction","sedimentaion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following is a example of a chemical change?","options":["Dissoultion of salt in water","Rusting of iron","Melting of ice","Separating a mixture by distillation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The number of hydrogen ions in 4.9 g of tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(S = 32, O =16, H = 1, Na = 6.02 x 10<sub>23<\/sub>","options":["3.01 x 10<sub>22<\/sub>","6.02 x 10<sub>22<\/sub>","3.01 x 10<sub>23<\/sub>","6.01 x 10<sub>23<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"What volume of oxygen will remain after reacting 8cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen with 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen?","options":["10 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","12 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","14 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","16 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A gas sample with an initial volume of 3.25 dm<sup>3<\/sup> is heated and allowed to expand to 9.75 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at constant pressure. What is the ratio of the final absolute temperature to the initial absolute temperature?","options":["3:1","5:2","5:4","8:3"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Two cylinders A and B each contains 30 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of<br>\r\noxygen and nitrogen respectively at the same temperature and pressure. If there are 5.0 moles of nitrogen, then the mass of oxygen is?","options":["3.2 g","6.4 g","80.0 g","160.0 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A liquid begins to boil when?","options":["its vapour pressure is equal to the vapour pressure of its solid at the given temperature","molecules start escaping from its surface","its vapour pressure equals the atmosphere pressure","its volume is sightly increased"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A particle that contains 8 proton, 9 neutrons and 7 electrons could be written as?","options":["O","O<sup>+<\/sup>","O<sup>+<\/sup>","O<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In the oil drop experiment, Millikan determined the?","options":["charge to mass ratio of the electron","mass of the electron","charge of the electron","mass of the proton"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The ability of ionic solids is generally due to the?","options":["negative electron affinity of most atoms","crystal lattice forces","electron pair sharing","positive ionization potentials"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is FALSE about isotopes of the same element?","options":["They have the same number of electrons in their outermost shells","They have different atomic masses","They have the same atomic number and the number of electrons","They have the same atomic number but different umber of elelctrons"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Helium  is often used in observation balloons because it is?","options":["light and combustible","light and non-combustible","heavy and combustible","heavy and non-combustible"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Deliquescent substances are also?","options":["efflorescent","anhydrous","hygroscopic","insoluble"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"When plastics and packaging materials made from chloroethene are burnt in the open, the mixture of gases released into the atmosphere is most likely to contain?","options":["ethane","chlorine","hydrogen chloride","ethene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The difference between colloides and and suspensions is brought out clearly by the fact that while colloids?","options":["do not scatter light, suspensions do","can be separated by filtration, suspension cannot be so separated","can be separated by a membrane, suspensions cannot","do not settle out on standing, suspensions do"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In general, an increase in temperature increases the solubility of a solute in water because?","options":["more solute molecules collide with each other","most solutes dissolve with the evoltion of heat","more solute molecules dissociate at hihger temperatures","most solutes dissolve with absorption of heat"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Neutralization involves a reaction between H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup> and?","options":["CI<sup>-<\/sup>","OH<sup>-<\/sup>","NO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>","CO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In the process of silver-plating a metal M, the metal M is the?","options":["anode and a driect current is used","cathode and an alternating current is used","anode and an alternating current is used","cathode and a direct current is used"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"How many moles of copper would be deposited by passing 3F of electricity through a solution of copper (II) tetraoxosulpohate (IV)? <br>\r\n<br>\r\n(F = 96 500 C mol<sup>-<\/sup>)","options":["0.5","1.0","1.5","3.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"2CL<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  CI<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  +  2e<sup>-(aq)<\/sup>. The above half-cell reaction occuring at the anode during the electrolysis of dilute ZnCI<sub>2<\/sub> solution is?","options":["ionization","oxidation","reduction","recombination"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following is a redox reaction?","options":["KCI<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  KHSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>  +  HCI<sub>(aq)<\/sub>","2FeBr<sub>2(aq)<\/sub>  +  Br<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  2FeBr<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>","3AgNO<sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +  FeCl<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192   3AgCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Fe(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)2-<\/sub>  +  CO<sub>2(g)<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 14H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +  6l<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  2Cr<sup>3+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  + 3l<sub2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  +  7H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>.<br>\r\nThe change in the oxidation number of oxygen in the equation above is?","options":["0","1","2","7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"If an  equilibrium reaction has \u2206H < O, the reaction will proceed favorably in the forward reaction at?","options":["low temperatures","high temperatures","all temperatures","all pressures"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following processes leads to increase in entropy?","options":["Mixing a sample of NaCl and sand","Condensation of water vapour","Boiling a sample of water","Cooling a saturated solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following equilibria is shifted to the right as a result of an increase in pressure?","options":["H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + I<sub>2(g)<\/sub>        2HI<sub>(g)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>         N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub>","PCl<sub>5(s)<\/sub>            PCl<sub>3(s)<\/sub>  +  Cl<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2O<sub>3(g)<\/sub>        3O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In the industrial production of hydrogen from natural gas, carbon (IV) oxide produced along with the hydrogen is removed by?","options":["washing under pressure","passing the mixture into lime water","using ammoniacal copper (l) chloride","drying over phoshorus (V) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Sulphur exists in six forms in the solid state. This property is known as?","options":["isomerism","allotropy","isotopy","isomorphism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A gas that will turn orange potassium heptaoxodichromate (lV) solution  to clear green is?","options":["sulphur (lV) oxide","hydrogen sulphide","sulphide (lV) oxide","hydrogen chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following ions will give a white precipitate with aqueous NaOH and soluble in excess of the base?","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cu<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In the extraction of iron in the blast furnace, limestone is used to?","options":["release CO<sub>2<\/sub> for the reaction","reduce the iron ore","increase the strenght of the iron","remove impurities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will impart a brick-red colour to a non-luminious bunsen flame?","options":["NaCl","LiCl","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","MgCl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Group 1 A metals are not found free in nature because they?","options":["are of low melting and boiling points","have weak metallic bonding","conduct electricity and heat","are very reactive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"CHCl<sub>3<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192  HCl + CCl<sub>4<\/sub>. The reaction above is an example of?","options":["an addition reaction","a substitution reaction","a chlorination reaction","a condensation reaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs has compounds that are isomers?","options":["Propanal and propanone","Ethanoic acid and ethylmethanoate","Ethanoic acid and ethane-1, 2-diol","2-methylbutane and 2, 2-dimethylbutane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Aromatic and aliphatic hydrocarbons can be distinguished from each other by the?","options":["action of bromine","use of polymerization  reaction","action of heat","use of oxidation reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The role of sodium chloride in the preparation of soap is to?","options":["purify the soap","separate the soap from glycerol","accelerate the decomposition of the fat or oil","react with glycerol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"C<sub>x<\/sub>H<sub>Y<\/sub> + 4O<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192  3CO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The hydrocarbon, C<sub>x<\/sub>H<sub>Y<\/sub>, in the reaction above is?","options":["propane","propene","propyne","propanone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"An example of a secondary amine is?","options":["propylene","di-butylamine","methylamine","trimethylamine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The relatively high boiling points of alkanols are due to?","options":["ionic bonding","aromatic character","covalent bonding","hydrogen bonding"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"USE THE SECTION OF THE PERIODIC TABLE ABOVE TO ANSWER THIS QUESTION.Which of the indicate an alkali metal and a noble gas respectively?","options":["M and E","G and E","R and L","G and L"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"USE THE SECTION OF THE PERIODIC TABLE ABOVE TO ANSWER THIS QUESTION.Which letter represents a non-metal that is a solid at room temperature?","options":["T","R","J","X"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The arrangement above can be used for the collection of","options":["sulphur (IV) oxide","ammonia","hydrogen chloride","nitrogen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Use the diagram above to answer this question. The activation energy of the uncatalysed reaction is","options":["X","X + Y","X - Y","Y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"It can be deduced that the rate of the reaction","options":["for bath l is higher than path ll","for path ll is higher than path l","is the same for both paths at all temperatures","depends  on the values of both x and y at all pressures"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The option above shows the PH changes for the titration of a","options":["strong acid versus strong base","weak acid versus strong base","strong acid versus weak base","weak acid versus weak base"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The functional group represented in the compound above is","options":["alkanol","alanal","alkanone","alanoate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A mixture of sand, ammonium chloride and sodium chloride is best separated by?","options":["sublimation followed by addition of water and filteration","sublimation followed by addition of  water and evaporation","addition of water followed by filtration and sublimation","addition of water followed by crystallization and sublimation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A pure solid usually melts?","options":["over a wide range of temperature","over a narrow range of temperature","at a lower temperature than the impure one","at the same temperature as the impure one"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"At the same temperature and pressure, 50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of nitrogen gas contains the same number of molecules as?","options":["25 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of methane","40 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen","50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of ammonia","100 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of chlorine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"8g CH<sub>4<\/sub> occupies 11.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at s.t.p. What volume would 22 g of CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub> occupy under the same condition?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(C = 12, H = 1)","options":["3.7 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","33.6 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"To what temperature must a gas 273 K be heated in order to double both its volume and pressure?","options":["298 K","546 K","819 K","1092 K"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"For a gas, the relative molecular mass is equal to 2Y. What is Y?","options":["The mas of the gas","The vapour density of the gas","The volume of the gas","The temperature of the gas"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The densities of two gases, X and Y, are 0.5 g dm<sup>-3<\/sup> and 2.0 dm<sup>-3<\/sup> respectively.<br>\r\nWhat is the rate of diffusion of X relative to Y?","options":["0.1","0.5","2.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The shape of ammonia molecule is?","options":["trigonal planar","octahedral","square planar","tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"An increase in  temperature causes an increase in the pressure of a gas because?","options":["it decreases the number of collision between the molecules","the molecules of the gas bombard the walls of the container more frequently","it increases the number of collision between the molecules","it causes the molecules to combine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The number of electrons in the valence shell of an element of atomic number 14 is?","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following physical properties decreases down a group in the periodic table?","options":["Atomic radius","Ionic radius","Electropositivity","Electronegativity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Element X, Y and Z belong to a groups I, V and VII respectively. Which of the following is TRUE about the bond types of XZ and YZ<sub>3<\/sub>?","options":["Both are electrovalent","Both are covalent","XZ is electrovalent  and YZ<sub>3<\/sub>  is covalent","XZ is covalent and YZ<sub>3<\/sub> is electrovalent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A solid that absorbs water from he atmosphere and forms an aqueous solution is?","options":["hydrophilic","efforescent","deliquescent","hygroscopic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A major effect of oil pollution in coastal waters is the?","options":["destruction of marine life","desalination of the water","increase in the acidity of the water","detoxification of the water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Sodium chloride has no solubility product value because of its?","options":["saline nature","high solubility","low solubility","insolubility"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The solubility, in moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup> of 20.2 g of potassium trioxonitrate (V) dissolve in 100 g of the resulting mixture is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(K = 39, O = 16, N =14).","options":["0.10","0.20","1.00","2.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following atoms represents deuterium?","options":["No protons = 1, No of neutrons = 0, No of electrons = 0","No protons = 1, No of neutrons = 0, No of electrons = 1","No protons = 1, No of neutrons = 1, No of electrons = 1","No protons = 1, No of neutrons = 2, No of electrons = 1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A few drops of concentrated PCI are added to about 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a solution of pH 3.4. The pH of the resulting mixtures is?","options":["less than 3.4","greater  than 3.4","unaltered","the same as that of pure water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is a base?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CaO","H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOCH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 2.0 M solution of ethanoic acid was added to excess of 0.05 M sodium hydroxide. The mass of the salt produced is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Na = 23, C = 12, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["2.50 g","2.73 g","3.28 g","4.54 g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"What volume of oxygen measured at s.t.p would be liberated on electrolysis by 9650 coulombs of electricity?<br><br>\r\n<br><br>\r\n(Molar volume of gas = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>, F = 96,500 C mol<sup>-<\/sup>)","options":["22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.12 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.560 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Crude copper could be purified by the electrolysis of concentrated copper (II) chloride if the crude copper is?","options":["made both the anode and the cathode","made the cathode","made the anode","dissolved in the solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"H<sup>-<\/sup> + H<sub>2(I)<\/sub>O  \u2192  H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + OH<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>. From the equation above, it can be inferred that the?","options":["reaction is a double decomposition","hydride ion is a reducing agent","hydride ion is an oxidizing agent","reaction is neutralization"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"An anhydride is an oxide of non-mental?","options":["which will not dissolve in water","whose solution in water has a pH greater than 7","whose solution in water has a pH less than 7","whose solution in water has a pH of 7"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"MnO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 8H + <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 5Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>  \u2192  Mn<sup>2+(aq)<\/sup> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>. The oxidation number of manganese in the above reaction changed from?","options":["+7 to +2","+6 to +2","+5 to +2","+4 to +2"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is TRUE of Le Chatelier's Principle for an exothermic reaction?","options":["Increase in temperature will cause an increase in the equilibrium constant","Increase in temperature will cause a decrease in the equilibrium constant","Addition of a catalyst will cause an increase in the equilibrium constant","Addition of a catalyst will cause a decrease in the equilibrium constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following are produced when ammonium trioxonitrate (V) crystals are cautiously heated in a hard glass round bottomed flask?","options":["N<sub>2<\/sub>O and steam","NO<sub>2<\/sub> and ammonia","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub> and NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO and NO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of these metals CANNOT replace hydrogen from alkaline solutions?","options":["Alulinium","Zinc","Tin","Iron"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Clothes should be properly rinsed with water after bleaching because?","options":["the bleach decolourizes the cothes","chlorine reacts with fabrics during bleaching","the clothes are sterilized during bleaching","hydrogen chloride solution is produced during bleaching"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of these solutions will give a white precipitate with a solution of barium chloride acidified with hydrochloric acid?","options":["Sodium trioxocarbonate (IV)","Sodium tetraoxosulphate  (IV)","Sodium trioxosulphate (IV)","Sodium sulphide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"SO<sub>3<\/sub> is NOT directly dissolved in water in the preparation of H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> by the contact process because?","options":["the reaction between SO<sub>3<\/sub> and water is violently exothermic","acid is usually added to water and never water to acid","SO<sub>3<\/sub> does not dissolve in water readily","SO<sub>3<\/sub> is an acid gas"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"In an electrolytic set-up to protect iron from corrosion, the iron is?","options":["made cathode","made anode","used with a metal of lower electropositive potential","initially coated with tin"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT true of metals?","options":["They are good conductors of electricity","They ionize by electron loss","Their oxides are acidic","They have high melting points"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is the correct order of decreasing activity of the metals Fe, Ca, Al and Na?","options":["Fe> Ca> Al> Na","Na> Ca> Al> Fe","Al> Fe> Na> Ca","Ca> Na> Fe>, Al"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is NOT an isomers of 2,2 dimethylbutane?","options":["2-methylbutane","3-methylpentane","2,3-dimethylbutane","2-methylpentane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"When sodium is added to ethanol, the products are?","options":["sodium hydroxide and water","sodium hydroxide and hydrogen","sodium ethoxide and water","sodium ethoxide and hydrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The general formula of alkanoates is?","options":["RCHO","R<sub>2<\/sub>CO","RCOOH","RCOOR"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"One mole of a hydrocarbon contains 48 g of carbon. If it vapour density is 28, the hydrocarbon is?","options":["an alkane","an alkene","an alkyne","aromatic (C = 12, H = 1)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following reagents will confirm the presence of unsaturation in a compound?","options":["Fehling's solution","Bromine water","Tollen's reagent","Benedict's solution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The diagram above represents an atom of","options":["magnesium","helium","chlorine","neon"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The set-up above would be useful for determining the amount of","options":["oxygen in air","water vapour in air","CO<sub>2<\/sub> in air","arygen in air"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The \u2206H for the reaction represented by the energy profile above is","options":["-100 kJ mol-<sup>-1<\/sup>","+ 100 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","+50 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","-50 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"In the diagram above the activation energy is represented by","options":["y - x","x","x - z","y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"2HCL<sub>(ag)<\/sub> + CaCO<sub>3(ag)<\/sub> \u2192 CaCL<sub>2(ag)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub> + CO from the reaction above, which of the following curves represents the consumption of calcium trioxocarbonate (IV) as dilute HCL is added to it?","options":["L","M","N","P"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"In the diagram above, R is a mixture of","options":["potassium tetraxochlorate (VII) and concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","potassium trioxochlorate (V) and concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","potassium tetratoxomanganate (VII) and concentrated HCI","manganes (IV) oxide and concentrated HCI"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The IUPAC name of the compound above is","options":["2,2-dimethyl but -1-yne","2,2-dmethyl but -1-ene","3,3-dimethyl but -1-ene","3,3-dimethyl but-1-yne"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Use the diagram above to answer this question. The reaction taking place in flask G is known as","options":["hydrolysis","double decomposition","dehydration","pyrolysis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"MnO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 8H + 5Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> \\(\\to\\) Mn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 5Fe<sup>3+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The oxidation number of maganese in the above reaction changed from","options":["+7 to +2","+6 to +2","+5 to +2","+4 to +2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"which of these metals CANNOT replace hydrogen from alkaline solutions?","options":["Aluminium","Zinc","Tin","Iron"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Clothes should be properly rinsed with water after bleaching because","options":["the bleach decolourizes the clothes","chlorine reacts with fabrics during bleaching","the clothes are sterilized during bleaching","hydrogen chloride solution is produced during bleaching"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"When sodium ethanoate is treated with a few drops of concentrated tetraoxosulphate(vi)acid. one of the products is","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOC<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>COOCH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"From the above diagram; The caustic soda in the conical flask serves to","options":["dry ethene gas","remove carbon (iv) oxides from ethene","remove carbon (ii) oxide from ethene","remove sulphur (iv) oxide from ethene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is a mixture?","options":["Sulphur powder","Bronze","Distilled water","Ethanol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A balanced chemical equation obeys the law of?","options":["conservation of mass","difinite proportions","multiple proportions","conservation of energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"How many moles of oxygen molecules would be produced from the decomposition  of 2.50 moles of potassium trioxochlorate (V)?","options":["2.50","3.50","3.75","7.50"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"For iodine crystals to sublime on heating, the molecules must acquire energy that is?","options":["less than the forces odf attraction in the solid","equal to the forces of attraction in th solid","necessary to melt the solid","greater than the forces of attraction in both the solid and the liquid phases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"An element, E, has the electronic configuration 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>p<sup>3<\/sup>. The reaction of E with a halogen X can give?","options":["EX<sub>3<\/sub> and EX<sub>5<\/sub>","EX<sub>3<\/sub> only","EX<sub>5<\/sub> only","EX<sub>2<\/sub> and EX<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Two atoms represented as U and U are?","options":["isomers","allotropes","isotopes","anomers"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"As the difference in electronegativity  between bonded atoms increases, polarity of the bond?","options":["decreases","increases","remains unchanged","reduces to zero"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which group of elements forms hydrides that are pyramidal in structure?","options":["III","IV","V","VI"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Water has a rather high boiling point despite its low molecular mass because of the presence of?","options":["hydrogen bonding","covalent bonding","ionic bonding","metallic bonding"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Argon is used in gas-filled electric lamp because it helps to?","options":["prevent the reduction of the lamp fillaments","prevent oxidation of the lamp fillaments","make the lamp fillament glow brightly","keep the atmosphere in the lamp inert"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The air around a petroleum refinery is most likely to contain?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub>, SO<sub>3<\/sub> and N<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO<sub>2<\/sub>,  CO and N<sub>2<\/sub>O","SO<sub>2<\/sub>, CO and NO<sub>2<\/sub>","PH<sub>3<\/sub> H<sub>2<\/sub>O and CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Water can be identified by the use of?","options":["anhydrous copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI)","anhydrous sodium trioxocarbonate (IV)","potassium heptaoxochromate (VII)","copper (II) trioxocaronate (IV)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The phenomenon whereby sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) decahydrate loses  some of its water of crystallization on exposure to the atmosphere is known as?","options":["deliquescene","hygroscopy","effervescence","efflorescence"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A student prepares 0.5 M solution each of hydrochloric and ethanoic acids and then measured pH. The result would show that the?","options":["pH values are equal","HCI solution has a higher pH","sum of the values is 14","ethanoic acid solution has a higher pH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"NH<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup><br>\r\n \u2192  NH<sub>4<\/sub><sup>+<\/sup> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O. It may be deduced from the reaction above that?","options":["a redox reaction has occurred","H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup> acts as an oxidizing agent","H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup> acts as an acid","water acts as ab acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"4.0 g of sodium hydroxide in 250 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of solution contains?","options":["0.40 moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.10 moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.04 moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.02 moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"During the electrolysis of a salt of a metal M, a current of 0.5 A flows from for 32 minutes 10 seconds and deposits 0.325 g of M, What is the charge of the metal ion?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(M = 65, If = 96,500 C per mole of electron)","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the reactions occurs at the anode during the electrolysis of a very dilute aqueous solution of sodium chloride?","options":["OH<sup>-<\/sup> - e \u2192 OH","CIsup>-<\/sup> - e \u2192 CI","OHsup>-<\/sup> + CIsup>-<\/sup>HCI + O<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>+<\/sub> - esup>-<\/sup> Hg (Na)\/(Hg) amalgam"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The oxidation states of chlorine in HOCL, HCLO<sub>3<\/sub> and HCLO<sub>4<\/sub> are respectively?","options":["-1, +5, and +7","-1, -5 and 7","+1, +3 and +4","+1, +5 and +7"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A reaction takes places spontaneously if?","options":["\u2206G  = O","\u2206S < O and \u2206H > O","\u2206H < T \u2206S","\u2206G > O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The standard enthalpies of formation of CO<sub>2(g),<\/sub> H<sub>2<\/sub>O(g) and CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> in kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup> are -394, -242 and -110 respectively. What is the standard enthalpy change for the reaction CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>O \u2192 CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>?","options":["-42 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+42 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","-262 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+262 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"10g of a solid is in equilibrium with its own vapour.<br>\r\nWhen 1 g of a small amount of solid is added, the vapour pressure?","options":["remains the same","drops","increases by 1%","increases by 99%"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"NaCI<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(I)<\/sub>  \u2192  HCI<sub>(g)<\/sub> + NaHSO<sub>4(s)<\/sub>.<br>\r\nIn the reaction above, H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> behaves as?","options":["a strong acid","an oxidizing agent","a good solvent","a dehydrating agent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of these gases can be dried with concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>?","options":["HBr","H<sub>2<\/sub>S","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of these salts will produce its metal, oxygen and nitrogen (IV) oxide on heating?","options":["Silver and trioxonitrate  (V)","Sodium trioxonitrate  (V)","Calcium trioxonitrate (V)","Lithium trioxonitrate (V)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"An experiment produces a gaseous mixtures of carbon (IV) oxide and carbon (II) oxide. In order to obtain pure carbon (II) oxide, the gas mixture should be?","options":["passed over heated copper (II) oxide","bubbled through concentrated tetraoxosulphate (IV)  acid","bubbled through sodium hydroxide solution","bubbled through water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following is a property of ionic chlorides?","options":["They can be decomposed by heat","They react with aqueous AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> to give a white precipiate which is soluble in excess ammonia","They explode when in contact with dry ammonia","They react with concentrated tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid to give white fumes of chlorine gas"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"When dilute aqueous solutions of lead (II) nitrate and potassium bromide are mixed, a precipitate is observed.<br>\r\nThe products of this reaction are?","options":["PbO<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  Br<sup>-<\/sup>  +  KNO<sub>3<\/sub>","Br<sub>2<\/sub>  +  NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  +  PbBr<sub>2(s)<\/sub>","PbO<sub>(s)<\/sub>  +  K<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>    +  Br<sub>(aq)<\/sub>  + NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","PbBr<sub>2(s)<\/sub>  +  K<sub>(aq)<\/sub>  +  K<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> +  NO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Bronze is an alloy of?","options":["silver and copper","silver and gold","copper and nickle","copper and zinc","copper and tin"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The active reducing agent in the blast furnace for the extraction of iron is?","options":["carbon","limestone","carbon(II)oxide","calcium oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The fraction of crude oil used as jet fuel is?","options":["refinery gas","diesel oil","kerosene","gasoline"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"It is not desirable to use lead tetraethyl as an anti-knock agent because?","options":["it is expensive","of pollution effects from the exhaust fumes","it lowers the octane rating of petrol","it is explosive"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(s)<\/sub>  +  3H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  Al<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>) + 3H<sub>2(I)<\/sub>O<br>\r\nAl<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(s)<\/sub>  +  2NaOH<sub>(aq)<\/sub>)  +  3H<sub>2(I)<\/sub>O  \u2192  2NaAl(OH)<sub>4(aq)<\/sub>).<br>\r\nWe can conclude from the equations above that Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(s)<\/sub> is?","options":["an acidic oxide","an amphoteric oxide","a basic oxide","a neutral oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The carbon atoms on ethane are?","options":["sp<sup>2<\/sup>  hybridized","sp<sup>3<\/sup>  hybridized","sp<sup>2<\/sup>d hybridized","sp hybridized"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Palm wine turns sour with time because?","options":["the sugar content is converted into alcohol","the carbon (IV) oxide formed during the fermentation process has a sour taste","it is commonly adulterated by the tappers and sellers","microbial activity results in the production of orgain acids within it"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Catalytic hydrogenation of benzene produces?","options":["an aromatic hydrocarbon","margarine","cyclohexane","D.D.T"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following represents saponification?","options":["Reaction of carboxylic acids with sodium hydroxide","Reaction of alkanoates with acid","Reaction of alkanoates with alcohols","Reaction of alkanoates with sodium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The confirmatory test for alkanoic acids in organic qualitative analysis is the?","options":["turning of wet blue litmus paper red","reaction with alkanols to form esters","reaction with sodium hydroxide to form salt and water","reaction with aqueous Na<sub>2<\/sub>COsp<sub>3<\/sub> to liberate a gas which turns lime water milky"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A gas that will turn orange potassium heptaoxodichromate (lV) solution  to clear green is?","options":["sulphur (ii) oxide","hydrogen sulphide","sulphide (lV) oxide","hydrogen chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the curves above represents the behaviour of 1 mole of an ideal gas?","options":["l","ll","lll","lV"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"For which salt in the graph above does the solubility increase most rapidly with rise in temperature?","options":["CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>","KNO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaCl","KCl"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Half-cell reaction. From the data above , it can be deduced that the most powerful reducing agent of the four metals is","options":["Cu","Fe","Ba","Zn"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"In the diagram above, curve X represents the energy profile for a homogeneous gaseous reaction. Which of the following conditions would produce curve Y for the same reaction?","options":["Increase in temperature","Increase in the concentration of a reactant","Addition of a catalyst","Increase in pressure"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The two functional groups in the above compound are","options":["alcohol and amine","acid and amine","aldehyde and acid","ketone and amine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The IUPAC nomenclature for the compound above is","options":["dimethlhexane","3,5  dimethylhexane","1.1 dmethyl, 3 methylpentane","2.4 dimethylhexane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The function of the copper (ll)tetraoxosulphate (IV) in dilute H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> in the figure above is to","options":["dry the gas","absorb phosphine impurity","absorb ethene impurity","from an acetylide with ethyne"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"<p>The dissolution of common salt in water is a physical change because<\/p>","options":["the salt can be obtained by crystallization","the salt can be recovered by the evaporation of water","heat is not generated during mixing","the solution will not boil at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"At 25<sup>o<\/sup>C and 1atm, a gas occupies a volume of 1.50dm<sup>3<\/sup>. What volume will it occupy at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C and 1atm?","options":["1.88 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.00 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","18.80 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","18.80 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","60.00dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The fraction of crude oil used as jet fuel is","options":["refinery gas","diesel oil","kerosine","gasoline"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"There is a large temperature interval between the melting point and the boiling point of a metal because?","options":["metals have very high melting points","metals conduct heat very repaidly","melting does not break the metalic bond but boiling does","the crystal lattice of metals is easily broken"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"How many moles of (H+) are there in 1 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.5 M solution of H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>?","options":["2.0 moles","1.0 moles","0.5 mole","0.25 mole"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"wH<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + xAI(OH)<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 yH<sub>2<\/sub>O + = zAI<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>. The respective values of w.x.y and z in the equation above are?","options":["2,2,5 and 1","3,2,5 and 2","3,2,6 and 1","2,2,6 and 2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A given mass of gas occupies 2 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at 300k. At what temperature will its volume be doubled keeping the pressure constant?","options":["400 k","480 k","550 k","600 k"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is a measure of the average kinetic energy of the molecules of a substance?","options":["Volume","Mass","pressure from age grades","Temperature"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"If 100 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen pass through a porous plug in 50 seconds, the time taken for the same volume of hydrogen to pass through the same porous plug is?<br><br>\r\n<br><br>\r\n(O = 16, H = 1)","options":["10.0 s","12.5 s","17.7 s","32.0 s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"An increase in temperature causes an increase in pressure of a gas in a fixed volume due to an increase in the?","options":["number of molecules of the gas","density of the gas molecules","number of collisions between the gas molecules","number of collisions between the gas molecules and the walls of the container"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The nucleus of the isotope tritium, contains?","options":["two neutrons with no protons","one neutron and one protons","two neutrons and one proton","two neutrons, one proton and one electron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"How many lone pairs of electron are there on the central atom of the H<sub>2<\/sub>O molecules?","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"<sup>14<\/sup><sub>7<\/sub>N + X \u2192 <sup>17<\/sup><sub>8<\/sub>O + <sup>1<\/sup><sub>1<\/sub> H. In the above reaction, X is a?","options":["neutron","helium atom","litgium atom","deuterium atom"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The pollutants that are likely to be present in an  industrial environment are?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S,SO<sub>2<\/sub> and oxides of nitrogen","NH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCI and CO","CO<sub>2<\/sub>, NH<sub>3<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>S","dust, NO and CI<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Four elements P,Q,R and S have 1,2,3, and 7 electrons in their outermost shells respectively. The element which is unlikely to be a metal is?","options":["P","Q","R","S"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following gases dissolves in water vapour to produce acid rain during rainfall?","options":["Oxygen","Carbon (II) oxide","Nitrogen","Sulphur (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Water for town supply is chlorinated to make it free from?","options":["bad odour","bacteria","temporary hardness","permanent hardness"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"On which of the following is the solubility of a gaseous substance dependent? I. Nature of solvent II. Nature of solute III. Temperature IV. Pressure","options":["I, II, III and IV","I and II only","II only","I, III and IV only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"An emulsion paint consists of ?","options":["gas or liquid particles dispersed in liguid","liquid particles dispersed in liquid","solid particles dispersed in liquid","solid particles dispersed in solid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A sample of orange juice is found to have a pH of 3.80. What is he concentration of the hydroxide ion in the juice?","options":["1.6 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>","6.3 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>","6.3 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>","1.6 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Arrange HCI, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH, C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub> in order of increasing conductivity.","options":["HCI, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH, C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCI, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH, HCI","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH, C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCI"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"How many grams of H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> are necessary for the preparation of 0.175 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of M 6.00 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(S = 32.06, O = 16.00 H = 1.00)","options":["206.0 g","103.0 g","98.1 g","51.5 g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI) solution is electrolyzed using carbon electrodes. Which of the following are produced at the anode and cathode respectively ?","options":["Copper and oxygen","Oxygen and copper","Hydrogen and copper","Copper and hydrogen"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Calculate the mass, in kilograms, of magnesium produced by the electrolysis of magnesium (II) chloride in a cell operating for 24 hours at 500 amperes.","options":["2.7","5.4","10.8","21.7"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sup>2-<\/sup><sub>3<\/sub> + I<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup> + 2I<sup>-<\/sup>. In reaction above, the oxidizing agent is?","options":["S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>","I<sub>2<\/sub>","S<sub>4<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>","I<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"MnO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2CI<sup>-<\/sup> + 4H<sup>+<\/sup> \u2192 MnO<sup>2+<\/sup> + CI<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O. <br>\r\nThe changes is oxidation numbers when the manganese, chloride and hydrogen ions react according to the above equation are respectively?","options":["2, 2, 4","-1, -2, 4","-2, 1, 0","2, 4, 0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"In which of the following is the entropy change positive?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>  \u2192   H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(g)<\/sub>","Cu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)  +  Fe<sub>(s)<\/sub>   \u2192  Fe<sup>(2+)<\/sup>  +  Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  +  3H<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>   \u2192   2NH<sub>3<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","2HCI<sub>(s)<\/sub>   \u2192   H<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  +  CI<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"In what way is equilibrium constant for the forward reaction related to that of the reversed reaction?","options":["The additional of the two is expected to be one","The product of the two is expected to be one","The two  equilibrium constants are identical","The product of the two is always greater than one"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following equilibria shows little or no net reaction when the volume of the system is decreased?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  + I<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  \u2248  2HI<sub>(g)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>2<\/sub><sup>(g)<\/sup>   \u2248  N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","PCI<sub>5<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  \u2248  PCI<sub>3<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  +  CI<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","ZnO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>  \u2248  ZnCO<sub>3<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"For a general equation of the nature xP + yQ \u2248 mR + nS, the expression for the equilibrium constant is?","options":["k (p)<sup>x<\/sup> (Q)<sup>y<\/sup>","(p)<sup>x<\/sup> (Q)<sup>y<\/sup> \/ (R)<sup>m<\/sup> (S)<sup>n<\/sup>","(R)<sup>m<\/sup> (S)<sup>n<\/sup> \/  (p)<sup>x<\/sup> (Q)<sup>y<\/sup>","m(R) n (S) \/  x(P) y (Q)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of these statements is TRUE about carbon (IV) oxide?","options":["it supports combustion","It is strongly acidic in water","It is very soluble in water","It supports the buring of magnesium to produce magnesium oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following combination of gases is used for metal welding? i. Oxygen and ethyne, ii. Hydrogen and ethyne, iii. Hydrogen and oxygen, iv. Ethyne, hydrogen and oxygen.","options":["i and ii","ii and iv","i and iii","ii and iv"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following oxides of nitrogen is unstable in air?","options":["NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5-<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The gas formed when ammonium trioxonitrate (V) is heated with sodium hydroxide is?","options":["hydrogen","nitrogen (IV) oxide","oxygen","ammonium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The gas formed when ammonium trioxonitrate (V) is heated with sodium hydroxide is?","options":["hydrogen","nitrogen (IV) oxide","oxygen","ammonium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Safety matches contain sulphur and?","options":["potassium trioxochlorate (V)","potassium trioxonitrate (V)","charcoal","phosphorus sulphide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Addition of an aqueous solution of a salt gives a white precipitate. The salt is likely to be a?","options":["nitrate","carbonate","chloride","sulphide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Sodium hydroxide solution can be conveniently stored in a container made of?","options":["lead","zinc","aluminium","copper"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT used as a raw material in the Solvay process?","options":["Ammonia","Sodium chloride","Calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)","Sodium trioxocarbonate (IV)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Duralumin consists of aluminium, copper, ?","options":["zinc and gold","lead and maganese","nickle and silver","manganese and magnesium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"CaO<sub>s<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub>  \u2192  Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(s)<\/sub> \u0394H -65 kj. The process represented by the above equation is known as?","options":["dissolution","slaking","liming","mortaring"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The carbon atoms in ethene are?","options":["sp<sup>3<\/sup> hybridized","sp hybridized","sp<sup>2<\/sup> hybridized","not hybridized"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds reacts with sodium metal as well as silver and copper salts ?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>C \u039e C\u2014CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/subCH<sub>3<\/sub>>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>C \u039e CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH = CH CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following are isomers?","options":["Ethanol and dimethyl ether","Benzene and methybenzene","Ethanol and propanone","Trichloromethane and tetrachloromethane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The functional group present in an organic compound which gives bubbles on treatment with a saturated solution of NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub> is?","options":["hydroxyl group","carboalkoxyl group","carbonyl group","carboxyl group"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"An organic compound containing 40.1% carbon and 6.6% hydrogen has an empirical formula of?","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","CH<sub>3<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The characteristics reaction of carbonyl compounds is?","options":["substitution","elimination","addition","saponfication"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Alkanals can be differentiated from alkanones by reaction with?","options":["2,4-dinitrophenylhydrazine","hydrogen cyanide","sodium hydrogen sulphite","Tollen's reagent"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"An example of a polysaccharides is?","options":["\u2014dextrose","mannose","glucose","starch"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"In the experiment above. Z can be","options":["a solution of sodium dioxonitrate (lll) and ammonium chloride","a solution of lead trioxnitrate (V)","a solution of sodium trioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid and sodium trioxonitrate (V)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is a secondary alkanol?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A given mass of gas occupies 2 dm<sup>2<\/sup> at 300k. At what temperature will its volume be doubled keeping the pressure constant?","options":["400k","480k","550k","600k"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is a measure of the average kinetic energy of the molecules of a substance?","options":["volume","mass","pressure","temperature"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The nucleus of the isotopes tritium,contains","options":["two neutrons with no protons","one neutron and one proton","two neutrons and one proton","two neutrons, one proton and one electron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following can be obtained by fractional distillation?","options":["Nitrogen from liquid air","Sodium chloride from sea water","Iodine from a solution  of Iondine in carbon tetrachloride","Sulphur from a solution of sulphur incarbon disulphide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following are mixtures? <br>\r\ni,  Petroleum <br>\r\nii, Rubber latex <br>\r\niii. Vulcanizer's solution <br>\r\niv, Carbon (II)sulphide","options":["i, ii and iii","i, ii and iv","i and ii only","i and iv"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"An iron ore is known to contain 70.0% Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>. The obtain from 80kg of the ore is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Fe = 56, O = 16)","options":["35.0 kg","39.2 kg","70.0 kg","78.4 kg"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"In two separate experiments, 0.36g and 0.71g of chlorine combined with a metal X to give Y and Z respectively. An analysis showed that Y and Z contain 0.20g and 0.40g of X respectively. The data above represents the law of ?","options":["multiple proportion","conservation of mass","constant composition","reciprocal proportion"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen at 10 atmospheres pressure is placed in a 20 dm<sup>3<\/sup> container. Calculate the new pressure if temperature is kept constant?","options":["6.7 atm","15.0 atm","60.0 atm","66. 0 atm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Calculate the volume of carbon (IV)oxide measured at s.t.p, produced when 1 kg of potassium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (IV) is totally decomposed by heat?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(G.M.V. at s.t.p 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>, K = 39, O = 16, C = 12, H = 1)","options":["28 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","112 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","196 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A given quantity of a gas occupies a volume of 228 cm<sup>3<\/sup> at a pressure of 750mm Hg. What will be its volume at atmospheric pressure?","options":["220 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","225 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","230 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","235 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A sample of a gas exerts a pressure of 8.2 atm when confined in a 2.93 dm<sup>3<\/sup> container at 20\u00b0C. The number of moles of gas in the sample is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(R = 0.082 litre atm \/ deg mole)","options":["1.00","2.00","3.00","4.00"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Atoms of element X (with 2 electrons in the outer shell). combine with atoms of Y (with 7 electrons in the outer shell). Which of the following statements is FALSE? The compound formed?","options":["has formula XY","is likely to be ionic","contains X<sub>2+<\/sub> ions","contains Y<sub-<\/sub> ions"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The electronic configuration of an elements is 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>3<\/sup>. How many unpaired electrons are there in the element?","options":["5","4","3","2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The ions X<sub>-<\/sub> and Y<sub>+<\/sub> are isoelectronic, each containing a total of 10 electrons.<br>\r\nHow many protons are in the nuclei of the neutral atoms of X and Y respectively?","options":["10 and 10","9 and 9","11 and 9","9 and 11"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following represents the type of bonding present in ammonium chloride molecule?","options":["Ionic only","Covalent only","Ionic and dative covalent","Dative covalent only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following is arranged in order of increasing electronegativity?","options":["Chlorine, aluminium, magnesium, phosphorus, sodium","sodium, magnesium, aluminium, phosphorus, chlorine","Chlorine, phosphorus, phosphorous, aluminium, magnesium, sodium","Sodium, chlorine, phosphorus, magnesium, aluminium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A quantity of air was passed through a weighed amount of alkaline pyrogallol. An increase in the weight of the pyrogallol would result from the absorption of?","options":["nitrogen","neon","argon","oxygen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following ions is a pollutant in drinking water even in trace amounts?","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Hg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The solubility of copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (Iv) is 75g in 100g of water at 100\u00b0C and 25g in 100g of water at 30\u00b0C. What mass of the salt would crystallize, if 50g of copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI) solution saturated at 100\u00b0C were cooled to 30\u00b0C ?","options":["57.5","42.2","28.6","14.3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A sample of temporary hard water can be prepared  in the laboratory by?","options":["disolving calcium chloride in distilled water","saturating lime water with carbon (IV) oxide","saturating distilled water with calcium hydroxide","dissolving sodium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (IV) in some distilled water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A property of a colloidal dispersion which a solution does not have is?","options":["the Tyndall effect","homogeneity","osmotic pressure","surface polarity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of sulphur (IV) oxide, 800 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of ammonia, 450 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen chloride, 1.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of at 15\u00b0C. Which of the following is suitable for demonstrating the fountain experiment?","options":["Sulphur (IV) oxide hydrogen chloride","Carbon (IV) oxide and amonia","Amonia and hydrogen chloride","Carbon (IV) oxide and surphur (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"How many structural isomers can be written for the     alkyl bromide, C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>9<\/sub>Br?","options":["3","4","6","8"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"What volume of CO<sub>2<\/sub> at s.t.p would be obtained by reacting trioxocarbonate (IV) with excess acid?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(G.M.V at s.t.p = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>)","options":["2.240 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","22.40 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","224.0 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","2240 cm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"If a current of 1.5 A is passed for 4.00 hours through a molten tin salt and 13.3g of tin is deposited, what is the oxidation state of the metal in the salt?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Sn = 118.7, F = 96500 C mol<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1","2","3","4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following equimolar solutions, Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> Na<sub>2<\/sub> SO<br>\r\n<sub>4<\/sub>CI FeCI<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa, <br>\r\nhave pH greater than 7?","options":["FeCI <sub>3<\/sub> and NH <sub>4<\/sub>CI","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa and Na,Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> and CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa","FeCI<sub>3<\/sub>, CH<sub>3<\/sub>COONa  and NH<sub>4<\/sub>CI"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"MnO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>4<\/sub> + 8H<sup>+<\/sup> + ne \u2192 Mn<sup>++<\/sup> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O. Which is the value of n in the reaction above?","options":["2","3","4","5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"2H<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>(g)<\/sub> + SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2192 3S<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>. The above reaction is?","options":["a redox reaction H<sub>2<\/sub>S is the oxidant and SO<sub>2<\/sub> is the reductant","a redox reaction in which SO<sub>2<\/sub> is the oxidant and H<sub>2<\/sub>S is the reductant","not a redox reaction because there is no oxidant in reaction equation","not a redox because there is no reductant in the reaction equation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Magnesium (IV) oxide is known to hasten the decomposition of hydrogen peroxide. Its main action is to?","options":["increase the surface area of the reactants","increase the concntration of the reactants","lower the activation energy for the reaction","lower the heat of reaction, \u2206H, for the reaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"1.1 g  of CaCI<sub>2<\/sub> dissolved in 50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water caused a rise in temperature of3.4\u00b0C. The heat of reaction, \u2206H for CaCI<sub>2<\/sub> in kj per mole is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Ca = 40, CI = 35.5, specific heat of water is 4.18 jk<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["-71.1","-4.18","+71.1","+111.0"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"NO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2194 (1)\/(2)N<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2206H = -89.3 kj. <br>\r\nWhat conditions would favour maximum conversion of nitrogen (II) oxide and carbon (II) oxide in the reaction above?","options":["Low temperature and high pressure","High temperature and low pressure","High temperature and high pressure","Low temperature and low pressure"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following equilibria is unaffected by a pressure change?","options":["2NaCI(s)  \u2194  2Na <sub>(I)<\/sub> + CI<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","H <sub>2(g)<\/sub> + I<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2HI<sub>(g)<\/sub>","2O<sub>3(g)<\/sub>   \u2194  3O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2NO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>   \u2194  N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following gases will rekindle a brightly glowing splint?","options":["NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","CI<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following salts can be melted without decomposition?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","MgCO<sub>3<\/sub>","ZnCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Oxygen gas can be prepared by heating?","options":["ammonium trioxonitrate (V)","ammonium trioxonitrate (III)","ppotassium trioxonitrate (V)","mamgamese (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Addition of aqueous ammonia to a solution of Zn<sup>++<\/sup> gives a white precipitate which dissolves in an excess of ammonia because?","options":["zinc is amphoteric","zinc hydroxide is readily soluble","zinc forms a complex which is readily soluble in excess ammonia","ammonia solution is a strong base"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following, in clear solution, forms a white precipitate when carbon (IV) oxide is bubbled into it for a short time?","options":["KOH","NaOH","Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","AI(OH)<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following metals can be prepared in samples by the thermal decomposition of their trioxonitrate (V) salts?","options":["Copper and mercury","Silver and copper","Mercury and silver","Magnesium and mercury"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (IV) is widely used as a?","options":["fertilizer","fungicide","disinfectant","purifier"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds can exist as geometric isomers?","options":["2-methylbut-2ene","But-2-ene","But-1-ene","CI-C-Br"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"How many grams of bromine will be required to completely react with 10 g of propyne?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(C = 12, H = 1, Br = 80)","options":["20 g","40 g","60 g","80 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Ethene when passed into concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> is rapidly absorbed. The product is diluted with water and then warmed to produce?","options":["ethanol","diethyl ether","ethanal","diethyl sulphate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"One advantages of detergents over soap is that detergents?","options":["are easier to maufacture","foam more than soap","form soluble salts with hard water","are able to deter germs more than soap"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A certain liquid has a high boiling point. It is viscous, non-toxic, miscible with water being very hygroscopic. This liquid is most likely to be?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>HO","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CHOHCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHOHCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub>OHCHOHCH<sub>2<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"CH<sub>3<\/sub>-CH-CH<sub>3<\/sub><br>\r\n   CH<sub>2<\/sub>CI    <br>\r\n<br>\r\nIs known as?","options":["1-chloro-2-methylbutane","1-chloro-2-methylpropane","2-chloromethylpropane","1-chloro-2, 2-dimethylethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is TRUE of the complete hydrolysis of a glycerine by sodium hygroxide?","options":["3 moles ofNaOH are required for each mole of glyceride","3 moles of glycerol are produced","Only one mole of soap is formed","concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> is essential for the completion of the reaction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following are the products of the reaction between CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH and CI<sub>2<\/sub> in sunlight?","options":["CICH<sub>2<\/sub>COOH +  HCI","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COCI + HOCI","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOCI + HCI","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COCI + HO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of these is an acid salt?","options":["K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4-<\/sub>.AI<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>.24H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CuCO<sub>3<\/sub>.Cu(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","NaHS","CaOCI<sub>2-<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The elections or two atoms Y and Z are arranged in shes as shown above. The bond formed between the atoms of Y and Z is","options":["ionic","convalent","dative","metallic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"50 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of sulphur (lV) oxide, 800 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of carbon (IV) oxide will respectively saturate 1.0cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water at 15<sup>o<\/sup>C. Which of the following is suitable for demonstrating the fountain experiment?","options":["Sulphur (IV) oxide and hydrogen chloride.","Carbon (IV) oxide and ammonia","Ammonia and hydrogen chloride","Carbon (IV) oxide and Sulphur (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The data in the table above shows the rate of reaction of nitrogen (ll) oxide with chlorine at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C It can be concluded that doubling the initial concentration of NO increase the rate of reaction by a factor of","options":["two","three","four","five"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The appropriate test paper to use in the above experiment is moist","options":["litmus psper","potassium heptaoxodichromate (IV) paper","lead (ll) trioxonitrate (V) paper","universal indicator paper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following is a physical change?","options":["The bubbling of chlorine into water","The bubbling of chlorine into a jar contanining hydrogen","The dissolution of sodium chloride in water","The passing of steam over heated iron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"In a reaction: SnO + 2C \u2192 Sn + 2CO, the mass of coke containing 80% carbon required to reduce 0.302 kg of pure tin oxide is?<br>\r\n(Sn - 119, O - 16, C - 12).","options":["0.40 kg","0.20 kg","0.06 kg","0.04 kg"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> + 6Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + 14H<sup>+<\/sup> \u2192 2Cr<sup>3+<\/sup> +6Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> + 7H<sub>2<\/sub>O. In the above , the oxidation number of chromium changed from?","options":["+7 to +3","+6 to +3","+5 to +3","-2 to +3"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"In the reaction 1O<sup>-<\/sup><sub>3<\/sub> + 5l<sup>-<\/sup> + 6H<sup>+<\/sup> \u2192 31<sub>2<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O, the oxidizing agent is?","options":["H<sup>+<\/sup>","l<sup>-<\/sup>","1O<sup>-<\/sup>","l<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(s)<\/sub> + 2Al<sub>(s)<\/sub> \u2192 Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> + 2Fe<sub>(s)<\/sub> If the heats of formation of Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> and Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> are - 1670 kj mol<sup>-1<\/sup> and - 822 kj mol<sup>-1<\/sup> respectively, the enthalpy change in kj for the reaction is ?","options":["+2492","+848","-848","-2492"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Iron galvanized with  zinc is cathodically protected from corrosion. This is because?","options":["zinc has a more positive oxidation potential than iron","zinc has less positive oxidation potential than iron","bith have the same oxidation potential","zinc is harder than iron"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following samples will react fastest with dilute trioxonitrate (V) acid?","options":["5 g of lumps of CacO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25\u00b0C","5 g of powered CacO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25\u00b0","5 g of lumps of CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 50\u00b0C","5 g of powered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> AT 50\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"In the reaction:<br>\r\n2Hl<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2194 H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + l<sub>2(g)'<\/sub> \u0394H = 10 kj;<br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe concentration of iodine in the equilibrium mixture can be increased by?","options":["raising the pressure","raising the temperature","adding a catalyst","lowering the pressure"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following gases can be collected by the upward displacement of air?","options":["NO","H <sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","Cl <sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The brown fumes given off when trioxonitrate (V) acid is heated consist of ?","options":["NO<sub>2<\/sub> and O<sub>2<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O and NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NO<sub>2'<\/sub> O<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NO, NO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following tests will completely identify anyone of surphur (VI) oxide, hydrogen, carbon (IV) oxide and nitrogen (II) oxide?","options":["Pass each gas into water and test with blue litmus paper","Pass each gas into lime water","Expose each gas to atmospheric air","Pass each gas to concentrated tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"In the Haber process for the manufacture of ammonia, the catalyst commonly used is finely divided ?","options":["vanadium","platinum","iron","copper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A metallic oxide which reacts with both HCl and NaOH to give salt and water only can be classified as?","options":["an acidic oxide","a basic oxide","a neutral oxide","an amphoteric oxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following metals will liberate hydrogen from steam or dilute acid?","options":["Copper","Iron","Lead","Mercury"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Coal fire should not be used in poorly ventilated rooms because ?","options":["of the accumulation of CO<sub>2<\/sub> which causes dep sleep","it is usually too hot","of the acumulation of CO which causes suffocation","it removes most most of the gases in the rooms"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The major component of the slag from the production of iron is?","options":["an alloy of calcium and iron","coke","impure iron","calcium trioxosilicate (IV)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Sodium hydrogen should be stored in properly closed containers because it?","options":["readily asborbs water vapour to air","is easily oxidize by atmospheric oxygen","turns golden yellow when exposed to light","melts  at a low temperature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"To make coloured glasses, small quantities of oxides of metals which form coloured silicates are often added to the reaction mixture consisting of Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> and SiO<sub>2<\/sub>. Such a metals is a?.","options":["pottasium","barium","zinc","copper"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds gives a yellow residue when heated and also reacts with aqueous sodium hydroxide to give a white gelatinous precipitate soluble in excess sodium hydroxide solution?","options":["(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)CO<sub>3<\/sub>","ZnCO<sub>3<\/sub>","Al<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>","PbCO<sub><\/sub>3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A cycloalkane with the molecular formula C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub> has ?","options":["one isomer","two isomers","three isomers","four isomers"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The label on a reagent bottle containing a clear organic liquid dropped off.The liquid was neutral to litmus and gave a colourless gas with metallic sodium. The liquid must be an?","options":["alkanoate","alkaene","alkanol","alkane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Alkaonic acids have low volatility compared with alkanols because they?","options":["are more polar than alkaonls","have two oxygen atoms while alkanols have one","form hydrogen bonds while alkanols do not","form two hydrogen bonds while alkanols form one"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The octane number of a fuel whose performance is the same as that of a mixture of 55 g of 2,2,4- trimethly pentane  and 45 g of n-heptane is ?","options":["45","55","80","100"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is formed when maltose reacts with concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid ?","options":["Carbon (IV) oxide","Coal tar","Charcoal","Toxic fumes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"If a gas occupies a container of volume 146 cm<sup>3<\/sup> at 18\u00b0C  and 0.97`atm, its volume 146cm<sup>3<\/sup> at s.t.p is?","options":["133","146","266","292"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The volume occupies by 1.58g of a gas at s.t.p is 500cm<sup>3<\/sup>. What is the relative molecular mass of the gas? <br>\r\n<br>\r\n(G.M.V at s.t.p = 22.40dm<sup>3<\/sup>)","options":["28","32","44","71"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Equal volumes of CO,SO<sub>2<\/sub>, and H<sub>2<\/sub>S were released into a room at the same point and time. Which of the following gives the order of diffusion of the gases to the opposite corner of the room?<br>\r\n(S = 32, C = 12, O = 16, N = 14, H = 1)","options":["CO, SO<sub>2<\/sub>,NO<sub>2<\/sub>,H<sub>2<\/sub>S","SO<sub>2<\/sub>,NO<sub>2<\/sub>,H<sub>2<\/sub>S,CO","CO,H<sub>2<\/sub>S,SO<sub>2<\/sub>,NO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO,H<sub>2<\/sub>S,NO<sub>2<\/sub>,SO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A basic postulate of the kinetic theory of gases is that the molecules of a gas move in straight lines between collisions. This implies that?","options":["collisions are perfectly elastic","forces of repulsion exist","forces of repulsion are in equilibrium","collision are inelastic"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":".....................P....Q.....R......S<br>\r\nProton..............13....16....17.....19<br>\r\nElectron............13....16....17.....19<br>\r\nNeutron.............14....16....35.....20<br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhich of the four atoms P,q,R and in S in the above data can be described by the following properties relative atomic mass is greater than 30 but less than 40; it has an odd atomic number and forms a unipositive ion in solution?","options":["P","Q","R","S"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following terms indicates the number of bonds that can be formed by an atom?","options":["Oxidation number","Valence","Atomic number","Electronegativity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"X<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 X<sub>(g)<\/sub>. The type of energy involved in the above transformation is?","options":["ionization energy","sublimation energy","lattice energy","electron affinity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Chlorine, consisting of two isotopes of mass numbers 35 and 37, has an atomic mass of 35.5. <br>\r\nThe relative abundance of the isotope of mass number 37 is?","options":["20","25","50","75"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"10.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of air containing H<sub>2<\/sub>S as an impurity was passed through a solution of Pb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> until all the H<sub>2<\/sub>S had reacted. The precipitate of PbS was found to weigh 5.02 g. According to the equation: <br><br>\r\nPb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>S \u2192 PbS + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub> the percentage by volume of hydrogen sulphide in the air is?<br><br>\r\n<br><br>\r\n(Pb = 207, S = 32, GMV at s.t.p = 22.4dm<sup>3<\/sup>)","options":["50.2","47.0","4.70","0.47"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A blue solid, T, which weighed 5.0g was placed on a table. After 8 hours, the resulting pink solid was found to weigh 5.5g. It can be inferred that substance T?","options":["is deliquescent","is hydroscopic","has some molecules of water of crystallization","is efflorescent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The solubility in moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup> of 20g of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> dissolve in 100 of water at 180\u00b0C is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Cu = 63.5, S = 32, O = 16)","options":["0.13","0.25","1.25","2.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Smoke consist of?","options":["solid particles dispersed in liquid","solid or liquid particles dispersed in gas","gas or liquid particles dispersed inliquid","liquid particles dispersed inliquid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Na<sub>2<\/sub>C<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>  + CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192 CaC<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub> + 2NaCl. Given a solution of 1.9g of sodium oxalate in 50g of water at room temperature, calculate the minimum volume of 0.1 M calcium oxalate using the above equation?","options":["1.40 \u03c7 10<sup>2<\/sup> dm<sup>3<\/sup>","14.0 \u03c7 10<sup>2<\/sup> cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.40 \u03c7 10<sup>-2<\/sup> dm<sup>-2<\/sup>","14.0 \u03c7 10<sup>-2<\/sup> cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"2.0g of a monobasic acid was made up to 250 cm<sup>3<\/sup> with distilled water. 25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of this solution required 20.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 M NaOH solution for complete neutralization. The molar mass of the acid is?","options":["200 g","160 g","100 g","50 g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"What is the concentration of H<sup>+<\/sup> ions in moles per dm<sup>3<\/sup>  of a sodium  of pH 4.398?","options":["4.0 \u03c7 10<sup>-5<\/sup>","0.4 \u03c7 10<sup>-5<\/sup>","4.0 \u03c7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.4 \u03c7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"What volume  of 11.0 M hydrochloric acid must be dilute to obtain 1 dm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.05 M acid?","options":["0.05 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.10 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.55 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"If 10.8 g of silver is deposited in a silver coulometer volume of oxygen liberated is?","options":["0.56 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.60 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.20 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","22.40 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"0.1 faraday of electricity deposited 2.95 g of nickel during electrolysis of an aqueous solution.<br>\r\nCalculate the number of moles of nickel that will be deposited by 0.4 faraday? <br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Ni = 58.7)","options":["0.20","0.30","0.04","5.87"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Changes in the physical in the scheme above.The letter X,Y and Z respectively represent","options":["sublimation, condensation and freezing","sublimation, vapourization and solidification","freezing, condensation and sublimation","evaporation, liquefaction and solidification"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question. The structure of cis-2-butene is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"What is the IUPAC name for the hydrocarbon","options":["2-ethyl-4-methylpent-2-ene","3,5-dimethylhex-3-ene","2,4-dimethylhex 3-ene","2-methyl-4-ethylpent-3-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Use the above graph above to answer this question . CH<sub>3<\/sub>-C = CH \\(\\frac{Na}{liq NH_3}\\)> P, Compound P, in the above reaction, is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The above reaction is an example of","options":["a displacement reaction","a neutralization reaction","an elimination reaction","saponification"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Select the right answer from the structure above.Which of the following compounds represents the polymerization product of ethyne?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The Avogadro number of 24g of magnesium is the same as that of","options":["1g of hydrogen molecules","16g of oxygen molecules","32g of oxygen molecules","35.5g of chlorine molecules"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following would support the conclusion that a solid sample is a mixture?","options":["the solid can be ground to a fine powder","the density of the solid is 2.25 g dm<sup>3<\/sup>","the solid has a melting range of 300<sup>o<\/sup>C to 375<sup>o<\/sup>C","the solid absorbs moisture from the atmosphere"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The molar ratio of carbon to hydrogen of a volatile liquid compound is 1: 2. 0. 12 g of the liquid on evaporation at s.t.p. gave 32 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of vapour. The molecular formula of the liquid is<br>\r\n[G.M.V =22.4 dm <sup>3<\/sup>, C = 12, H = 1]","options":["C <sub>3<\/sub> H <sub>6<\/sub>","C <sub>4<\/sub>H <sub>8<\/sub>","C <sub>5<\/sub>C <sub>10<\/sub>","C <sub>6<\/sub>H <sub>12<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"20.00 cm <sup>3<\/sup> of a solution containing 0.53 g of anhydrous Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> in 100 cm<sup>3<\/sup> requires 25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> for complete neutralisation. The concentration of the acid solution in moles per dm is [H =1, C = 12, O = 16, Na =23, S = 32]","options":["0.02","0.04","0.06","0.08"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The minimum volume of oxygen required for the complete combustion of a mixture of 10cm <sup>3<\/sup>  of CO and 15 cm <sup>3<\/sup> of H <sup>2<\/sup> is","options":["25.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","12.5 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"What is the partial pressure of hydrogen gas collected <br>\r\nover water at standard atmospheric pressure and 25 <sup>o<\/sup>C if the saturation vapour pressure of water at saturation vapour pressure of water is 23 mm Hg at that temperature?","options":["737 mm Hg","763 mm Hg","777 mm Hg","783 mm Hg"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The atomic radius of Li, Na and K are 1: 33A, 1. 54A and 1. 96A res pectively. Which of the following explaqins this gradation in atomic radius?","options":["electropositivity decreases from Li to Na to K","electronegativity decreases from Li to Na to K","the number of the electron shells increases from Li to Na to K","the elements are in the same period"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Elements X and Y have electronic configurations 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> and 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>1<\/sup> respectively. When they combine, the formula of the compound formed is","options":["XY","YX","X<sub>2<\/sub>Y<sub>3<\/sub>","Y<sub>2<\/sub>X<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The atomic number of caesium is 55 and its atomic mass is 133. The nucleus of caesium atom therefore contains","options":["78 protons and 55 elections","55 protons and 78 neutrons","55 neutrons 78 electrons","78 protons and 55 neutrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Four elements P,Q, R and S have atomic numbers of 4, 10, 12 and 14 respectively . Which of these electrons is a noble gas?","options":["P","Q","R","S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"How many valence electrons are contained in the element represented  <sup>31<\/sup><sub>15<\/sub>P?","options":["3","5","15","31"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The gaseous pollutant sulphur (IV)oxide is most likely to be detected in fairly reasonable quantities in the area around a plant for the","options":["extraction of aluminium from bauxite","production of margarine","smelting of copper","production of chlorine from brine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Calcium hydroxide is added in the treatment of town water supply to","options":["kill bacteria in the water","facilitate coagulation of organic particles","facilitate sedimentation","improve the taste of the water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A hydrated salt of formula MSO<sub>4<\/sub>.xH<sub>2<\/sub> O CONTAINS 45.3% by mass of water of crystalisation. Calculate the value of  x [M = 56, S = 32, O = 16, H = 1 ]","options":["3","5","7","10"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Using 50 cm <sup>3<\/sup> of 1 M potassium hydroxide and 100cm <sup>3<\/sup> of 1 M tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid, calculate the respective volumes in cm <sup>3<\/sup> of base and acid that would be required to produce the maximum amount of potassium tetraoxosulphate (IV) [ = 39, S = 32, O = 16, H = 1]","options":["50, 50","25, 50","50, 25","25, 25"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A solution of calcium bromide contains 20 g dm <sup>3<\/sup> What is the molarity of the solution with respect to calcium bromide and bromide ions? [Ca = 40, Br = 80]","options":["0. 1, 0 . 1","0. 1, 0. 2","0. 1, 0. 05","0.05, 0.1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The substance ZnO dissolves in sodium hydroxide solution and mineral acid solution to give soluble products in each case. ZnO is therefore referred to as","options":["an allotropic oxide","an amphoteric oxide","a peroxide","a dioxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"An acid and its conjugate base","options":["can neutralise each other to form a salt","differ only by a proton","differ only by the opposite charges they carry","are always neutral substances"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The same current is passed for the same time through solutions of AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> and CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> connected in series. How much silver will be deposited if 1.0 g of copper is produced?<br>\r\n[Cu = 63.5, S = 32, O = 16, Ag = 108, N = 14]","options":["1.7 g","3.4 g","6. 8 g","13. 6 g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"What is discharged at the cathode during the electrolysis of copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (VI) solution?","options":["Cu <sup>2+<\/sup> only","H <sup><\/sup>+ only","Cu <sup>2+<\/sup> and H","Cu <sup>2+<\/sup> and SO <sup>2-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"An element, Z froms an anion whose formula is [Z(CN)<sub>6<\/sub>]<sup>y<\/sup>. If Z has an oxidation number of +2, what is the value of y?","options":["- 2","- 3","- 4","- 5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The combustion of ethene, C <sub>2<\/sub>H <sub>4<\/sub>, is given by the equation C <sub>2<\/sub>H <sub>4<\/sub> + 30 <sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 2CO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub> O; \u2206H =  - 1428 KJ. If the molar heats of formation of water and carbon (IV) oxide are - 286 kJ and - 396 kJ respectively, calculate the molar heat of formation of ethene in KJ","options":["- 2792","+ 2792","- 64","+ 64"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following represents the balanced equation for the reaction of copper with concentrated trioxonitrate (V) acid?","options":["Cu <sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2HNO <sub>3(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 Cu (NO <sub>3<\/sub>) <sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + H <sub>2(g)<\/sub>","Cu <sub>(s)<\/sub> + 4HNO <sub>3(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 Cu (NO <sub>3<\/sub>) <sub>2(aq) <\/sub> + 2H <sub>2<\/sub>O <sub>(1)<\/sub> + 2NO <sub>2(g)<\/sub>","3Cu <sub>(s)<\/sub> + 8HNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 3Cu (NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(1)<\/sub> + 2NO<sub>(g)<\/sub>","3Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 4HNO<sub>3(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 3Cu(NO <sub>3<\/sub>) <sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + 2H <sub>2<\/sub>O <sub>(1)<\/sub> + 2NO <sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The catalyst used in the contact process for the manufacture of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid is","options":["manganes (IV) oxide","manganese (ll) tetraoxosulphate (VI)","vanadium (V) oxide","iron metal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Some products of destructive distillation of coal are","options":["carbon (IV) oxide and ethanoic acid","trioxocarbonate (IV) acid and methanoic acid","producer gas and water gas","coke and ammonia liquor"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Gunpower is made from charcoal, sulphur and potassium trioxonitrate (V) The salt in the mixture performs the function of","options":["an oxidant","a reductant","a solvent","a catalyst"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following reactions is (are) feasible? <br>\r\nI Br <sub>(1)<\/sub> + 2CI <sub>2(aq)<\/sub> 2Br <sub>(aq)<\/sub>  + CI <sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nll 21 <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Br <sub>2(1)<\/sub>   2Br <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 1 <sub>2(s)<\/sub> <br>\r\nlll 2F  <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + CI  <sub>2(g)<\/sub> 2CI  <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + F <sub>2(g)<\/sub> IV 2F <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Br <sub>2(1)<\/sub>   2Br <sub>(aq)<\/sub> + F <sub>2(g)<\/sub>","options":["l","ll","l and lll","lll and lV"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Bleaching powder, CaOCI<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O, deteriorates on exposure to air because","options":["it loses its water of crystallization","atmospheric nitrogen displaces chlorine from it","carbon (IV) oxide of the atmosphere displaceschlorine from it","bleaching agents should be stored in solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The products of the thermal decomposition of ammonium trioxonitrate (V) are","options":["NO <sub>2<\/sub> and oxygen","NH<sub>3<\/sub> and oxygen","nitrogen and water","N<sub>2<\/sub>O and water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The scale of a chemical balance is made of iron plate and coated with copper electrolytically because","options":["iron is less susceptible to corrosion than copper","copper is twice as less susceptitible to corrosion as iron","copper is less susceptible to corrosion than iron","copper and iron are equally susceptible to corrosion"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A metal is extracted from its ore by the electrolysis of its molten chloride and it displaces lead from lead (ll) trioxonitrate (V) solution. The metal is","options":["copper","aluminium","zinc","sodium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Mortar is NOT used for under-water construction because","options":["it hardens by lose of water","its hardening doe not depend upon evaporation","it requires concrete to harden","it will be washed away by the flow of water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT involved in the extraction of metals from their ores?","options":["reduction with carbon","reduction with other metals","reduction by electrolysis","oxidation with oxidizing agents"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"When excess chlorine is mixed with ethene at room temperature, the product is","options":["1,2 - dichloroethane","1,2 - dichloroethene","1,1 - dichloroethane","1, 1 - dichloroethene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Vulcanization of rubber is a process by which","options":["isoprene units are joined to produce rubber","rubber latex is coagulated","sulphur is chemically combined in the rubber","water is removed from the rubber"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The reaction between ethanoic acid and sodium hydroxide is an example of","options":["esterification","neutralization","hydroxylation","hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The bond which joins two ethanoic  acid molecules in the liquid state is","options":["a covalent bond","an ionic bond","a dative covalent bond","a hydrogen bond"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The alkaline hydrolysis of fats and oils produces soap and","options":["propane 1, 1, 3 - triol","propane - 1,2,3 - triol","propane - 1,3,3 - triol","propane - 1, 2, 2 - triol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The gas responsible for most of the fatal explosions in coal mines is","options":["butane","ethene","ethane","methane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Three liquids X, Y and Z containing only hydrogen and carbon were burnt on a spoon. X and Y burnt with sooty flames while Z did not. Y is able to discharge the colour of bromine water whereas X and Z cannot. Which of the liquids would be aromatic in nature?","options":["X and Z","Y","X","Z"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"It can be deduced from the vapour pressure curves above that","options":["liqiud 1 has the highest boiling point","liquid ll has the highest boiling point","liquid lll has the highest boiling point","liquid lll has the lowest boiling point"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"In the above set up substances X and Y are respectively","options":["lime water copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (lV)","potassium trioxocarbonate and alkaline pyrogallol","potassium hydroxide and alkaline pyrogallol","potassium trioxocarbonate (lV) and concentrated tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the curves in the above graph illustrates the behaviour of an ideal gas?","options":["W","X","Y","Z"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The above diagram gives the potential energy profile of the catalyst and uncatalysed reactions of X<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Y<sub>(g)<\/sub> \u2192 XY<sub>(g)<\/sub>. Deduce the respective activation energies in KJ of the catalysed and uncatalysed reverse reactions: XY(g) \u2192 X<sub>(g)<\/sub> + Y<sub>(g)<\/sub>","options":["300, 500","500, 300","-300, -500","-500, -300"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"If in the graph above 1 dm <sup>3<\/sup> of a saturated solution of KCL is cooled from 80<sup>o<\/sup>C, the mass of crystals deposited will be <br>\r\n[K = 39, Cl = 35.5]","options":["7.45 g","14.90 g","74.50 g","149.00 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The above graph shows a typical heating curve from the solid phase through the liquid phase to the gaseous phase of a substance. Which part of the curve shows solid and liquid in equilibrium?","options":["T","U","X","Y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Use the figure above to answer this question. Which of the following compounds is an isomer of the compound","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Use the figure above to answer this question. Which of the following is NOT a monomer?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"What is the IUPAC name for the compound","options":["1-chloro-2-methylprop-2,3-ene","1-chloro-2-methylprop-2-ene","3-chloro-2-methylprop-1-ene","3-chloro-2methylprop-1,2-ene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"CO<sub>g<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>g<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) <sub>2<\/sub><sub>g<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub><sub>g<\/sub> \\(\\Delta\\)H = -4100J. Which of the following factors favour the formation of hydrogen in the above reaction?   i. high pressure.  ii. low pressure  iii. high temperature   iv. use of excess steam","options":["i, iii and iv","iii only","ii, iii and i","iv only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is NOT correct?","options":["The average kinetic energy of a gas is directly proportional to its temperature","At constant tempearture, the volume of a gas increases as the pressure increases","The pressure of a gas is inversely proportional to its volume","The temperature of a gas is directly proportional to its volume","The collisions of molecules with each other are inelastic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The ion that may be assumed to have negligible concentration in a sample of water that lathers readily with soap is?","options":["Mg<sup>+<\/sup>","K<sup>+<\/sup>","CO<sub>2<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup>","HCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A substance S is isomorphous with another substance R. When a tiny crystals of S is added into a supersaturated solution of R?","options":["S dissolves in the solution","crystals of R are precipitated","there is no observable change","R and S react to generate heat"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following dilute solutions has the lowest  pH value?","options":["Calcium trioxocarbonate (IV)","Sodium trioxocarbonate (IV)","Hydrochloric acid","Ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following in aqueous solution is neutral to litmus?","options":["NH<sub>4<\/sub>CI","NaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","FeCl<sub>3<\/sub>","NaCl"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"What volume of a 0.1 M H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>4<\/sub> will be required to neutralize 45.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a 0.2 M NaOH?","options":["10.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","20.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","27.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","30.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is a basic salt?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","Mg(OH)CI","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","K<sub><\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.AI<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>,24H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following acts both s a reducing and an oxidizing agent?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S\/\/D","E\/\/"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following reactions takes place in the cathode compartment during the electrolysis of copper (II) chloride solution?","options":["Cu<sup>2+<\/sup> + 2e<sup>-<\/sup> \u2192 Cu(s)","2Cl<sup>-<\/sup>  -2e  \u2192 Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> -2e \u2192 Cu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>","Cu<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  + 2Cl<sup>-<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub>  \u2192  CuCl<sub>2(aq)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A mixture of starch solution and potassium iodide was placed in a test tube. On adding dilute tetraoxosulphate (lV) acid and then K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> solutions, a blue-black colour was produced. In this reaction, the?","options":["iodide is oxidized","tetraoxosulphate (Vl) acid  acts as an oxidizing agent","starch has been oxidized","K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> is oxidized"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following will produce the greatest increase in the rate of the chemical reaction represented by the equation Na<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3(aq)<\/sub> + 2HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 2NaCI<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub> + SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + S<sub>(g)<\/sub>?","options":["A decrease in temperature and an increase in the concentration of the reactants","An increase in the temperature and a decrease in the cocentration of the reactants","An increase in temperature and an increase in the concentration of the reactants","A decrease in the temperature and a decrease in the concentration of the reactants"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the followingstatements is TRUE?","options":["The dissolution of NaOH<sub>(s)<\/sub> in water is endothermic","The heat os solution of NaOH<sub>(s)<\/sub> is positive","The NaOH<sub>(s)<\/sub> gains heat from the surroundings","The heat of solution of NaOH<sub>(s)<\/sub> is negative"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which property of a reversible reaction is affected by a catalyst?","options":["Heat content (enthalphy)","Energy of activation","Free energy change","Equilibrium position"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following is used in fire extinguishers?","options":["Carbon (ll) oxide","Carbon (lV) oxide","Sulphur (lV) oxide","Ammonia"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"When H<sub>2<\/sub>S gas is passed into a solution of iron (III) chloride, the colour changes from yellow to green. This is because?","options":["H<sub>(s)<\/sub>S is reduced to S","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are oxidized by H<sub>(s)<\/sub>S","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are oxidized Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are reduced to Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> ions"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Suitable reagents for the laboratory preparation nitrogen are?","options":["sodium dioxonitrate (III) and ammonium chloride","sodium dioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","sodium chloride and ammonium chloride","sodium chloride and ammonium diozonitrate (III)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The thermal decomposition of copper (ll)trioxonitrate (V) yields copper (ll) oxide, oxygen and?","options":["nitrogen  (ll) oxide","nitrogen  (l) oxide","nitrogen  (lV) oxide","nitrogen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Chlorine is produced commmercially by?","options":["electrolysis of dilute hydrochloric acid","electrolysis of brine","neutralization of hydrogen chloride","heating potassium trioxochlorate (V)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Aluminium is extracted commercially from its ore by?","options":["heating aluminium oxide with coke in a furance","the electrolysis of fused aluminium oxide in cryolite","treating cryolite with sodium hydroxide solution under prressure","heating sodium aluminium silicate to a high temperature"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Given the reactions (i) Fe<sub>(s)<\/sub> + X(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 Fe(NO<sub>3<\/sub>) + X<sub>(s)<\/sub>  (ii) H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + XO<sub(s)<\/sub> \u2192 X<sub(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(s)<\/sub>; X is likely to be?","options":["copper","zinc","calcium","lead"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Crude copper can be purified by the electrolysis of CuSO<sub>4(aq)<\/sub> if?","options":["platinum electrodes are used","the crude copper is made the anode of the cell","the crude copper is made the cathode of the cell","crude copper electrodes are used"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Methylethanoate reacts with ammonia to yield?","options":["mettylamine and ethanol","ethylamine and methanol","methanamide and ethanol","ethanamide and methanol"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Alkanoates are formed by the reaction of alkanoic acid with?","options":["Alkyl halides","alkanols","ethers","sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The four classes of hydrocarbons are?","options":["ethane, ethene, ethyne and benzene","alkanes, alkenes, alkynes and aromatics","alkanes, alkenes, alkynes and benzene","methane, ethane , propane and butane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds has the highest boiling point?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>HO","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CHO","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>OCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Detergents have the general formula?","options":["R(CH<sub>2<\/sub>)<sub>n<\/sub>OH","RSO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>Na<sup>+<\/sup>","RSO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>2<\/sub>Na<sup>+<\/sup>","RSO<sub>2<\/sub>H"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"What process would coal undergo to give coal gas, coal tar, ammoniacal liquor and coke?","options":["Steam distillation","Destructive distillation","Liquefaction","Hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The formula of a compound formed in a reaction between a trivalent metal M and a tetravalent non-metal X is~?","options":["MX","M<sub>3<\/sub>X<sub>4<\/sub>","M<sub>4<\/sub>X<sub>3<\/sub>","M<sub>3<\/sub>X<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"2.25g of a sample of an oxide of copper on reduction gave 2.0g of copper. 2.50g of another oxide of copper on reduction also gave 2.0g of copper. These results are in accordance with the law of?","options":["constant composition","conservation of matter","multiple proportions","definite proportions"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"One mole of propane is mixed with five moles of oxygen. The mixture is ignited and the propane burns completely. What is the volume of the products at s.t.p?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(G.M.V = 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup> mol<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["112.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","67.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","44.8 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"An increase in temperature causes an increase in the pressure of a gas because there is an increase in the?","options":["average velocity of the molecules","number of collisions between the molecules","density of the molecules","free mean path between each molecules and other"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The forces holding naphthalene crystals together can be overcome when naphthalene is heated to a temperature of 354K resulting in the crystal to melting. These forces are known as?","options":["coulombic","ionic","covalent","Van der waals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A metallic ion X<sup>2+<\/sup> with an inert gas structure contains 18 electrons. How many protons are there in this ion?","options":["20","18","16","2"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following physical properties decreases across the Periodic Table?","options":["Ionization potenial","Electron affinity","Electronegativity","Atomic radius"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"What are the possible oxidation numbers of an element  if its atomic number is 17?","options":["-1  and 7","-1  and 6","-3 and 5","-2 and 6"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The energy changes accompanying the addition of an electron to a gaseous atom is called?","options":["first ionization energy","second ionization energy","electron affinity","electronegativity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The molar ratio of oxygen to nitrogen in dissolved air is 2:1 whereas the ratio is 4:1 in atmospheric air because?","options":["nitrogen is less soluble than oxygen","oxygen is heavier than nitrogen","nitrogen has a higher partial pressure in air","gases are hydrated in water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"An eruption pollution an environment with gas suspected to be H<sub>2<\/sub>S, a poisonous gas. A residue team should spray the environment with?","options":["water","moist SO<sub>2<\/sub>","acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> and water","water, acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> and oxygen"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"In the experiment above, ammonium chloride crystals deposit on the walls of the tube is as a result of","options":["evaporation","recrystallization","sublimation","fractional precipitation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the gas laws does the above graph illustrate?","options":["Boyle","Charles","Graham","Gay-Lussac"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Use the graph above to answer this question. The mass of a substance, M, liberated at an electrode during electrolysis is proportional to the quantity of electricity, Q passing through the electrolyte. This is represented graphically by.","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The diagram above shows the reaction path of an exothermic reaction. The heat of reaction is represented by","options":["l","ll","lll","lV"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The IUPAC name for","options":["2-methylbutanoic acid","2-methyl-1- hydroxyketone","2-methyl-1-hydroxy aldehyde","2-methylpentanoic acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Carbon (ll) oxide may be collected as shown above because it","options":["is heavier than air","is less dense than air","is insoluble in water","burns in oxygen to form carbon (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The acidic hydrogen in the compound  is the hydrogen attached to carbon number","options":["5","4","3","1"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The reaction between sulphur (IV) oxide and oxygen is represented by the equilibrium reaction 2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub>, \u2206H = -196 kJ. What factor would influence increased production of SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub>?","options":["Addition of a suitable catalyst","Increase in the temperature of the reaction","Decrease in the temperature of the reaction","Decrease in the concentration of SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Magnesium ribbon was allowed to burn inside a given gas P leaving a white solid residue Q. Addition of water to Q liberated a gas which produced dense white fumes with a drop of hydrochloric acid. The gas P was?","options":["nitrogen","chlorine","oxygen","sulphur (IV) oxide"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The best treatment for a student who accidentally poured concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid on his skin in the laboratory is to wash the skin with?","options":["cold water","sodium hydroxide solution","iodine solution","sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) solution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"In which of the following pairs of element is allotropy exhibited by each element?","options":["Phosphorus and hydrogen","Oxygen and chlorine","Sulphur and nitrogen","Oxygen and sulphur"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Which of the following gases can best be used for demonstrating the fountain experiment?<br>\r\ni) Nitrogen (ii) Ammonia (iii) Nitrogen (I) oxide<br>\r\n(iv) Hydrogen chloride.","options":["ii and iii","i and iii","ii and iv","ii only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"When sodium hydroxide is heated with ammonium tetraoxosulphate (IV), the gas given off may be collected by?","options":["bubbling it through concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>2<\/sub>","bubbling it through water and then passing it through calcium oxide","passing it directly through calcium oxide","passing it directly through calcium chloride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Which of the following elements will form oxide which will dissolve both in dilute HNO<sub>3<\/sub> and NaOH solutions to form salts?","options":["Al","Mg","Ag","Mn"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Stainless steel is an alloy of?","options":["Iron, carbon and  silver","iron, carbon and lead","iron, carbon and chromium","iron and carbon only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Alloys are best prepared by?","options":["high temperature weilding of the metals","electrolysis using the major metallic component as cathode","reducing a mixture of the oxies of the elements","cooling a molten mixture of the necessary elements"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Corrosion is exhibited by?","options":["iron only","electropostive metals","metals below hydrogen inthe electrochemical  series","all metals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Inspite of the electronic configuration, 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>2<\/sup>, carbon is tetraavalent because?","options":["the electrons in both 2s and 2p orbitals have equal energy","the electrons in both 2s and 2p orbitals are equivalent","both the 2s and 2p orbitals hybridizes","the six orbitals hybridize to four"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will give a precipitate with an aqueous ammoniacal solution of copper (l) chloride?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub> = CHCH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> \u2261 CCH<sub>3<\/sub>","HC = C-CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CH-CH = CH<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The efficiency of petrol as a fuel in high-compression internal combustion engines  improves with an increase in the amount of?","options":["branched chain alkanes","straight chain alkanes","cycloalkanes","halogenated hydrocarbons"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Ethanol reacts with aqueous sodium mono-oxoio date (l) to give a bright yellow solid with a characteristic smell. The product is?","options":["trichloromethane","triodomethane","iodoethane","ethanal"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The most volatile fraction obtained from fractional distillation of crude petroleum contains?","options":["butane , propane and kerosene","butane , propane and petrol","ethane, methane and benzene","methane, ethane and propane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Local black soap is made by boiling palm oil with liquid extract of ash. The function of the ash is to provide the?","options":["acid","ester of allanoic acid","alkali","alkanol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Synthetic rubber is made by polymerization of?","options":["2 methyl buta - 1, 3 - diene","2 methyl buta - 1, 2 - diene","2 methyl but -1-ene","2 methyl but-2-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Complete oxidation of propan -1- ol gives?","options":["propanal","propan-2-al","propan-1-one","propanoic acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"When water drops are added to calcium carbide in a container and the gas is passed through a jet and lifted, the resultant flame is called an?","options":["oxyethylene flame","oxyhydrocarbon flame","oxyacetylene flame","oxymethane flame"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The greater the different in electronegativity between bonded atoms, the?","options":["lower the polarity of the  bond","higher the polarity of the bond","weaker the bond","higher the possibility of the substance formed being a molecule"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"A stream of air was successively passed through three tubes X, Y and Z containing a concentrated aqueous solution of KOH, red hot copper powder and fused calcium chloride respectively. What was the composition of the gas emanating from tube Z?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> ad ithe inert gases","N<sub>2<\/sub>, CO<sub>2<\/sub> and the inert gases","N<sub>2<\/sub> and the inert gases","water vapour, N<sub>2<\/sub> and the inert gases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"In the purification of town water supply, alum is used principally to?","options":["kill bacteria","control the pH of water","improve the taste of the water","coagulate small pasrticles of mud"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Which of the following water samples will have the highest titre value when titrated for the Ca<sup>2+<\/sup> ions using soap solution?","options":["Permanently hard water after boiling","emporarily hard water after boiling","Rain water stored in a glass jar for two years","Permanent hard water passed through permuitit"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Oil spillage in ponds and creeks can be cleaned up by?","options":["burning off the oil layer","spraying with detergent","dispersal with compressed air","spraying with hot water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The solubility of Na<sub>3<\/sub>AsO<sub>4<\/sub>(H<sub>2<\/sub>O)<sub>12<\/sub> is 38.9g per 100g H<sub>2<\/sub>O. What is the mass percentage of Na<sub>3<\/sub>AsO<sub>4<\/sub> in the saturated solution? <br>\r\n<br>\r\n(As = 75, Na = 23, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["87.27%","38.9%","19.1%","13.7%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"In which of the following are the aqueous solutions of each of the substances correctly arranged in order to decreasing acidity?","options":["Ethanoic acid, milk or magnesia, sodium chloride, hydrochloric acid and sodium hydroxide","Ethanoic acid, hydrochloric acid, milk of magnesia, sodium chloride and sodium chloride and sodium hydroxide","Hydrochloride acid, ethanol acid, sodium chloride, milk of magnesia and sodium hydroxide","Hydrochloride acid, sodium hydroxide sodium chloride, ethanol acid, and milk of magnesia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"If 24.83 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.15 M NaOH is titrated to its end point with 39.45 cm<sup>3<\/sup><br>\r\n of HCl, what is the molarity of the HCl?","options":["0.094 M","0.150 M","0.940 M","1.500 M"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The atomic numbers of two elements X and Y are 12 and 19 respectively. The bond of these two elements is?","options":["ionic","covalent","neutral","co-ordinate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"If d represents the density of a gas and K is a constant, the rate of gaseous diffusion r is related to d by the equation?","options":["r  = k\/\u221ad","r = kd","r =k\/d","r = k \u221ad"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"An isotope has an atomic number of 17 and a mass number of 36. Which of the following gives the correct number of neutrons and protons in an atom of the isotope?","options":["Neutrons 53, Protons 17","Neutrons 17, Protons 36","Neutrons 19, Protons 17","Neutrons 36, Protons 17"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"An element Z, contained 90% of <sup>16<\/sup><sub>8<\/sub>Z and 10% of Z<sup>18<\/sup><sub>18<\/sub> its relative atomic mass is?","options":["16.0","16.2","17.0","17.8"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Use the option above to answer this question. Which is the correct set of results for tests conducted respectively on fresh lime juice and ethanol.","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"The times taken for iodine to be liberated in the reaction between sodium thiosulphate and hydrochloric acid at various temperature are as follows. These results suggest that","options":["for a 10<sup>o<\/sup> rise in temperature, rate of reaction is double","for a 10 <sup>o<\/sup> rise in temperature, rate of reaction is halved","time taken for iodine to appear does not depend on temperature","for a 10 <sup>o<\/sup> rise in temperature rate of reaction is tripled"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Use the option above to answer this question. The structure of benzoic acid is","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1987"},{"question":"Which of the following salts when dissolved in water will NOT give the corresponding pH value?","options":["NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub>, pH < 5","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>, pH > 8","Na<sub>2<\/sub>Cl,pH = 7","NaHCO<sub3<\/sub>, pH < 6"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following is an acidic salt?","options":["NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>Na","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following solutions will conduct the least amount of electricity?","options":["2.00 M aqueous solution of NaOH","0.01 M aqueous solution of NaOH","0.01 M aqueous solution of hexanoic acid","0.01 M aqueous solution of sugar"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"How many coulombs of electricity are passed through a solution in which 6.5 amperes are allowed to run for 1.0 hour?","options":["3.90 x 10<sup>2<\/sup> coulombs","5.50 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> coulombs","6.54 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> coulombs","2.34 x 10<sup>4<\/sup> coulombs"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of these represents a redox reaction?","options":["AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> + NaCl \u2192 AgCAl + NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S + Pb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>) \u2192 PbS + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 CaO + CO<sub>2<\/sub>","Zn + 2HCl \u2192 ZnCl<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1.0 molar NH<sub>4<\/sub>OH solution when neutralized with 20.05cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 molar HCl liberated -102 joules of heat. Calculate the heat of neutralization of NH<sub>4<\/sub>OH?","options":["-51.O KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+57.3 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+57.O KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>","+51.0 KJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"What is the consequences of increasing pressure on the equilibrium reaction ZnO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>   Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(I)<\/sub>?","options":["The equilibrium is driven to the left","The equilibrium is driven to the right","There is no effect","More ZnO is produced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The approximate volume of air containing 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen is?","options":["20 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","25 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","50 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The reaction Mg + H<sub>2<\/sub>O \u2192 MgO + H<sub>2<\/sub> takes place only in the presence of?","options":["excess Mg ribbon","excess cold water","very hot water","steam"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"When steam is passed through red hot carbon, which of the following are produced?","options":["Hydrogen oxygen and carbon (IV)  oxide","Hydrogen and carbon (IV) oxide","Hydrogen and carbon (II) oxide","Hydrogen and trioxocarbonate (IV) acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The exhaust fumes from a garage in a place that uses petrol of high sulphur content are bound to contain?","options":["CO and SO<sub>3<\/sub>","CO and SO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO,SO<sub>2<\/sub> and SO<sub>3<\/sub>","CO and H<sub>2<\/sub>S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Oxygen-demanding waste are considered to be a water pollutant because they?","options":["deplete oxygen which is necessary for the survival of aquatic organism","increase oxygen which is necessary for survival of aquatic organism","increase other gaseous substances which are necessary for the survival of aquatic organisms","deplete other gaseous species which is necessary for the survival of aquatic organisms"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following will react further with oxygen to form higher oxide?","options":["NO and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO and CO<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and NO","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"In the course of an experiment, two gases X and Y were produced. X turned wet lead ethanoate to black and Y bleached  moist litmus paper. What are the element(s) in each of the gases X and Y respectively?","options":["H and S;Cl","H and O;Cl","H and S;C and O","H and Cl;S and O"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following metals does NOT form a stable trioxocarbonate (IV)?","options":["Fe","Al","Zn","Pb","none of the options is correct"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following sulphides is insoluble in dilute HCl?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>S","ZnS","CuS","FeS"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"When chlorine is passed into water and subsequently exposed to sunlight, the gas evolved is?","options":["HCl","HOCl","O<sub>2<\/sub>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"A substance Z reacts with NaOH to give salt and water only. When Z is treated with dilute HCl, a gas is evolved which gives a yellow suspension on passing into concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>. Substance Z is?","options":["NaHS","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S","NaHSO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Ammonia gas is normally dried with?","options":["concentrated sulphuric acid","quicklime","anhydrous calcium chloride","magnesium sulphate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"What are the values of x, y and z respectively in the equation: xCu + yHNO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 xCu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O + zNO?","options":["4: 1: 2","3:8:2","2:8:3","8:3:2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The iron (III) oxide impurity in bauxite can be removed by?","options":["Fractional crystallization in acid solution","dissolution in sodium hydroxide and filtration","extraction with concentrated ammonia  and reprecipitation","electroysis of molten mixture"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following does NOT  contain aluminium as component?","options":["Over-head cables","Duralumin","Container for caustic soda","Container for nitric acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"A white solid suspected to be lead trioxonitrate (V) zinc trioxocarbonate (IV) or calcium trioxocabonate (IV) was heated strongly. Its residue which was yellow when hot and white when cold is?","options":["lead (II) oxide","calcium oxide","zinc oxide","lead nitrate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds would give lilac flame coloration and a white precipitate with acidified barium chloride solution?","options":["KCI","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"How will a metal X, which reacts explosively with air and with dilute acids be best extracted from its ores?","options":["Electrolysis of solution of its salts","Decomposition of its oxides","Displacement from solution by an alkali metal","Electroiysis of fused salt"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT correct test for the named organic compound in each case?","options":["Butanoic acid solution gives effervescence with Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> solution","Glucose when reacted with Na<sub>2<\/sub>CrO<sub>4<\/sub> at 0\u00b0C will show immediate discharge of colour","When but-2-ene is reacted with dilute solution of KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> the purple colour of KMnO is discharged readily even room temperature","When butan-2-ol is boiled with butanoic acid with a drop of concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> a sweet smelling liquid is produced"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following is used as an 'anti-knock' in automobile engines?","options":["Tetramethyl silane","Lead tetra-ethyl","Glycerol","n-heptane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"What reaction takes place when palm-oil is added to potash and foam are observed?","options":["Neutralization","Saponification","Esterification","Salting-out"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"When ethanol is heated with excess concentrated sulphuric acid, the ethanol is?","options":["oxidized to ethene","polymerized to polyethene","dehydrated to ethene","dehydrated to ethyne"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is NOT formed by the action of chlorine on methane?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CI","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>CI","CH<sub>2<\/sub>CI<sub>2<\/sub>","CHCI<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following substance is a mixture?","options":["Granulated sugar","Sea-water","Sodium chloride","Iron fillings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The general formula of an alkyl halide (where X represents the halide) is?","options":["C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub> <sub>2<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub> + <sub>1<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>  +  <sub>2<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>X"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following are made by the process of polymerization?","options":["Nylon and soap","Nylon and artificial rubber","Soap and butane","Margarine and nylon"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Starch can be converted to ethyl  alcohol by?","options":["distillation","fermentation","isomerization","cracking"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The movement of liquid molecules from the surface of the liquid to the gaseous phase above it is known as?","options":["Brownian movement","condensation","evaporation","liquefaction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"What mass of a divalent metal M (atomic mass = 40) would react with excess hydrogen gas measured at S.T.P?","options":["8.0 g","4.0 g","0.8 g","0.4 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"In the solubility curve above, water at 98<sup>o<\/sup>C is saturated with KCL and KCIO <sub>3<\/sub> What is the percentage of KCL impurity in the crystals formed when the solution is cooled to 30 <sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["51.5","45.5","34.5","26.5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of aqueous solution of K<sub>2<\/sub>SO <sub>4<\/sub> in the above cell, which species migrate to the anode?","options":["SO<sup>2-<\/sup>OH  <sup>-<\/sup>","K <sup>+<\/sup> and SO <sub>4<\/sub> <sup>2-<\/sup>","OH and HO","H<sub>3<\/sub>O <sup>+<\/sup> and K"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The tabulated results below were obtained by titration 10.0 cm<sub>3<\/sub> of water with soup. The titration was repeated with the same sample of water after boiling. The ratio of permanent to temporary hardness is","options":["1.5","1.4","4.1","5.1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Use the options above to answer this question. Which is the structural formula for pent-2-enoic acid?","options":["A","B","C","D"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen fluoride gas react with 5cm<sup>3<\/sup> of dinitrogen difluoride gas (N<sup>2<\/sup>F<sub>2<\/sub>) to form 10<sub>3<\/sub> of a single gas. Which of the following is the most likely equation of the reaction?","options":["HF + N<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>2<\/sub>  \\(\\to\\) N<sub>2<\/sub>HF<sub>3<\/sub>","2HF + N<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>2<\/sub>  \\(\\to\\) 2NHF<sub>2<\/sub>","2HF + N<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>2<\/sub>  \\(\\to\\) N<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>3<\/sub>","HF + 2N<sub>2<\/sub>F<sub>2<\/sub>  \\(\\to\\) N<sub>4<\/sub>HF<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The number of atoms of chlorine present in 5.85g of NaCl is [Avogaro's Number = 6.02 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>]","options":["6.02 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>","5.85 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>","6.02 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>","5.85 x 10<sup>24<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"How much of magnesium is required to react with 260cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.5 M HCl? [Mg = 24]","options":["0.3g","1.5g","2.4g","3.0g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"The relationship between the velocity (U) of gas molecules and their relative molecular mass (M) is shown by the equation","options":["U = (kM)\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)","U = (kM)<sup>2<\/sup>","U = \\(\\sqrt{k}{m}\\)","U = (\\(\\frac{k}{m}\\))\\(^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"An element with atomic number twelve is likely to be","options":["electrovalent with a velocity of 1","electrovalent with a valency of 2","covalent with a valency of 2","covalent with valency of 4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"Which of the following groups of physical properties increases from left to right of the periodic table? i. Ionization energy ii. Atomic radius iii. Electronegativity iv. Electro affinity","options":["i and ii","i, ii and iii","iii and iv","i, ii, iii and iv"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"When 50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a saturated solution of sugar (molar mass 342.0g) at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C was evaporated to dryness, 34.2g of dry solid was obtained. The solubility of sugar at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C is","options":["10.0 moles dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","7.0 moles dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.5 moles dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","2.0 moles dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1986"},{"question":"X + Y = Z is an equilibrium reaction. The addition of a catalyst?","options":["increase the amount of Z produced in a given time","increases the rate of change in concentrations of X, Y and Z","increases the rate of disapearance of X and Y","increases the rate of the forward reaction","decreases the amounts of X and Y left after the attainment of equilibrium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"What is the formula of sodium gallate if gallium (Ga)shows an oxidation number of + 3?","options":["NaGaO<sub>3<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>Ga(OH)<sub>3<\/sub>","NaGa(OH)<sub>3<\/sub>","NaGa(OH)<sub>4<\/sub>","NaGaO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"If the ONLY pollutants found in the atmosphere over a city are oxides of nitrogen, suspended lead compounds. carbon monoxide and high levels of methane, the probable source(s) of the pollution must be?","options":["automobile exhaust and biological decomposition","combustion of coal and automobile exhaust","biological decomposition only","combustion of coal, automobile exhaust and biological decomposition","combustion of coal and biological decomposition"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A correct electrochemical series can be obtained from K, Na, Ca, Al, Mg, Zn, Fe, Pb, H, Cu, Hg, Ag, Au by interchanging?","options":["Al and Mg","Zn and Fe","Zn and Pb","Pb and H","Au and Hg"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A certain industrial process is represented by the chemical equation 2A<sub>(g)<\/sub> + B<sub>(g)<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) C<sub>(g)<\/sub> + 3D<sub>(g)<\/sub> \\(\\Delta\\)H = X kJmol<sup>-1<\/sup>. Which of the following conditions will favour the yield of the products?","options":["increase in temperature, decrease in pressure","increase in temperature, increase in pressure","decrease in temperature,increase in pressure","decrease in temperature, decrease in pressure","constant in temperature, increase in pressure"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"2MnO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>4<\/sub> + 10Cl<sup>-<\/sup> + 16H<sup>+<\/sup>  \u2192  2Mn<sup>2+<\/sup> + 5Cl<sub>2<\/sub> + 8H<sub>2<\/sub>O. Which of the substances serves as an oxidizing agent?","options":["Mn<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O","MnO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>4<\/sub>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following metals will displace iron from a solution of iron(ll)tetraoxosulphate(lV)?","options":["Copper","Mercury","Silver","Zinc","Gold"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"In the reaction H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>O \\(\\to\\) H<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + 1\/2O<sub>2(g)<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\n\u0394H = -2436000 KJ, which of the following has no effect on the equilibrium position?","options":["Adding argon to the system","Lowering the temperature","Adding hydrogen to the system","Decreasing the pressure","Increasing the temperature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Complete hydrogenation of ethyne yields?","options":["benzene","methane","ethane","ethene","propane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following is used in the manufacture of bleaching powder?","options":["Sulphur dioxide","Chlorine","Hydrogen tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Hydrogen sulphide","Nitrogen dioxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A man suspected of being drunk is made to pass his breath into acidified potassium dichlormate solution. If his breath carries a significant level of ethanol, the final colour of the solution is?","options":["pink","purple","orange","blue-black","green"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"When pollen grains are suspended in water and viewed through a microscope, they appear to be in a state of constant but erratic motion. This is due to?","options":["convection currents","small changes","small changes in temperature","a chemical reaction between the pollen grain and water","the bombardment of the pollen grains by molecules of water"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The energy change (\u0394H) for the reaction CO(g) + (1)\/(2)O<sub>2(g)<\/sub>  \u2192  is?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(\u0394Hi(CO) = -110.4 kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>) (\u0394Hi(CO<sub>2<\/sub>) = -393 kJ mol<sup>-<\/sup>)","options":["-503.7 kJ","+503.7kJ","-282.9 kJ","+282.9 kJ","+393.3 kJ"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Tetraoxosulphate (IV) ions are finally tested using?","options":["acidified silver nitrate","acidified barium chloride","ime-water","dilute hydrochloric acid","acidified lead nitrate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"An organic compound decolourized acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> solution but failed to react with ammoniacal silver nitrate solution. The organic compound is likely to be?","options":["a carbonxylic acid","an alkane","an alkene","an alkyne","an akanone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Solid sodium hydroxide on exposure to air absorbs a gas and ultimately gives another alkaline substance with the molecular formula?","options":["NaOH.H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NaOH.N<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>O","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is the most abundant in the universe?","options":["Carbon","Air","Water","Oxygen","Hydrogen"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A colourless organic compound X was burnt in excess air to give two colourless and odourless gases, Y and Z, as products. X does not decolorize blue bromine vapour, Y turns lime milky while Z gives a blue colour with copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (IV). <br>\r\nCompound X is?","options":["an alkene","an alkane","an alkyne","tetrachloromethane","dichloromethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A colourless organic compound X was burnt in excess air to give two colourless and odourless gases, Y and Z, as products. X does not decolorize blue bromine vapour, Y turns lime milky while Z gives a blue colour with copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (IV).<br>\r\nY and Z are respectively?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","CO and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds is NOT the correct product formed when the parent metals is heated in air?","options":["Calcium oxide (CaO)","Sodium oxide (Na<sub>2<\/sub>O)","Copper (ll) oxide (CuO)","Tri-iron tetroxide (Fe<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>)","Aluminium oxide (Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The atomic number of an element whose cation, X<sup>2+<\/sup>, has the ground state electronic configuration 1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> is?","options":["16","18","20","22","24"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"When marble is heated to about 1473 K, another white solid is obtained which reacts vigorously with water to give an alkaline solution. The solution contains?","options":["NaOH","KOH","Mg(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","Zn(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Addition of dilute hydrochloride acid to an aqueous solution of a crystalline salt yield a yellow precipitate and a gas which turned dichromate paper green. The crystalline salt was probably?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S","Na<sub>2<\/sub>S<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>.5H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The process involved in the conversion of an oil into margarine is known as?","options":["hydrogenation","condensation","pyrolysis","dehydration","cracking"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"An aqueous solution of an inorganic salt gave white precipitate (i) soluble in excess aqueous NaOH (ii) insoluble in excess aqueous NH<sub>3<\/sub> (iii) with dilute HCl. The cation present in the inorganic salt is?","options":["Na<sub>4<\/sub><sup>+<\/sup>","Ca<sup>++<\/sup>","Zn<sup>++<\/sup>","Al<sup>+++<\/sup>","Pb<sub>++<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following roles does sodium chloride play in soap preparation? It","options":["reacts with glycerol","purifies the soap","accelerates the decomposition of the fat or oil","separates the soap from the glycerol","converts the fatty acid to its sodium salt"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The function of sulphur during vulcanization rubber is to?","options":["act as catalyst for the polymerization of rubber molecules","convert rubber from thermosetting to thermo plastics polymer","from chains which bind rubber molecules together","break down rubber polyer","shorten the chain length of rubber polyer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Figure 1 above shows part of the periodic Table which of the elements belongs to the p-block?","options":["S, T and U","V, W and X","S and T only","P, Q and R","V, W, X and S"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The diagram shown above represents the solubility curves of two salts, X and Y, in water, use this diagram to answer the question. At room temperature (300 K)","options":["Y is twice as soluble as X","X is twice as soluble as Y","X and Y are soluble to the same extent","X is three times as soluble as Y","Y is three times as soluble as X"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The diagram shown above represents the solubility curves of two salts, X and Y, in water, use this diagram to answer the question. If 80 g each of X and Y are taken up in 100 g of water at 353 K we shall have","options":["only 10g of X undissolved","only 16 g of Y undissolved","10 g of X and 16 g of Y undissolved","all X and Y dissolved","all X and Y undissolved"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The diagram shown above represents the solubility curves of two salts, X and Y, in water, use this diagram to answer the question. If the molar mass of X is 36 g, the number of moles of X dissolved at 343 K is","options":["0.2 moles","0.7 moles","1.5 moles","2.0 moles","3.0 moles"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Use the above options to the question. The products formed on hydrolysis of","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The oxidation of","options":["2-butanone","2-butanal","butane","butanoic acid","3-butanal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The I.U.P.A.C name for the compound","options":["2-methyl-3-pentene","4-methyl-2-pentane","2-methyl-2-pentene","4-methylpent-2-ene","2-methyl-3-pentane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Use the following option above to answer this question. Which of the following is the functional group of carboxylic acids?","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Which of the following conduct electricity?","options":["sulfur","graphite","diamond","red phosphorus","yellow phosphorus"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"An organic compound contains 72% carbon, 12% hydrogen and 16% oxygen by mass. The empirical formula of  the compound is","options":["C<sub>8<\/sub>H<sub>22<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>12<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"0.499g 0f CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>.xH<sub>2<\/sub>O when heated to constant weight gave a residue of 0.346g. the value of x is? (Cu = 63.5, S = 32.0, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["0.5","2.0","3.0","4.0","5.0"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"In the experiment, which of the following observations would suggest that a solid sample is a mixture? The","options":["solid can be ground to a fine powder","density of the solid is 2.25gdm<sup>-3<\/sup>","solid begins to melt at 573k but is not completely melted until 648k","solid absorbs moisture from the atmosphere and turns into liquid","solid melts at 300k"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Hydrogen diffuses through a porous plug","options":["at the same rate as oxygen","at a slower rate than oxygen","twice as fast as oxygen","three times as fast as oxygen","four times as fast as oxygen"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Given that the molecular mass of iron is 56 and that of oxygen is 16, how many moles of iron(iii)oxide will be contained in 1kg of the compound?","options":["25.0 moles","12.5 moless","6.25 moles","3.125 moles","0.625 moles"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"3.0g of a mixture of potassium carbonate and potassium chloride were dissolved in a 25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of this solution required required 40.00cm<sub>3<\/sub> of 0.1M HCl for neutralization. What is the percentage by weight of K<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> in the mixture. (K = 39, O = 16, C = 12)","options":["60","72","82","89","92"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Some properties of chemical substances are mentioned below... i. sour taste ii. slippery touch iii. yields alkaline gas with ammonium salt iv. has pH less than 7  v. turns phenolphthalein pink.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhich of the above are NOT typical properties of alkalis?","options":["i, iv and v","iv and v","i and iv","ii and v","ii, iii and iv"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"A certain volume of gas at 298k is heated such that its volume and pressure are now four times the original values. What is the new temperature?","options":["18.6k","100.0k","298.0k","1192.0k","4768.0k"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Hydrogen is not liberated when trioxonitrate(v)acid reacts with zinc because","options":["zinx is not rendered passive by acid","hydrogen produced is oxidized to water","oxides of nitrogen are produced","all nitrates are soluble in water","trioxonitrate(v)acid is a strong acid"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"The boiling point of water, ethanol, toluene and butan-2-ol are 373.0k, 351.3k, 383.6k and 372.5k respectively. Which liquid has the highest vapour pressure at 323.0k?","options":["water","toluene","ethanol","butan-2-ol","none"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"In what respect will two dry samples of nitrogen gas differ from each other if sample 1 is prepared by completely removing CO<sub>2<\/sub> and O<sub>2<\/sub> from air, and sample 2 is prepared by passing purified nitrogen(i)oxide over heated copper? sample 1 is","options":["purer than sample 2","slightly denser than sample 2","in all respects the same as sample 2","colourless but sample 2 has a light brown colour","slightly less reactive than sample 2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Copper sulphate solution is electolysed using platinum electrodes A. current of 0.193 amperes is passed for 2hrs. How many grams of copper are deposited? (cu = 63.5, F = 96500 coulombs)","options":["0.457g","0.500g","0.882g","0.914g","1.00g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1985"},{"question":"Sodium chloride may be obtained from brine by","options":["titration","decantation","distillation","evaporation","sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"20 cm <sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen gas are sparked with 20cm <sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen gas in an endimoeter at 373k (100 <sup>o<\/sup>C) and 1 atmosphere. The resulting mixture is cooled to 298 K (25 <sup>o<\/sup>C) and passed over calcium chloride. The volume of the residual gas is","options":["40 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","20 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","30 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","10cm <sup>3<\/sup>","5cm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"For the reaction NH<sub>4<\/sub>NO<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) N<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O, calculate the volume of nitrogen that would be produced at S. T. P from 320 g of the dioxonitrate(iii)salt. (Relative atomic masses: N = 14, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["2.24 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","2.24 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1. 12<sup>3<\/sup>","1. 12dm <sup>3<\/sup>","4. 48 dm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"A molar solution of caustic soda is prepared by dissolving","options":["40 g NaOH in 100 g of water","40 g NaOH in 1000 g of water","20 g NaOH in 500 of solution","20 g NaOH in 1000 g of solution","2o g NaOH in 80 g of solution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which among the elements 1. Carbon 2. Oxygen 3. Copper 4. Bromine 5. Zinc, will NOT react with either water or steam?","options":["1 and 2","2 and 3","3 and 4","1, 2, and 3","2, 3, and 5"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Naphthalene when heated melts at 354 K (81 <sup>o<\/sup>C). At this temperature the molecules of naphthalene","options":["decompose  into smaller molecules","change their shape","are oxidized by atmospheric oxygen","contract","become mobile as the inter molecular forces are broken"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The ratio of the number of molecules in 2g of hydrogen to that in 16g of oxygen is","options":["2:1","1:1","1:2","1:4","1:8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The balanced equation for the reaction of tetraoxosulphate(VI)acid with aluminium hydroxide to give water and aluminium tetraoxosulphate(VI) is","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + Al(OH)<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + AlSO<sub>4<\/sub >","3H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2Al(OH)<sub>3<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) 6H<sub>2<\/sub>O + Al<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>","3H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2AlH \\(\\to\\) 6H<sub>2<\/sub>O + Al(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>","3H<sub>2<\/sub> SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2Al(OH)<sub>3<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) Al(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + Al(OH)<sub>3<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) H<sub>2<\/sub>O + Al<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following mixtures would result in a solution of pH greater than 7?","options":["25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.05 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> and 25.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.50 M Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.05 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>  and 25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.10 M NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","25.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.11 MH<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> and 25.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> 0. 10 M NaOH","25.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.11 MH<sub>2<\/sub> SO<sub>4<\/sub> and 50.00 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.05 M NaOH","25.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.25 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> and 50.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.20 M NaOH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"In which of the following reactions does hydrogen peroxide act as a reducing agent?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) S + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","PbSO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) PbSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","2I+ 2H<sup>+<\/sup> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) I<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","PbO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>  \\(\\to\\) Pb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\)  H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"For the reaction 2Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> 2I<sup>-<\/sup> \\(\\to\\) 2Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + I<sub>2<\/sub>, which of the following statements is TRUE?","options":["Fe is oxidized to Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> is oxidized to Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>","I<sup>-<\/sup> is oxidized to I<sub>2<\/sub>","I<sup>-<\/sup> is reduced to I<sub>2<\/sub>","I<sup>-<\/sup> is displacing an electron from Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"In dilute solution the heat of the reaction NaOH + HCl = NaCl + H2O is - 57.3kJ. Therefore the heat of the reaction 2NaOH + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O is","options":["+ 28.65 kJ","- 28.65KJ","+ 57.3KJ","- 114.6 KJ","- 229.2 KJ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following methods may be used to prepare trioxonitrate (V) acid (nitric acid) in the laboratory?","options":["Heating ammonia gas with tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","Heating ammonium trioxonitrate (V) with tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","Heating sodium trioxonitrate (V) with tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","Heating potassium trioxonitrate (V) with calcium hydroxide","Heating a mixture of ammonia gas and oxygen."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Lime - water, which is used in the laboratory for the detection of carbon(iv)oxide is an aqueous solution of","options":["Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>","CaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"An element that can exist in two or more different structural forms which possess the same chemical properties is said to exhibit.","options":["polymerism","isotopy","isomorphism","isomerism","allotrophy"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Sulphur","options":["forms two alkaline oxides","is spontaneously flammable","burns with a blue flame","conducts electricity in the molten state","is usually stored in the form of sicks in water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is NOT true of carbon monoxide?","options":["CO is poisonous","CO is readily oxidized at room temperature by air to form CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO may be prepared by reducing CO<sub>2<\/sub> mixed with coke heated to about 1000<sup>o<\/sup>C","CO may be prepared by heating charcoal with a limited amount of O<sub>2<\/sub>","CO is a good reducing agent"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"From the reactions : ZnO + Na<sub>2<\/sub>O \\(\\to\\) NaZnO and ZnO + CO<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) ZnCO<sub>3<\/sub> it may be concluded that zinc oxide is","options":["neutral","basic","acidic","amphoteric","a mixture"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"An example of a neutral oxide is","options":["AL<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO","SO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"3Cl<sub>2<\/sub> + 2NH<sub>3<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) N<sub>2<\/sub> + 6HCl. In the above reaction, ammonia acts as","options":["a reducing agent","an oxidizing agent","an acid","a catalyst","a dry agent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"In the Haber process for the manufacture of ammonia, finely divided iron is used as","options":["an ionizing agent","a reducing agent","a catalyst","a dehydrating agent","an oxidizing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The hybridization of the carbon atom in ethyne is","options":["sp <sup>4<\/sup>","sp <sup>3<\/sup>","sp<sup>2<\/sup>","sp","s"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"An organic compound with a vapour density 56.5 has the following percentage composition:C =53.1% N = 12.4%, O = 28.3%, H = 6.2%. The molecular formula of the compound  is <br>\r\nRelative atomic masses: N = 14, O = 16, C = 12, H = 1 )","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>N","C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>N","(C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>N)<sub>1\/2<\/sub>","C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>N","(C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>7<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>N)<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"When the kerosene fraction from petrol is heated at high temperature, a lower boiling liquid is obtained. This process is known as","options":["polymerization","refining","hydrogenation","cracking"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Alkaline hydrolysis of naturally occurring fats and oils yields","options":["fats and acids","soaps and glycerol","margarine and butter","esters","detergents"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is INCORRECT?","options":["Fractional distillation of crude petroleum will give the folloing hydrocarbon fuels in order of increasing boiling point","Butane < petrol < kerosene of polythene.","Both but-1-ene and but-1-yne will decolorize bromine readily","but-2-ene will react with chlorine to form 2,3-dichlorobutane","calcuim carbide will react with water to form any alkyne"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is NOT correct about all four of the acids: HBr, HNO<sub>3<\/sub>, H <sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>? They","options":["dissolve marble to liberate CO","have a PH less than 7","Turn blue litmus red","neutralize alkalis to form salt","react with magnesium to liberate hydrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"If the cost of electricity required to deposit 1 g of magnesium is N5.00, how much would it cost to deposit 10g of aluminium?","options":["N 10.00","N27.00","N44.44","N66.67","N33.33"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Nitrogen can best be obtained from a mixture over oxygen and nitrogen by passing the mixture over","options":["potassium hydroxide","heated gold","heated magnesium","heated phosphorus","calcium chloride"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Water is said to be 'hard' if it","options":["easily forms ice","has to be warmed before sodium chloride dissolves in it","froms an insoluble scum with soap","contains nitrates","contains sodium ions"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Sodium hydroxide (NaOH) pellets are","options":["deliquescent","hygroscopic","efflorescent","hydrated","fluorescent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Alkanes","options":["are all gases","have the general formula C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub> + <sub>2<\/sub>O","contain only carbon and hydrogen","are usually soluble in water","are usually active compounds"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"If an excess of a liquid hydrocarbon is poured into a jar of chlorine, and the sealed jar is then exposed for several hours to bring sunlight, all the chlorine gas is consumed. The hydrocarbon is said to have undergone","options":["a polymerization reaction","an isomerization reaction","an addition reaction","a substitution reaction","a reduction reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The function of conc. H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> in the esterification of ethanoic acid with ethanol is to","options":["serve as a dehydrating agent","serve as a solvent","act as a catalyst","prevent any side reaction","serve as an oxidizing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"A piece of sea shell, when dropped into a dilute solution of hydrochloric acid, produces a colourless, odourless gas which turns clear limewater milky. The sea shell contains","options":["sodium chloride","ammonium nitrate","calcium carbonate","calcium chloride","magnesium chloride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the following electrodes is used in electrolysis of bauxite (Al<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>) in molten cryolite?","options":["Steel electrodes","Carbon electrodes","Mercury electrodes","Carbon anode and steel cathode","Carbon cathode and stell anode"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"An aqueous solution of a metal salt, M, gives a white precipitate with NaOH which dissolves in excess NaOH. With aqueous ammonia, the solution of M also gives a white precipitate which dissolves in excess ammonia. Therefore cartion in M is","options":["Zn <sup>++<\/sup>","Ca<sup>++<\/sup>","Ai<sup>+++<\/sup>","Pb<sup>++<\/sup>","Cu<sup>++<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"At S. T. P how many litres of hydrogen can be obtained from the reaction of 500 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.5 M H <sub>2<\/sub>SO <sub>4<\/sub> with excess zinc metal?<br>\r\n(Gram molecular volume of H<sub>2<\/sub> = 22. 4 dm <sup>3<\/sup>)","options":["22.4 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","11 . 2 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","6. 5 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","5. 6 dm <sup>3<\/sup>","0. 00 dm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The solubility curves of four substances are shown in the figure above. Which of the four substances would crystallize from a saturated solution cooled from 353K(80<sup>o<\/sup>C)to 323K(50<sup><\/sup>C)?","options":["P and Q","P and R","P and S","R and S","Q and R"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Which of the curves shown in the figure given represents the relationships between the volume(V) and pressure(P) of an ideal gas at constant temperature","options":["1","2","3","4","1 and 3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The diagram above (Fig.3) shows the energy profile for the reaction A + B + = C + D From this diagram, it is clear that the reaction is","options":["spontaneous","isothermal","adiabatic","exothermic","endothermic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The name of the compound above is","options":["acetic acid","propanal","propanol","ethanoic acid","propanoic acid"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"USE THE DIAGRAM ABOVE TO ANSWER THIS QUESTION.<br>\r\nWhich of the following represents a carboxylic acid?","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"Use the diagram above to answer this question <br>\r\nWhich of the following structural formula is NOT isomeric with the others?","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"The I.U.P.A.C name for the compound is","options":["isopropylethene","acetylene","3- methylbutane","2-methylbutane","5-methylpentane"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1984"},{"question":"X is a crystalline salt of sodium solution of X in water turns litmus red and produces a gas which turns lime water milky when added to sodium carbonate. With barium chloride solution, X gives hydrochloric acid. X is","options":["Na <sub>2<\/sub>CO <sub>3<\/sub>","NaHCO <sub>3<\/sub>","NaHSO <sub>4<\/sub>","Na <sub>2<\/sub>SO <sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The alkanol obtained from the production of soap is","options":["ethanol","glycerol","methanol","propanol","glycol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The flame used by welders in cutting metals is","options":["butane gas flame","acetylene flame","kerosene flame","oxy-acetylene flame","oxygen flame"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Consecutive members of an alkane homologous serires differ by","options":["CH","CH<sub>2<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>n<\/sub>","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub><\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"If an element has the electronic configuration 1s <sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup> 2p<sup>3<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p<sup>4<\/sup>, it is","options":["a metal","an alkaline earth metal","an s-block element","a p-Block element","a transition element"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Some copper (ll) sulphate pentahydrate (CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> 5H<sub>2<\/sub>O), was heated at 120 <sup>o<\/sup>C with the following results. Wt of crucible = 10.00 g; Wt of crucible + CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> 5H<sub>2<\/sub>O =14.98g; Wt of crucible + residue = 13.54 g. How many molecules of water of  crystalization were lost?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n[H = 1, Cu = 63.5, O = 16, S = 32]","options":["1","2","3","4","5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The three-dimensional shape of methane is","options":["hexagonal","trigonal","linear","tetrahedral","cubical"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"An unknown organic compound X has a relative molecular mass of 180. It is a colourless crystaline solid, readily soluble in water. X contains the elements C, H and O in the atomic ratio 1: 2:1. The compound has a sweet teste and melts on heating. In the presence of yeast and in the absence of air, X is converted to compound Y and a colourless gas. Compound Y reacts with sodium metal to produce a gas Z which gives a 'pop' sound with a glowing splint. Y also reacts with ethanoic acid to give a sweet smelling compound W.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nCompound W is","options":["a soap","an oil","an alkane","an ester","sucrose"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"An unknown organic compound X has a relative molecular mass of 180. It is a colourless crystaline solid, readily soluble in water. X contains the elements C, H and O in the atomic ratio 1: 2:1. The compound has a sweet teste and melts on heating. In the presence of yeast and in the absence of air, X is converted to compound Y and a colourless gas. Compound Y reacts with sodium metal to produce a gas Z which gives a 'pop' sound with a glowing splint. Y also reacts with ethanoic acid to give a sweet smelling compound W.<br>\r\n <br>\r\nThe molecular formula of X is","options":["C<sub>12<\/sub>H<sub>22<\/sub>O<sub>11<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O <sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>14<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub>","C<sub>12<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"An unknown organic compound X has a relative molecular mass of 180. It is a colourless crystaline solid, readily soluble in water. X contains the elements C, H and O in the atomic ratio 1: 2:1. The compound has a sweet teste and melts on heating. In the presence of yeast and in the absence of air, X is converted to compound Y and a colourless gas. Compound Y reacts with sodium metal to produce a gas Z which gives a 'pop' sound with a glowing splint. Y also reacts with ethanoic acid to give a sweet smelling compound W.<br>\r\n <br>\r\nReaction of X with yeast forms the basis of the","options":["plastic industry","textile industry","brewing industry","soap industry","dyeing industry"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"A mixture of common salt, ammonium chloride and barium sulphate can best be separated by","options":["addition of water followed by filtration then sublimation","addition of water followed by sublimation then filtration","sublimation followed by addition of water then filtration","fractional distillation","fractional crystallization"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following relationships between the pressure P, the volume V and the temperature T, represents an ideal gas behaviour?","options":["P \\(\\alpha\\) VT","P \\(\\alpha\\) T\/V","PT \\(\\alpha\\)  V","PV \\(\\alpha\\) I\/T","P \\(\\alpha\\)  V\/T"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The colour imparted to a flame by calcuium ion is","options":["green","blue","brick-red","yellow","lilac"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the reaction M + N P;\u2206H = + QKJ. Which of the following would increase the concentration of the product?","options":["Decreaseing the concentration of N","Increasing the concentration of P","Adding a suitable catalyst","Decreasing the temperature","Increasing the temperature"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In which of the following processes is iron being oxidized?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n1 Fe + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> \u2192 FeSO<sub>4<\/sub>  +H<sub>2<\/sub> <br>\r\n<br>\r\n2 FeSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>S \u2192 FeS + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\n3 2FeCI<sub>2<\/sub> + Cl<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 2FeCl<sub>3<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\n4 2FeCl<sub>3<\/sub> + SnCl<sub>2<\/sub> + \u2192 2FeCl<sub>2<\/sub> + SnCl<sub>4<\/sub>","options":["1 only","2 only","3 only","1 and 3","2 and 4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the reaction Fe + Cu<sup>2+<\/sup> \\(\\to\\) Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + Cu,iron displaces copper ions to from copper. This is due to the fact that","options":["irn is in the metallic from while the copper is in the ionic from","the atomic weight of copper is greater than that of iron","copper is greater than iron","copper metal has more electrons than iron metal","iron is higher in the electrochemical series than copper"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub> - C = CH<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\n                                 CH<sub>3<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe correct name of the compound with the above structural formula is","options":["2-methylbut -1-ene","2-methylbut -2-ene","2-methylbutane","2-ethylprop-1 -ene","2-ethylprop-2-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"How many isomeric forms are there for the molecular formula C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>Br<sub>2<\/sub>?","options":["1","2","3","4","5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"A piece of burning sulphur will continue to burn in a gas jar of oxygen to give misty fumes which readily dissolved in water. The resulting liquid is","options":["sulphur (VI) trioxide","tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","trioxosulphate (IV) acid","dioxosulphate (II) acid","hydrogen sulphide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Sodium sulphate decahydrate (Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.10 H<sub>2<\/sub>O) on exposure to air loses all its water of crystallization.<br>\r\nThe process of loss is known as","options":["efflorescence","hygroscopy","deliquescence","effervescence","dehydration"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following happens during the electrolysis of molten sodium chloride?","options":["Sodium ion loses an electron","Chlorine atom gains an electron","Chlorine ion gains an electron","Sodium ion is oxidized","Chloride ion is oxidized"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Crude petroleum pollutant usually seen on some Nigerian creeks and waterways can be dispersed or removed by","options":["heating the affected parts in order to boil off the petroleum","mechanically stirring to dissolve the petroleum in water","pouring organic solvents to dissolve the petroleum","spraying the water with stergents","cooling to freeze out the petroleum"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"An element is electronegative if","options":["it has a tendency to exist in the gaseous from","its ions dissolve readily in water","it has a tendency to lose electrons","it has a tendency to gain electrons","it readily froms covalent bonds"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Solutions X, Y, and Z have PH values 3.0. 5. 0 and 9. 0 respectively. Which of the following statements is correct?","options":["All the solutions are acidic","All the solutions are basic","Y and Z are more acidic than water","Y is more acidic than X","Z is the least acidic"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the reactions<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(I) H<sub>2<\/sub> (g) + 1\/2O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>O(l); \u2206H = -286 KJ<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(II) C(s) + O<sub>2<\/sub>g) \u2192 CO<sub>2<\/sub> (g); \u2206H = -406 KJ the equations imply that","options":["more heat is absorbed in (l)","more heat is absorbed in (ll)","less heat is evolved in (l)","reaction (ll) proceeds faster than (l)","reaction (l) proceeds faster than (ll)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of these metals, Mg, Fe, Pb and Cu will dissolve in dilute HCI?","options":["All the metals","Mg ,Fe and Cu","Mg, Fe and Pb","Mg and Fe only","Mg only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Stainless steel is an alloy of","options":["carbon, iron and lead","carbon, iron and chromium","carbon, iron and copper","carbon, iron and silver","carbon and iron only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which volume of 0.5 M H <sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> will exactly neutralize 20 cm <sup>3<\/sup>  of 0.1 M NaOH solution?","options":["2.0 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","5.0 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","6.8 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","8.3 cm <sup>3<\/sup>","10.4 cm <sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following pair of gases will NOT react further with oxygen at a temperature between 30<sup>o<\/sup>C AND 400<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["SO<sub>2<\/sub> and  NH<sub>3<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>  and H<sub>2<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub>  and SO<sub>3<\/sub>","SO<sub>3<\/sub> and NO","CO and H<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Some metals are extracted from their ores after some preliminary treatments by electrolysis (L), some of both processes (TL). Which set-up in the following for the extraction of ion, copper and aluminium is correct?","options":["lron (L), copper (L) aluminium (T)","lron (T) copper (L) aluminium (T)","lron (TL) copper (TL) aluminium (TL)","Iron  (L)  copper (T) aluminium (T)","lron (T) copper (L), aluminium (TL)"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the preparation of some pure crystals of Cu (NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> starting with CuO, a student gave the following statements as steps he employed.  Which of these shows a flaw in his report ?","options":["some CuO was reacted with excess dilute H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","the solution was concentrated","when the concentrate was cooled, crystals formed were removed by filtration","the crystals were washed with very little cold water","the crystals were then allowed to dry"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following separation processes is most likely to yield high quality ethanol (>95%) from palm wine?","options":["Fractional distillation without a dehydrant","simple distillation with a dehydrant","fractional distillation with a dehydrant","column chromatography","evaporation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Increasing the pressure of a gas","options":["lowers the average kinetic energy of the molecules","decreases the density of the gas","decreases the temperature of the gas","increases the density of the gas","increases the volume of the gas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"2.5 g of a hydrate barium salt gave on heating, 2.13 g of the anhydrous salt. Given that the relative molecular mass of the of the anhydrous salt is 208, the number of molecules of water of crystallization of the barium salt is","options":["10","7","5","2","1"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"3. 06 g of a sample of potassium trioxochlorate (V) (KCIO) was required to make a saturated solution with 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C. The solubility of the salt at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C is [K =39, Cl = 35.5, O = 16]","options":["5.0 moles dm<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0 moles dm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.5 moles dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.0 molesv","0.5 moles dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The cracking process is very important in the petroleum industry because it.","options":["gives purer products","yields more lubricants","yields more engine fuels","yields more asphalt","yields more candle wax"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"A gas that can behave as a reducing agent towards chlorine and as an oxidizing agent toward hydrogen sulphide is","options":["O<sub>2<\/sub>","NO","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following solutions will give a white precipitate with barium chloride solution and a green flame test?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaCI<sub>2<\/sub>","(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The mass of an atom is determined by","options":["its ionization potential","its electrochemical potential","the number of protons and electrons","the number of neutrons and protons","the number of neutrons and electrons"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following is a neutralization reaction?","options":["Addition of sodium chloride solution to potassium chloride solution","Addition of trioxonitrate (V) acid (nitric acid) to distilled water","Addition of trioxonitrate (V) acid (nitric acid) to tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid (sulphuric acid)","Addition of trioxonitrate (V) acid (nitric acid) to potassium trioxonitrate (V) (potassium nitrate) solution","Addition of trioxonitrate (V) acid (nitric acid) to potassium hydroxide solution"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"A jet plane carrying 3,000 kg of ethane burns off all the gas forming water and carbondioxide. if all the carbondioxide is expelled and all the water formed is condensed and kept on board the plane, then the gain in weight is","options":["1,800 kg","900 kg","600 kg","2, 400 kg","1, 200 kg"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Liquid X, reacts with sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) (Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>) to give a gas which turns calcium chloride solution milky X is","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>(aq)","Kl (aq)","an alkali","an acid","a hydrocarbon"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is FALSE?","options":["Copper (ll) ion can be reduced to copper (l) ion by hydrochloric acid and zinc","Sodium metal dissolves in water giving oxygen","Nitrogen is insoluble in water","Carbondioxide is soluble in water","lead has a higher atomic weight than copper"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"When sodium dioxonitrate (lll) (NaNO<sub>2<\/sub>) dissolves in water, \u2206H is positive. The process of dissolution is","options":["exothermic","endothermic","isothermal","isomeric","hygroscopic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"The equilibrium reaction between copper (l) chloride and chlorine at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C and 1 atmosphere is represented by the equation:<br>\r\n2CuCl +Cl<sub>2<\/sub> \u21cc 2 CuCl<sub>2<\/sub> \u2206H = - 166 KJ. Which of the following statements is TRUE for the reaction, pressure remaining constant?","options":["more CuCl  is formed at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C","more CuCl<sub>2<\/sub> is formed at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C","Less CuCl<sub>2<\/sub> is formed at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C","there is no change in the amount of CuCl<sub>2<\/sub> formed at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C and10<sup>o<\/sup>C","more CuCl is consumed at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"zn + 2HCl \u2192 ZnCl<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nThe rate of the above reaction will be greatly increased if","options":["the zinc is in the powered form","a greater volume of the acid is used","a smaller volume of the acid is used","the reaction vessel is immersed in an ice-bath","the zinc is in the form of pellets"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"Zn + H<sub>2<\/sub> SO<sub>4<\/sub> \u2192 ZnSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub><br>\r\n<br>\r\nin the above reaction how much zinc will be left of 1.0 M of H<sub>2<\/sub>SO?<br>\r\n[Zn =65, s = 32, O = 16, H = 1]","options":["1.35g","1.00g","0.70g","0.65g","0.00g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"30 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 M Al (NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub> SOLUTION IS RECTED WITH 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.15M of NaOH solution. Which reactant is in excess, and by now much ?","options":["NaOH solution by 70 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","NaOH solution, by 60 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","NaOH solution by 40 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","Al(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub> solution by  20 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","Al(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub> solution by  10 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the above experiment, the litmus paper will initially","options":["be bleached","turn green","turn red","turn blue","turn black"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"In the experiment above, a current was passed for 10 minutes and 0.63g of copper was found to be deposited on the cathode of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> cells. The weight of silver deposited on the cathode og AgNO<sup>3<\/sup> cell during the same period would be? [Cu = 63, Ag = 108]","options":["0.54g","1.08g","1.62g","2.16g","3.24g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1983"},{"question":"An acid is said to be weak if?","options":["its ions are so completely dissociated that they easily drift apart","the acid is not corrosive","the acid has low specific gravity","its ions move very slowly when in solution","its ions are incompletely dissociated"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct during the electrolysis of a caustic soda solution using platinum electrodes?","options":["Oxygen gas is given off at the cathode","Hydrogen gas is given of at the anode","Sodium metals is deposited at the anode","Sodium metal is deposited at the cathode","AAlkalinity at the cathode increases"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"An amphoteric oxide is an?","options":["amorphous oxide of a metal","amorphous oxide of a non-mental","oxide that is insoluble in water","oxide that behaves both as a base as well as an acid","oxide that loses its oxygen on sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Water is poured over a white solid and a colourless neutral gas is evolved which burns with a sooty flame. The white solid is?","options":["calcium","calcium oxide","calcium carbide","sodium peroxide","sodium sulphate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Cotton is almost pure?","options":["starch","protein","animal fibre","celluose","mineral fibre"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following types of reactions takes place between C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub> and the halogens?","options":["Substitution","Polymerization","Addition","Saponification","Oxidation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The product formed at the the cathode during the electrolysis of sodium chloride solution with carbon electrodes is?","options":["sodium","chlorine","hydrogen","sodium hydroxide","oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Sodium carbonate crystals on exposure to a dry atmosphere change to a white powder. This phenomenon is known as?","options":["deliquescence","hygroscopy","oxidation","efforescence","sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is incorrect?","options":["Calcium reacts with water to form calcium","Magnesium reacts very slowly with water but faster with warm water","Iron will not react with water in the absence of air","Sodium reacts with water","Copper reacts with steam"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"In the reaction NH<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sup>+<\/sup> \u2192 NH<sub>4<\/sub><sup>+<\/sup>, the bond formed results from?","options":["an electron transferred from NH<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sup>+<\/sup>","an electron pair donated by NH<sub>3<\/sub>","an electron pair equally shared","an electron pair donated by H<sup>+<\/sup>","an electron tarnsferred from H<sup>+<\/sup> to NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following CANNOT be obtained by fractional distillation of petroleum?","options":["Ether","Methane","Butane","Ethene","Hydrogen"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"In the reaction N<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O(g) <br>\r\n\u2194  2NO(g) produced i an increase in the total pressure will?","options":["cause less nitrogen to be produced in the equilibrium mixture","cause less nitric oxide to be produced in the equilibrium mixture","cause more nitric oxide to be produced in the equilibrium mixture","cause more oxygen to be produced in the equilibrium mixture","have no effect"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"In the chemical reaction A + B \\(\\to\\) C + D, more of D is formed?","options":["if the concentrated of A is reduced","if the concentrated of B is reduced","if the concentrated of C is reduced","if the concentration of C is increased","if D is continuously removed from the reaction mixture"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"1.00 g of the oxide of metal X (atomic mass = 64) gave 0.80 g of the metal when reduced with hydrogen. <br>\r\nThe formula of the oxide is?","options":["X<sub>2<\/sub>O","XO","XO<sub>2<\/sub>","X<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","X<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"When a solution of silver (l) nitrate is saturated with hydrogen sulphide, a black precipitate forms which is?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S","Ag<sub>2<\/sub>S","PbS","HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","S"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The production of ammonia by the haber process may be represented by the equilibrium equation N<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)  \u2194  2NH<sub>3<\/sub> \u2206H = -22KJ. Therefore the production of ammonia will be favoured by?","options":["only high pressure","only high temperature","a combination of high temperature and low pressure","a combination of low temperature and high pressure","low pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following represents ethyl ethanonate?","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","(CH<sub>3<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>O","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>CH<sub>2<\/sub>COCH<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following equations represents an oxidizing action of sulphur dioxide?","options":["SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2HNO<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2NO<sub>2<\/sub> + heat","2SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + CI<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2HCI","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>S  \u2192  3S + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 3SO<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192 K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + Cr<sub>2<\/sub>(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"If the rate of diffusion of oxygen gas is taken as 1, what will be rated of diffusion of methane whose relative molar mass is 16?","options":["2.0","1.8","1.4","1.0","0.5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"If the temperature of a gas is increased?","options":["the kinetic energy of the emolecules will decrease","the pressure will decrease if the volume is constant","the gas will  occupy a greater volume if the pressure is constant","the mass of the gas will decrease","the pressure and volume will increase"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"When a little brine was added to a metal nitrate a white precipitate was formed which first turned violet and then black on exposure to ai. The metal nitrate is therefore?","options":["sodium nitrate","mercuric nitrate","lithium nitrate","silver nitrate","potassium nitrate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"If atom X with six electrons in its outermost shell combines with atom Y with one electron in its  outermost shell to form an ionic compound, then?","options":["six atoms of X will combine with one of Y","two atoms of X will combine with six of Y","one atom of X will combine with two of Y","two atoms of X will combine with one of Y","one atom of X will combine with six of Y"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The nitrogen gas obtained by burning an excess  of phosphorus in air has a density higher than the  nitrogen from nitrogen compounds because the nitrogen from air is contaminated with?","options":["some unburnt phosporus","P<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>  vapour","some oxygen","rare gases","carbondioxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"When air is passed  through alkaline pyrogallol and then over quicklime, the only gases left are?","options":["nitrogen and carbondoxide","the rare gases","nitrogen and oxygen","nitrogen and the rare gases","nitrogen, carbonioxide  and the rare gases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"9.8g of solid potassium chlorate (KCIO<sub>3<\/sub>) were added to 40 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water and heated to dissolve all the solid. As he solution cooled, crystals of potassium chlorate started forming at 60\u00b0C. The solubility of potassium chlorate at 66\u00b0C is therefore?","options":["24.5 mole per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.2 mole per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","10.0 mole per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","20.0 mole per dm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.0 mole per dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"100 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen is made to react with 50 cm <sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen, and the whole reaction mixture was then passed through anhydrous calcium chloride. What is the volume of gas left?","options":["5 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","25 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","50 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","75 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"A mixture contains 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen, 35cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen, 15cm<sup>3<\/sup> of carbon monoxide and 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of nitrogen at S.T.P. Which of the following gives the mole fraction of hydrogen in this mixture?","options":["0.02","0.16","0.20","0.25","20"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"0.07g of a hydride of carbon occupies 56.0cm<sup>3<\/sup> at S.T.P. when vaporized and contains 14.29% by mass of hydrocarbon is(C = 12, H = 1)","options":["CH<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The pressure on 100 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen gas at 35\u00b0C is 750mm of Hg.What would be the volume of the gas if the pressure is increased to 1000mm of Hg without changing the temperature?","options":["133.3 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","85  cm<sup>3<\/sup>","75  cm<sup>3<\/sup>","65  cm<sup>3<\/sup>","58.3  cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following bonds exist in crystalline ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl)?","options":["Ionic and covalent","Ionic and co-ordinate","Ionic covalent and co-ordinate","Covalent , co-ordinate and metalllic","Ionic, covalent and metallic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"When a pressure cooker is half filled with water, and heated to boiling point, then the pressure inside the cooker will?","options":["decrease, since only a fraction of the water molecules has changed to vapour","remain constant, because the total number of water molecules has not changed","increase, because the water molecules can now reach every part of the sealed tube","decrease,  since water boils under reduced pressure","increase, because the water vapour  molecules now strike the walls of the tube more frequently because of their increased velocity"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"An element X has two isotopes, <sup>20<\/sup><sub>10<\/sub>X and <sup>20<\/sup><sub>10<\/sub>X,<br>\r\npresent in the ratio 1:3. The relative atomic mass of X would be?","options":["20.5","21.0","21.5","22.0","22.5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following is a neutralization reaction? Addition of","options":["nitric acid to hydrochloric acid","nitric acid to sulphuric acid","nitric acid to distilled water","nitric acid to sodium hydroxide","sodium chloride to distilled water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"A current of 10.0A was passed for 1 hour through a solution of copper (ll) sulphate between the copper electrodes.  Which of the following observation would be correct?<br>\r\n(1 Faraday = 96,500 coulobms) (i) 0.186 mole of copper is dissolved from the anode. (ii) 0.372 mole of copper is deposited on the cathode. (iii) the original Cu<sup>2+<\/sup> ion concentration of the solution remains unchanged. (iv) the original Cu<sup>2+<\/sup> ion concentration of the solution decreases.","options":["i and ii","i and iii","i and iv","ii and iii","ii and iv"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"In the preparation of carbon monoxide by heating ethanedioic acid with concentrated sulphuric acid, the concentrated sulphuric acid act as?","options":["an  oxidizing agent","a reducing agent","a dehydrating agent","a reaction medium","a catalyst"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"When copper powder is heated with concentrated sulphuric acid, the gas produced is?","options":["hydrogen  sulphide","sulphur dioxide","sulphur trioxide","hydrogen pentasulphide","sulphur pentoxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Magnesium ribbon was added to each of the following aqueous solution in turn: H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>, AgNO<sub>3<\/sub>,  HNO<sub>3<\/sub>, HCl, NH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCl, NH<sub>3<\/sub>. In which case does the magnesium become covered with a dark precipitate?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","AgNO<sub>3<\/sub>","HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>","HCl"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"How many grams of methylacetylene (propyne) CH<sub>3<\/sub> \u2014 C \u039e CH will completely discharge the colour of 8g of bromine?<br>\r\n(Br = 80, C = 12, H = 1)","options":["0.5","1.0","2.0","3.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"What weight of sodium hydroxide is required to make 500 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.2 M solution?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Na = 23, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["40 g","20 g","10 g","4 g","2 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following combinations of conditions may increase the rate of a chemical reaction?","options":["Decrease in temperature, increase in concentration of the reactants","Increase in temperature, addition of a catalyst, decrease in the surface area of the reactants","Increase in temperature, increase in concentration, addition of a catalyst and increase in the surface area of the reactants","Decrease in temperature concentration and surface area of the reactants","Additionof a catalyst and in the absence of light"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a redox reaction?","options":["2HNO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2HI  \u2192  2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + 2NO + I<sub>2<\/sub>","Zn + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>  \u2192  ZnSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>","Ca(HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192  CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O + CO<sub>2<\/sub>","4FeO + O<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192  2Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","2Na + Cl<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192   2NaCl"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"0.16g of methane when burnt raises the temperature of 100g of water by 40\u00b0C. What is the of combustion of methane when if the heat capacity of water is 4.2 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>\u00b0C<sup>-1<\/sup>?<br><br>\r\n(CH<sub>4<\/sub> = 16)","options":["1,160 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","1,180 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","1,560 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","1,600kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>","1,680 kJ mol<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Which of the following processes NOT lead to a chemical change?","options":["Strirring iron in sulphur (IV) acid","Stirring sodium carbonate in water","Stirring glucose in concentrated sulphur (IV) acid","Mixing sulphur (IV) acid with potassium carbonate","Titrating an acid against base"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"Brass is an alloy containing copper and?","options":["zinc","tin","aluminium","silver","lead"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The number of grammes of potassium hydroxide in 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of one molar solution is?<br>\r\n(K = 39, O = 16, H = 1)","options":["40g","52g","100g","26g","14g"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"60cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen are sparked with 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen at 100\u00b0C and 1 atmosphere. The total volume of the residual gases is?","options":["60 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","40 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","30 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","70 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The solubility curve of a solid X (molecular mass = 160) is as show above 1,000 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a saturated solution of X at 80<sup>o<\/sup>C . The weight of X crystalized out would be","options":["10 g","12 g","14 g","16 g","18 g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"The i.u.p.A.C name for the compound","options":["2-chloro-isopentane","3-chloro-isopentane","2-chloro-2-methylbutane","1-chloro-2,2- dimethylpropane","2-chloro-2-ethylpropane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"1.00g of mixture of calcium carbonate and calcium oxide liberated 0.33g of carbon dioxide on strong heating. The percentage of calcium oxide in the mixture is? (Ca = 40, C = 12, O = 16)","options":["5","15","25","35","50"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1982"},{"question":"An element X has 127 neutrons and 82 electrons. <br>\r\nIts atomic number is?","options":["209","105","45","82"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"When a bottle of Coca-Cola is opened, bubbles of evolve. The gas is?","options":["hydrogen","carbon monoxide","carbon dioxide","sulphur oxide","chlorine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"When glowing splint is inserted into the mouth of a jar containing a gas, the splint is extinguished. The gas gives a white precipitate when passing into barium hydroxide. The gas is?","options":["methane","hydrogen chloride","hydrogen","nitrogen","carbondioxide"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"An example of a strong electrolyte is?","options":["ethyl acetate","ethanol","glucose","sodium formate","formic acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The oxidation number of manganese in KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> is?","options":["+1","+3","+5","+7","+2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Methane is member of the homologous series called?","options":["alkenes","alcohols","esters","alkanes","alkynes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"For iron to rust, there should be present?","options":["oxygen","moisture","carbondioxide","oxygen and moisture","oxygen, moisture and carbondioxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The mass number of an atom is?","options":["the number of electrons in the atom","the number of protons in the nucleus of the atom","the number of neutrons in the nucleus of the atom","the sum of numbers of electrons and protons inthe atom","the sum of numbers of proton and neutrons in the nucleus of the atom"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Sodium and potassium belong to the same group of the Periodic Table. This is because?","options":["both are metals","both are soft and  lighter than water","both form cations by losing electrons","both have identical electronic configuration","both react with water vigorously"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Oxidation is the process of?","options":["gain of electrons","loss of electrons","gain of hydrogen","loss of oxygen","addition of an electropositive element to a substance"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"the number of atoms in one mole of a substance is equal to?","options":["the atomic number","the avogadro number","the gas constant","the number of neutrons","the number of electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is NOT true of electrovalent compounds?","options":["They are solids","They do not vaporized easily","They usually dissolve in water","The elements forming the compounds normally have their valency electrons in a shared state","They conduct electricity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"If concentrated sulphric acid is added to sugar and warmed gently, the sugar changes from white to brown and finally to a black mas of carbon. In this reaction, concentrated sulphuric acid  is acting as ?","options":["a drying agent","an oxidizing agent","a dehydrated agent","a reducing agent","a hydrolysing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"In the reaction<br>\r\nC + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>2<\/sub> + NO<sub>2<\/sub> + NO + H<sub>2<\/sub>O nitric acid is acting as?","options":["a reducing agent","a nitrating agent","an oxidizing agent","a catalytic agent","a neutralizing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The brown coloration in nitric acid prepared in the laboratory can be removed by?","options":["heating the acid","bubbling air through the acid","cooling the acid","adding a decolorizing agent","adding a base"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following processes takes place during electrolysis?","options":["Positive ions are discharged at the anode bby gaining sufficient electrons to become neutral","Negative ions are dicharged at the anode by gaining suficient electrons to become neutral","Positive ions are discharged at the anode by losing sufficient electrons to become neutral","Negative ions are discharge  at the anode by losing sufficient electrons to become neutral","Nothing happens"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"In the preparation of ammonia, which of the following is used as the drying agent?","options":["CaO","CaCI<sub>2<\/sub>","Conc. H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","P<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>","H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following can have an isomer?","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Allotropes are elements having?","options":["different physical but the same chemical properties","different chemical but the same physical properties","the same chemical and physical properties","different atomic structure","the same position in the periodic table"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"A polymerization reaction is one in which?","options":["small molecules form giant molecules","atoms form molecules","giant molecules form small molecules","molecules form volatile compounds","a molecule rearranges  itself"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following is the electronic configuration of sodium? <br>\r\n(Atomic number of Na = 11)","options":["1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>2<\/sup> 3p1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>1<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>1<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 3s<sup>\u00b0<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup> 2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup> 4s<sup>1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"In the reaction of oxygen with hydrogen to produce water, which of the following statements is true?","options":["One atom of hydrogen reacts with two atoms of oxygen to give one molecule of water","Two atoms of hydrogen react with two atoms of oxygen to give two molecules of water","One molecule of oxygen reacts with one molecule of hydrogen to give two molecules of water","One molecule of hydrogen reaccts with two molecules of oxygen to give three molecules of water","One molecule of oxygen reacts with two molecules of hydrogen to give two molecules of water"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub> + 2HCI \u2192 2NaCI + H<sub>2<\/sub>O + CO<sub>2<\/sub>.  Using the above equation, what volume of  carbondioxide, measured at s.t.p is liberated when 53g of sodium carbonate is dissolved in hydrochloric acid?<br>\r\n(1 mole of gas occupies 22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at s.t.p)<br>\r\n(Na = 23, C = 12, O = 16)","options":["44.8 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.2 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","100.1 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup>","22.4 dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"When sodium nitrate dissolves in water, \u2206H is positive. This means that?","options":["the reaction is catalysed","the reaction is complete","the reaction is exothermic","the reaction is endthermic","sodium nitrate is highly soluble in water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"If an organic compound decolorizes bromine water then the compound is?","options":["saturated","supersaturated","unsaturated","a solid","protonated"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"When air is compressed?","options":["its density decreases","it solidifies","its temperature decreases","its temperature increases","its temperature remains unchanged"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Fats and oils are?","options":["addition products of long chain fatty acids and alkali","addition products of long-chain fattyy acids and glycerol","condensation products of long-chain fatty acids and glycerol","condensation products of formaldehyde and glycerol","liquids at  20\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about phosphorus is NOT correct?","options":["Phosphorus is a solid mineral","Phosphorus  is obtained by oxidation reaction of phosphate","Phosphorus exists in two allotropic  forms","Both forms of phosphorus are interconvertible","Yellow phosporus ignites when rubbed on a rough surface"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"28.8 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of nitrogen at 15\u00b0C is cooled to O\u00b0C at constant pressure, the new volume of nitrogen is?","options":["17.4 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","14.7 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","27.3 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","31.7 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"If 48,000 coulombs of electricity are required to discharge 0.5 mole of sodium from a molten sodium chloride mass, then the number of coulombs required to discharge 2 moles of lead from molten lead (ll) chloride is?","options":["48,000","96,000","192,000","384,000","576,000"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The following compounds are given with their corresponding boiling points.<br>\r\nCompound                          Boiling Point <br>\r\n  i.................................14\u00b0C <br>\r\n  ii................................24\u00b0C <br>\r\n  iii................................0\u00b0C <br>\r\n  iv................................120\u00b0C <br>\r\n  V.................................-2\u00b0C  <br>\r\nFrom the above information, indicate which of the following is correct?","options":["All the compounds are gaseous at 20 \u00b0C","One of the compounds is gaseous at 20 \u00b0C","Two of the compounds are gaseous at 20 \u00b0C","Three of the compounds are gaseous at 20 \u00b0C","None of the compounds is gaseous at 20 \u00b0C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The products of the reaction between dilute sulphuric acid and sodium thiosulphate crystals are?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + SO<sub>2<\/sub> + O<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>3<\/sub> + SO<sub>3<\/sub> + O<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + SO<sub>2<\/sub> + S + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + SO<sub>3<\/sub> + S + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + SO<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a true statement of the kinetic Theory of Gases?","options":["The molecules move at random","The size of molecules is negligble as compared with the volume of gas","The molecular collisions are perfectly elastic","Every molecule has the same kinetic energy at a particular temperature","The average kinetic energy is proportional to the absolute temperature of the gas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The electronic configuration of elements X and Y are X = 2, 8, 6;  Y = 2, 8, 7. The bond in the compound formed by X and Y is expected to be?","options":["ionic","covalent","dative covalent","metallic","none of the above"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"5cm<sup>3<\/sup>  of a saturated solution of sodium chloride at 30\u00b0C gave, on careful evaporation, 1.95g of solid salt. The solubility of sodium chloride at 30\u00b0C?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Na = 23, Cl = 35.5)","options":["5.00 mole dm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.67 mole dm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.00 mole dm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.67 mole dm<sup>3<\/sup>","7.00 mole dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"In the extraction of iron, which  of the following reactions does NOT take place in the blast furnace?","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> + C  \u2192  2CO","2Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> + 3C  \u2192  4Fe + 3CO<sub>2<\/sub>","Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> + 3C  \u2192 2Fe + 3CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 CaO + CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CaO + SiO<sub>2<\/sub>  \u2192  CaSiO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Pure sulphuric acid is a liquid of 1:84 density. What volume of it would be required to prepare 250 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 2.0 M solution?<br><br>\r\n<br><br>\r\n(H = 1, S = 32, O = 16)","options":["2.00","2.66","3.00","3.66","4.00"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"What mass of sodium carbonate solution is in 500 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1 molar sodium carbonate solution?<br>\r\n<br>\r\n(Na = 23, C = 12, O = 16)","options":["10.6 g","5.3 g","500 g","10 g","20 g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds and elements would sublime on exposure to the atmosphere?","options":["Ice","Sulphur","Phosphurous","Iodine","Potassium iodie"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"When hydrogen sulphide and sulphur dioxide are each passed in turn into a solution of potassium dichromate?","options":["both gases change the colour of the solution from yellow to colourless","both gases causes sulphur to be deposited","only hydrogen sulphide decolourizes the solution","only sulphur dioxide deposits sulphur","only hydrogen sulphide deposits sulphur"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which one of the following metals is not normally extracted by chemical reduction because of its position in the electrochemical series?","options":["Copper","Iron","Lead","Potassium","Zinc"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"If one mole of aluminium contains 6 x 10<sup>23<\/sup> atoms of aluminium, how many atoms are contained in 0.9g of aluminium?<br>\r\n(Al = 27)","options":["1.0 x 10<sup>21<\/sup>","6.6 x 10<sup>21<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>","1.0 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>","5.4 x 10<sup>23<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"4g each of aluminium foil and aluminium powder were introduced respectively  into flasks P and Q.<br>\r\nFlask P was treated with warm bench sodium hydroxide and all the aluminium dissolved in one hour. Flask Q was treated with cold sodium hydroxide and all the aluminium dissolved in 10 minutes. What was responsible for Q reacting faster than P?","options":["There were more aluminium atoms in Q than P","The heat given off in retarded the reaction","Q generated more pressure than P during the reaction","P generated more pressure than Q","Q has a greater surface area for the reaction than P"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"What happens when the nitrates of potassium, calcium, zinc and copper are separately heated?","options":["All the nitrate will decompose to their respective metals","The nitrates of calcium and potassium will decomposes to their nitrites","Only copper nitrate decomposes to the metal","Only the nitrates of zinc and copper will decompose to their oxides","The nitrates of calcium, zinc and copper decompose to their oxides"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The scale formation in a kinetic used for boiling water is caused by the presence in water of?","options":["calcium sulphate","calcium carbonate","calcium hydrogen carbonate","calcium hydroxide","magnesium sulphate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"An efflorescent compound is a substance that?","options":["absorbs water froom the air without dissolving in it","is capable of giving off coloured luminosity","gives out water to the atmosphere","absorbs water from the air and dissolves in it","gives out its water of crystallization on heating"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The general formula of an alkyl halide (which represent the halide) is?","options":["C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>  -  <sub>2<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>  + <sub>1<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>  +  <sub>2<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>X","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n<\/sub>  -  1"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"The IUPAC name for","options":["1-methlpentane","3-methylbutane","2-methylbutane","1-dimethylpropane","2-methylpentane"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"Which of the following represents a precipitation reaction?","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + NaCl \\(\\to\\) NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub> + HCl","Fe +H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) FeSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>","4HCl + MnO<sub>2<\/sub> \\(\\to\\) MnCl<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + pb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>) \\(\\to\\)  PbSO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2NaNO","CuO +2HCl \\(\\to\\) Cl<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1981"},{"question":"In an attempt to remove sugar from a breaker containing a quantity of sand and sugar, 2 M ammonium chloride solution was accidentally added instead of water. Which of the following method could be used to remove the ammonium chloride from the mixture?","options":["Fractional distillation","crystallization","Filtration followed by evaporation","Evaporation followed by sublimation","Filtration followed by sublimation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The alloy duralumin is used for the building of aeroplanes because it?","options":["asborbs heat readily from sure thereby preventing the inside of the plane from getting cold at high attitudes","reflects sunlight readily, thereby keeping the inside of the plane cool","is extremely durable and possesses reflective ability","is easily the lightest building material","possesses both strenght and lightness"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"A solution X on mixing with AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> solution, gives a white precipitate solution in NH<sub>3<\/sub>. A Solution Y, when added to X, also gives a white precipiate which is soluble on boiling. Solution Y contains?","options":["Ag<sup>+<\/sup>ion","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup>ion","Pb<sup>4+<\/sup>ion","Zn<sup>2+<\/sup>ion","Al<sup>3+<\/sup>ion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of CO is mixed and sparked with 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air containing 21% O<sub>2<\/sub>. If all the volumes measured at S.T.P. the volume of resulting gases would be?","options":["90cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100cm<sup>3<\/sup>","105cm<sup>3<\/sup>","110cm<sup>3<\/sup>","115cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"A sample of an oxide of mercury weighed 1.00g. When this was heated, oxygen was given off, and 1.00g of mercury metal only was left. What is the formula of the oxide?","options":["Hg<sub>2<\/sub>O","HgO<sub>2<\/sub>","HgO<sub>2<\/sub>","HgO","None of the above"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"On heating, under suitable conditions, 1 litres of monoatomic gas,X, combines with 1<sup>1<\/sup>\/<sub>2<\/sub> litres of an oxide, What is the formula of the oxide.","options":["XO<sub>3<\/sub>","X<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","X<sub>3<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>","XO<sub>2<\/sub>","None of the above"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"If 1 litre of 2.2M sulphuric acid is poured into a bucket containing 10 litre of water,and resulting solution mixed thoroughly, the resulting sulpuric acid concentration will be?","options":["2.2 M","1.1 M","O.22 M","0. 11 M","0.20 M"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following reactions is correct as as written?","options":["FeCl<sub>2<\/sub>  + 3NH<sub>4<\/sub>OH \u2192 Fe(OH)<sub>3<\/sub> + 3NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl","Pb<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub> + 4HCl \u2192 PbCl<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","PbNO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>S \u2192 PbS + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","NaOH + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> \u2192  NaHSO<sub>4<\/sub> +H<sub>2<\/sub>O","2NH<sub>4<\/sub>NO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192 N<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Under high pressure, real gases do not obey gas laws because their molecules?","options":["have become more energetic","have become less energetic","have become smaller in size","decompose into atoms","start repelling each other"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"How many grams of hydrogen gas will be liberated when 6g of magnesium ribbon dissolves in 500cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 6M HCl?   <br><br><br>\r\n(Mg=24, H=1, Cl=35.5)","options":["1.2 g","0.7 g","0.5 g","0.3 g","0.12 g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is an exception in the assumptions of the kinetic theory of gases?","options":["Gases are composed of many elastic particles","The particles are of negligible size","The particles are in constant random motion","The particles are of negligible mass","The particles collide with each other"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true?","options":["Metals conduct electricity while non-metals do not","Metals have high density, non-metals have low density","Metals form basic oxides, non-metals form acidic oxides","In the electro chemical series, metals are above hydrogen while non-metals are below hydrogen","Metals lose elections while non-metals gain electron during normal reactions"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The boiling point of water is higher than that of methanol because?","options":["water is oxide while methanol is an alcohol","inter molecular forces in water are stronger than those in methanol","water is an inorganic compound while methanol is organic","water is an ionic compound while methanol is a covalent compound","water is more reactive than methanol"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Chlorine, bromine and iodine resemble each other in that all?","options":["dissolve in alkalis","react violently with hydrogen without  heating","displace each other from solutions of their salts","are gases","are liquids"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Element X has a total of 19 electrons and can react with oxygen to form an oxide. Which of the following statements is NOT true of the oxide of the element?","options":["When exposed to air, it slowy changes to liquid","its solution in water conducts electricity","Its solution in water, on evaporationm gives a white solid","Its solution in water liberates hydroge when in contact with aluminium metal","Its oxide, when stronlgy heated, regenerates the elements  X"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which ONE of the following statements is true?","options":["All alkali metals salts dissolves with dissociation in water","Most ionic substances are easily vaporized","Ionic substances exist only as liquid","Non-ionic substances are good electrolytes","Nitrogen exists in a trivalent state in ammonium salts"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"When ethene gas reacts with chlorine gas to form 1, 2-dichloroethene, the reaction is called?","options":["substitution","addition","polymerization","hydrolysis","reduction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> is mixed 20 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1 M NaOH. The resulting solution is?","options":["acidic with a molarity of 0.50 M H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","acidic with a molarity of 0.25 H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","neutral","alkaline with a molarity of 0.25 M  NaOH","alkaline with a molarity of 0.50 M  NaOH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following is acceptable as the organic product of the reaction of ethanoic acid and ethanol with an acid catalyst?","options":["Ethyl ethanoate","Methyl ethanoate","Ethyl methyl ketone","Butanol","None"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Given the mean atomic mass of chlorine prepared in the laboratory to be 35.5 and assuming that chlorine contains two isotopes of mass number 35 nad 37, what is the percentage composition of the isotope of mass number 35?","options":["20","25","50","75","90"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"When dilute hydrochloric acid is added to iron(ll)sulphide, the gas evolved will?","options":["turn moist red litmus paper blue","turn lime water milky","blacken lead acurate paper","rekindle a glowing splint","burn a sqeakly pop"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"In which of the following is the oxidation state of oxygen different from its value in water?","options":["OH<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup>","O<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following silver halides is readily soluble in ammonium hydroxide?","options":["Agl","AgBr","AgCl","AgF","None of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The chemical reaction which takes place at the anode (positive electrode) in electrolysis is?","options":["oxidation","hydrolysis","dissociation","reduction","disproportionation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following does NOT happen when a zinc rod is introduced into a solution of copper (ll) sulphate?","options":["Electrons flow towards the zinc rod","The zinc rod dissolves","The temperature of the soil changes","The blue colour of the solution gradually disappears","Copper metal is deposited"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Hardening of an oil may be achieved by?","options":["boiling the oil with water","boiling the oil with a catalyst","treating the oil with sodium hydroxide","treating the oil with hydrogen and catalyst","distilling oil under reduced pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Hardening of an oil may achieved by?","options":["boiling the oil with water","boiling the oil with a catalyst","treating the oil with sodium hydroxide","treating the oil with hydrogen and catalyst","distilling oil under reduced pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"A cold aqueous solution of sodium chloride is electrolyzed using a graphite anode and an iron cathode. In the course of the electrolysis the electrolyte is continuously stirred. The liquid left after electrolysis will therefore consist of?","options":["sodium hydroxide solution","chlorine water","pure water","sodium hypochlorite solution","hydrochloric acid solution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The best way of collecting chlorine is?","options":["by downward displacement of air","by upward displacement of air","over water","under water","over mercury"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Cellulose and starches can be classified as one of the following?","options":["sugars","sucrose","hydrocarbons","carbohydrates","isomers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"If one of the following oxides is heated with hydrogen or carbon using a bunsen burner, it is not reduced to the metal. Which one is it?","options":["Lead oxide","Magnesium oxide","Copper oxide","Tin oxide","Iron oxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is false?","options":["Acids react with some metals, liberating hydrogen","Acids react with carbonates, liberating carbondioxide","Acids conduct electricity and are decomposed by the current, liberating hydrogen at the anode","Acids have a sour taste","Acids change the colour of indicators"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"A mixture of ethanol, sodium dichromate, and water is allowed to drop gradually into a boiling solution containing one part concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<br>\r\n<sub>4<\/sub> and the liberate gas is collected by cooling it with ice water to give a liquid. This liquid is?","options":["ethanoic acid","acetaldehyde","ethyl acetate","methanol","ethylene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"When chlorine gas is passed into a solution of sulphur dioxide?","options":["sulphur dioxide is reduced to sulphur","the chlorine is oxidized to hydrochloric acid","dilute sulphuric  acid and hydrochloric acid are produced","Hydrochloric acid and sulphur are produced","sulphur trioxide is the only product"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"In the above experiment X is","options":["pure nitrogen","a mixture of nitrogen and oxygen","a mixture of nitrogen and carbondioxide","a mixture of oxygen and inert gases","a mixture of nitrogen and inert gases"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The IUPAC name for the compound is","options":["2,3-dimethylpent-2,3-ene","2, 3- dimethylpent-2-ene","3, 4-dimethylpent-3-ene","3,4-dimethylpentene","3,4-dimethlhept-2-ene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will take up the molecules of bromine?","options":["l","ll","lll","l and ll","l and lll"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following is the correct order in the above diagram increasing boiling point, of the isomeric C <sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub> compounds?","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The following graph demonstrates the rate of reaction between calcium carbonate (marble)and dilute hydrochloric acid. The graph shows that the rate of reaction is initially greatest when","options":["the initial slope of the curve is steepest and this occur when small pieces of marble are used and is due to a small surface area of reactant","the occur when large pieces of marble are used and is due to a small surface area of reactant","the initial slope of the curve is steepest and this occurs when small pieces of marble are used and is due to a large surface area of reactant","the initial slope of the curve is steepest and this occur when large surface area of reactant","the initial slope of the curve is least steep and this occur when small pieces of marble are used and is due to the increased surface area of the reactant"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Copper sulphate solution was electrolysed using the apparatus show above. Which of the following changes are observed?","options":["The bulb lights and copper is deposited at both electrodes","the bulb lights and copper is deposited at the anode and disappears from the cathode","the bulb lights and copper is deposited at the cathode and oxygen liberated at the anode","the bulb lights and copper is deposited at the cathode and disappears from the anode","the bulb lights but no additional changes are observed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"The following arrangement of elements in order of decreasing number of outer electrons; One of the elements is wrongly placed. Which is it? ALUMINIUM, CHLORINE, SILICON, MAGNESIUM AND SODIUM.","options":["chlorine","aluminium","silicon","magnesium","sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following tests would confirm-unequivocally that a solution X contain the sulphate ion if it gives with","options":["silver nitrates solution, a white precipates insoluble in dilute HNO<sub>3<\/sub>","barium chloride solution, a white precipitate insoluble in dilute H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","barium chloride solution, a white precipitate insoluble in dilute HCl","barium chloride solution a white precipitate soluble in dilute ammonia","barium chloride solution a white precipitate insoluble in dilute HCl"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"When copper (ii) sulphate solution is treated with excess ammonium hydroxide, a precipitate is first formed, and then this dissolves to give a deep blue solution. This deep blue solution is a","options":["Cu(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","CuSo<sub>4<\/sub>.5H<sub>2<\/sub>O","(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","Cu(NH<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>4<\/sub>(OH)<sub>2<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>.(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.2H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following derivatives of nitrogen affords an aqueous solution having a pH of less that 7?","options":["N<sub>2<\/sub>O","NO","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Detergents are more advantageous than soaps in hard water districts because","options":["on treatment with hard water they either form soluble calcium salts or do not react with calcium ion","on treatment with hard water they form soluble calcium salts","on treatment with hard water they form sodium salts","on treatment with hard water they are converted into soaps","on treatment with hard water they form more lather than soaps does"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"Which of the following classes of organic compounds undergoes rapid oxidation with bromine water?","options":["alcohols","alkenes","carboxylic acids","esters","alkanes"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"An endothermic reaction is one during which heat is.....and can be represented by the symbol.... which of the following combinations can be used accurately to complete the above definition?","options":["liberated, -\\(\\Delta\\)H","liberated, +\\(\\Delta\\)H","absorbed, -\\(\\Delta\\)H","absorbed, +\\(\\Delta\\)H","absorbed, +\\(\\Delta\\)G"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1980"},{"question":"An organic compound X has the following properties: I. It is not miscible with water. ll. lt has boiling point of 77<sup>o<\/sup>C lll. lt has a sweet odour lV. lt is insoluble in sodium hydrogen carbonate solution . V lt  does not decolourize bromine water X is therefore","options":["methane","ethanoic acid","ethene","ethyl ethanoate","carbon tetrachloride"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which are the correct IUPAC names for H-CO<sub>2<\/sub>CH<sub>3<\/sub> and CH = CH","options":["Methyl methanoate and ethene","Metanoic acid and ethyne","Ethyl methanoate and ethyne","Methyl methanoate and ethyne","Ethanoic acid and ethene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following substances are all made by the process of polymerization?","options":["Nylon and soap","Ethanoic acid margarine and ethanol","Nylon and artificial rubber","Soap and butane","Margarine and nylon"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The reaction of zinc with copper (ll) ions in aqueous solution can be represented as follows: Cu <sup>2+<\/sup>(aq) +Zn (s) \u2192 Cu(s) + Zn <sup>2+<\/sup>(aq).Which of the following is the most complete description of this reaction?","options":["Cpper (ll) ions are being reduced","Zinc is being oxidized.","Copper (ll) ions and zinc are being reduced","copper (ll) ions and zinc are being  oxidized","copper(ll) ions are being reduced and zinc oxidized"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The oxidation state of manganese in potassium permanganate is","options":["+7","+5","+3","+2","+1"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"When carbondioxide is bubbled into limewater a white precipitate is formed. If the passage of the gas is continued, the precipitate disappears. The reason for this is","options":["calcium carbonate is formed which on reaction dissolves","calcium hydrogen carbonate is precipitated and then dissolves","calcium carbonate is formed which on reaction with further carbondioxide forms solube calcium hydrogen carbonate","concentration of the solution has occurred with the deposition of calcium hydroxide","the solution has become saturated and solid carbondioxide has been deposited"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Methanoic acid mixes with water in all proportions and has about the same boiling point as water which of the following methods would you adopt to obtain pure water from a mixture of stand, water and methanoic acid?","options":["fractional distillation","filtration followed by distillation","neutralization with sodium hydroxide followed by distillation","esterification with ethanol followed by distillation","neutralization with sodium hydroxide followed by filtration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following statements applies during the electroysis of sodium hydroxide sodium hydroxide solution using platinum electrodes?","options":["Na<sup>+<\/sup> ions are discharged at the cathode","Hydrogen ions are discharged at the anode","the concentration of sodium hydroxide decrease at both electrode compartments","the concentration of sodium hydroxide increases at the cathode only","the concentration of sodium hydroxide increases at the anode only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true? When the potassium atom forms its ion","options":["it gains one electron and becomes neutral","its atomic number decreases","it achieves electronic configuration of orgon","it loses one proton","it loses one neutron"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following contains two amphoteric oxides?","options":["sodium oxide, Zinc oxide , Magnesium oxide","Aluminium oxide, Calcium oxide, Zinc oxide","Potassium oxide, Lithium oxide, Carbon monoxide","Silver oxide, Lead oxide, Sodium oxide","Sulphur dioxide, Aluminium oxide, Carbon monoxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Helium atoms are chemically unreactive because","options":["there are no electrons around the nucleus","the number of protons equals the number of electrons","there are equal number of protons and neutrons in the nucleus","the outer electron shell is completely filled","the atoms contain only protons"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen are sparked with 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C and I atmosphere . The total volume of the residual gases in","options":["50 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","40 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","30 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","70 cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"How many grams of HBr would exactly be required to react with 2 g of propyne? (C =12, H=1, Br = 80)","options":["4. 1 g","6. 1 g","8. 1g","16.2g"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"When ammonium, potassium and calcium carbonates are each separately heated","options":["none of them will decompose","each of them will decompose to give carbondioxide and the respective oxide","ammonium carbonate and potassium carbonate will not decompose","only ammonium carbonate and the respective oxide","ammonium carbonate will decompose to give carbondioxide, water and ammonia"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"If chlorine gas is bubbled into water and then this yellowish-green coloured solution is exposed to bright sunlight for a while","options":["the solution will give out chlorine gas and hydrogen chloried gas","the solution will produce chlorine gas and oxygen","the solution will give out solution will producing hypochloric acid","the solution is decomposed giving out oxygen, hydrogen and chlorine","the solution will give out oxygen gas leaving behind aqueous hydrochloric acid"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"12 g of solid protassium chlorate (KCIO) were added to 40 g of water and heated to dissolve all the solid. As the solution cools, crystals of potassium chlorate at 66 <sup>o<\/sup>C. The solubility of potassium chlorate at 66 <sup>o<\/sup>C is therefore","options":["66","33","10","20","30"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"In the electrolysis of dilute sulphuric acid using platinum electrodes, the products obtained at the anode and cathode are:<br>\r\nAnode         Cathode","options":["Sulphur            hydrogen","Hydrogen        oxygen","Oxygen         Hydrogen","Hydrogen   sulphate ions","Sulphur       oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The empirical formula of an oxide of nitrogen containing 30.4 per cent of nitrogen is (N=14.0,O=16.0)","options":["N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>2<\/sub>","NO","NO<sub>2<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","N<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"When a piece of charcoal enclosed in a cylinder containing air is ignited","options":["the toatl volume of air is increased","the relative amount of oxygen present is increased","the relative amount of nitrogen present is decreased","the relative amount of carbondioxide present is increased","the ratio of oxygen to nitrogen in the system is increased"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Indicate which of the following statements is not true as we move from left to right along the periodic Table:","options":["atomic number of elements increases","atomic mass of elements increases","electropositive character of elements increases","electronegative character of elements increases","number of electrons in the outermost orbits of element increases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"0.1 Faraday of electricity was passed through a solution of copper (ll) sulphate. The maximum weight of copper deposited on the cathode would be [Cu = 64]","options":["64.0g","32.0g","16.0g","6.4 g","3.2g"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which one of these compounds will NOT give an oxygen gas on heating?","options":["Manganese dioxide","Hydrogen peroxide","Zinc nitrate","Sodium nitrate","Ammonium nitrate"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"In the extraction of aluminum from purified bauxite by electrolysis, cryolite is used because","options":["it makes bauxite a better conductor of electricity","it makes bauxite melt at a lower temperature","it makes aluminium purer","it prevents aluminium from getting oxidized","it protects the carbon electrodes used in the process"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"In the redox reaction 2Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + CI<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 2Fe <sup>3 +<\/sup> + 2Cl","options":["Cl<sub>2<\/sub> is reduced because it has lost electrons","Cl<sub>2<\/sub> is reduced because its oxidation number has decreased","Cl<sub>2<\/sub> is reduced because its molecule is change to two ions","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> is reduced because it has lost electrons","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> is reduced because it has gained electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"An anhydride is","options":["a compound wich has no water of crystallization","an oxide whose solution in water has a PH greater than 7","an oxide whose solution in water has a PH less than 7","an oxide that has hydrogen atoms","an amphoteric oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"In which of the following reactions is sulphur dioxide acting as an oxidizing agent?","options":["SO <sub>2<\/sub> + 2HNO<sub>3<\/sub> \u2192H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + NO<sub>2<\/sub> + Heat","2SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + O<sub>2<\/sub>\u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + CI<sub>2<\/sub>\u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> + 2HCI","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>S \u2192 3S + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","SO<sub>2<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O \u2192 H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Calcium hydroxide and ammonium chloride when heated together will give an important product. This compound may be obtained dry by","options":["dissolving it in water, recrystallizing it and then drying in the oven","passing it through a concentrated aqueous solution of sodium hydroxide","passing it through calcium oxide","passing it through concentrated sulphuric acid","passing it through anhydrous calcium choride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Starch can be converted to ethyl alcohol by","options":["distillation","fermentation","isomerization","cracking","cooking"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The reaction between hydrogen and iodine may be represented by the equation H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)+ I<sub>2<\/sub>(g) \u2192 2HI(g), and is exothermic. Therefore","options":["an increase in temperature favours the forword reaction","an increase in pressure favours the backward reaction","both pressure and temperature muct be increased to favour the forward reaction","a decrease in temperature will favour the forward reaction","a decrease in pressure and an increase in temperature will favour the forward reaction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Weighed salts Y and Z were left exposed in the laboratory overnight. In the morning Y had gained weight, and Z had become liquid. What conclusion could be drawn about the nature of the two salts?","options":["Z is efflorescent","Y and Z are efflorescent","Y and Z are deliquescent","Y and Z are hygroscopic","Y is deliquescent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"In the manufacture of iron in the blast furnace, iron (lll) oxide is mixed with coke and limestone, and different reactions occur in the process. Which of the following statements is true with respect to these reactions?","options":["the coke is a powerful reducing agent and easily converts the iron oxide to iron","the calcuim carbonate reacts with SiO<sub>2<\/sub> an earthly impurity in the ore, to from calcuim silicate","the coke will react with the iron produced to form steel","all the carbondioxide required in the process comes from the decomposition of the calcium carbonate","the calcium carbonate decomposes to give calcium oxide, which then forms calcium silicate with the earthly impurity"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true?","options":["an increase in the temperature of a given mass of gas increases the number of gas molecules","an increase in the temperature of the gas does not affect the kinetic energy","an increase in the pressure of the gas is proportional to the increase in volume","a decrease in the pressure of a gas is proportional to the decrease in volume at constant temperature","a decrease in the pressure of the gas decreases the number of gas molecules present"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"the vapour density of a gas may be defined as","options":["the mass of a unit volume of the gas compared to an equal volume of water vapour","the mass of a unit volume of the gas compared to an equal volume of hydrogen","the mass of a unit volume of the gas compared to an equal volume of oxygen","the mass of a unit volume of the gas minus the vapour pressure of water","two times the relative molecular mass of the gas"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The reaction 3C(s) + 2Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>(s) = 4Fe(s) + 3CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g): \\(\\Delta\\)H =46.0 kJ is","options":["isothermic","adiabatic","isobaric","endothermic","exothermic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The solution of a sample in a tube will be identified  as a chloride if it gives","options":["a white precipitate on addition of AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> and barium chloride solutions","a white precipiate when acidified with HCI, and then AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> solution added","a white precipitate when acidified with dilute HNO<sub>3<\/sub> and then AgNO<sub>3<\/sub> solution added","a white precipitate when acidified with dilute H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> and then barium nitrate solution added","a pungent smell of chlorine gas when dilute HCI and MnO<sub>2<\/sub> are added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Hydrogenation may be effected by","options":["the removal of hydrogen from an alkane in the presence of a catalyst","the addition of hydrogen to an alkane in the presence of a catalyst","the addition of hydrogen to an alkyne","the removal of hydrogen from an alkyne","the addition of hydrogen to an ethyl alcohol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Two metallic ions associated with hard water are","options":["copper and zinc","magnesium and silver","calcium and magnesium","potassium and tin","sodium and lead"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Bronze is an alloy of","options":["copper, zinc and nickel","aluminium and copper","copper and zinc","tin and zinc","tin and copper"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Phosphorus burns in oxygen according to the equation P<sub>4<\/sub> + 50<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 P<sub>4<\/sub>O<sub>10<\/sub>. How many litres of oxygen will be required at S.T.P for complete oxidation of 12.4g of phosphorus? [P = 31,O = 16 and molar volume of a gas at S.T.P = 22.4 litres]","options":["5. 20","11. 20","2. 24","20. 20","6. 20"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"On oxidizing anhydrous iron (ll) oxide, which of the following is produced?","options":["SO<sub>2<\/sub> (g) + FeS (s)","SO<sub>3<\/sub> (g) +FeS(s)","SO<sub>2<\/sub> (g)  + SO<sub>3<\/sub>(g)","SO<sub>2<\/sub> (g) + H<sub>2<\/sub>S (g)","SO<sub>3<\/sub>(g) + H<sub>2<\/sub>S(g)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"One of the following techniques can be used to show that chlorophyll pigment is a mixture of chemical compounds and not a single coloured compound","options":["cystallization","hydrolysis","sublimation","filtration","chromatography"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"A gas occupies 30.0 dm<sup>3<\/sup> at S.T.P. What volume would it occupy at 91<sup>o<\/sup>C and 380 mm Hg?","options":["20. 0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","40.0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","60. 0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","80. 0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","100. 0dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"When excess ethanol is  heated to 145 <sup>o<\/sup>C in the presence of concentrated sulphuric acid, the product is","options":["diethyl ether","ethyne","diethyl sulphate","acetone","ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the following raw materials would be required from the smelting of iron ore in a blast furnace?","options":["CaCO <sub>3<\/sub>","Zn(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>","AICI<sub>3<\/sub>","CaSO<sub>4<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"A piece of metal (M) is dissolved in nitric acid and the resulting solution is treated with a small quantity of sodium hydroxide to produce a white precipitate (B) which redissolves on the addition of excess alkali. The precipitate (B)when ignited in a crucible produces the oxide of the metal(m). The METAL M is","options":["Zn","Cu","Al","Au","Ca"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Pick out the correct statement","options":["Zin heated to redness reacts  with steam to give oxygen and zinc oxide","Zinc heated to redness reacts with steam to give oxygen and hydrogen","Zinc does not react with hot or cold water","Zinc reacts with hot water to form zinc oxide and hydrogen","Zinc reacts very easily with cold water to give zinc oxide and hydrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Consider the following exothermic reaction 2SO<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) = 2SO<sub>3<\/sub> (g) . If the temperature of the reaction is reduced from 800<sub>o<\/sub>C to 500<sub>o<\/sub>C, and no other change takes place, then","options":["the reaction rate increases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub> decreases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub> increases","SO<sub>2<\/sub> gas becomes unreactive","O<sub>2<\/sub> gas becomes unreactive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"The IUPAC name for","options":["2-methylbut-3-ene","2-methylbut-4-ene","3-methylbut-2-ene","3-methylbut-1-ene","3-methylpent-1-ene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Which of the structural formal above is ethanoic acid is","options":["A","B","C","D","E"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1979"},{"question":"Zinc Oxide is a","options":["Basic Oxide","Acidic Oxide","Amphoteric Oxide","Neutral Oxide","Reactive Oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When sodium chloride and metallic sodium are each dissolved in water","options":["both processes are exothermic","both processes are endothermic","the dissolution of metallic sodium is endothermic","the dissolution of metallic sodium is exothermic","the dissolution of sodium chloride is explosive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The periodic classification of elements is an arrangement of the elements in order of their","options":["Atomic Weights","Isotopic Weights","Molecular Weights","Atomic Numbers","Atomic Masses"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"In the reaction between sodium hydroxide and sulphuric acid solutions, what volume of 0.5 molar sodium hydroxide would exactly neutralise 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1.25 molar sulphuric acid?","options":["5cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10cm<sup>3<\/sup>","20cm<sup>3<\/sup>","25cm<sup>3<\/sup>","50cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"A small quantity of solid ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl) was heated gently in a test tube, the solid gradually disappears to produce two gases. Later, a white cloudy deposit was observed on the cooler part of the test tube. The ammonium chloride is said to have undergone","options":["distillation","sublimation","precipitation","evaporation","decomposition"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Elements P, Q, R, S have 6, 11, 15, 17 electrons respectively, therefore,","options":["P will form an electrovalent bond with R","Q will form a covalent bond with S","R will form an electrovalent bond with S","Q will form an electrovalent bond with S","Q will form a covalent bond with R"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"An element X forms the following compounds with chlorine; XCl<sub>4<\/sub>, XCl<sub>3<\/sub>, XCl<sub>2<\/sub>. This illustrates the","options":["law of multiple proportions","law of chemical proportions","law of simple proportions","law of conservation of mass","law of definite proportions"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The oxidation state of chlorine in potassium chlorate is","options":["+1","+2","+3","+5","+7"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When air which contains the gases Oxygen, nitrogen, carbondioxide, water vapour and the rare gases, is passed through alkaline pyrogallol and then over quicklime, the only gases left are;","options":["nitrogen and carbondioxide","the rare gases","nitrogen and oxygen","nitrogen and the rare gases","nitrogen, carbondioxide and the rare gases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When heat is absorbed during a chemical reaction, the reaction is said to be","options":["thermodynamic","exothermic","isothermal","endothermic","thermostatic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When large hydrocarbon molecules are heated at high temperature in the presence of a catalyst to give smaller molecules, the process is known as","options":["disintegration","polymerization","cracking","degradation","distillation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The pH of four solutions W, X, Y, Z are 4, 6, 8, 10 respectively, therefore","options":["none of these solutions is acidic","the pH of Y is made more acidic by addition of distilled water","Z is the most acidic solution","W is the most acidic solution","X is neutral"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When each of the nitrates of Potassium, Magnesium and iron is heated,","options":["all the nitrates decompose to their oxides","the nitrate of magnesium gives the nitrite and oxygen","the nitrates of iron magnesium and iron give the oxides","the nitrate of iron gives the nitrite and oxygen","the nitrate of the magnesium is not decomposed"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following metals cannot replace hydrogen from water or steam?","options":["Sodium","Magnesium","Iron","Calcium","Copper"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"A sample of hard water contains some calcium sulphate and calcium hydrogen carbonate. The total hardness may therefore be removed by","options":["boiling the water","adding excess calcium hydroxide","adding a calculated amount of calcium hydroxide","adding sodium carbonate","adding magnesium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"During the electrolysis of copper II sulphate between platinum electrodes, if litmus solution is added to the anode compartment,","options":["the litmus turns blue but no gas is evolved","the litmus turns blue and oxygen is evolved","the litmus turns blue and hydrogen is evolved","the litmus turns red and oxygen is evolved","the litmus turns red and then becomes colourless"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The reaction between an organic acid and an alcohol in the presence of an acid catalyst is known as;","options":["saponification","dehydration","esterification","hydrolysis","hydration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The IUPAC names of the compounds CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH and CH<sub>2<\/sub>=CH<sub>2<\/sub> are respectively;","options":["acetic acid and ethane","ethanoic acid and ethene","methanoic acid and ethylene","ethanol and ethene","acetic acid and ethylene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"If 30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen diffuses through a porous pot in 7 seconds, how long will it take 60cm<sup>3<\/sup> of chlorine to diffuse through the same pot, if the vapour densities of oxygen and chlorine are 16 and 36 respectively?","options":["9.3 sec","14 sec","21 sec","28 sec","30.3 sec"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Brass and bronze are both metallic alloys. Which of the following constituents is common to both alloys?","options":["Tin","Zinc","Copper","Lead","Aluminium"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following gases may not be dried with concentrated sulphuric acid?","options":["HCl","N<sub>2<\/sub>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following reactions does not take place in the smelting of iron in a blast furnace?","options":["CaCO<sub>3<\/sub><sub>(s)<\/sub> <f_arrow> CaO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + CO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + O<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub> <f_arrow> CO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub>","3FeCO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2OCO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub> <f_arrow> FeO<sub>4<\/sub><sub>(s)<\/sub>","SiO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(s)<\/sub> + CaO<sub>(s)<\/sub> <f_arrow> CaCO<sub>3<\/sub><sub>(s)<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub><sub>(g)<\/sub> + C<sub>(s)<\/sub> <f_arrow> 2CO<sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a member of the homologous series of the paraffins (alkanes)?","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>","C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub>","C<sub>15<\/sub>H<sub>32<\/sub>","C<sub>24<\/sub>H<sub>48<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"When ammonia and hydrogen ion bond together to form ammonium ion, the bond formed is called","options":["ionic bond","electrovalent bond","covalent bond","co-ordinate bond","hydrogen bond"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"An example of an alcohol is","options":["CCl<sub>4<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","CHCl<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The nucleus of an atom contains","options":["protons only","neurons only","protons and electrons","neutrons and electrons","protons and neutrons"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Hypochlorous acid is used as a bleach because","options":["it is a strong acid","it yields chlorine readily in pure water","it is an oxidising agent","it is a weak acid","it is a reducing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The normal boiling point of a liquid is defined as","options":["the temperature at which its vapour pressure equals the atmospheric pressure","the temperature at which bubbles begin to form","the temperature at which the vapour pressure equals 1 temperature","the temperature at which the rate of condensation of vapour equals the rate of vaporisation of the liquid","the temperature at which the space above the liquid is saturated"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following compounds will form a solution if exposed to air?","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>.10H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.10H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The most common type of chemical reaction which alkanes undergo is","options":["substitution","addition","condensation","polymerisation","double decomposition"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Consider the following exothermic reaction<br>\r\n2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub><br>\r\nIf the temperature of the reaction is reduced from 800\u00b0C to 500\u00b0C, an no other change takes place, then","options":["the reaction rate increases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub> decreases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub>  increases","SO<sub>2<\/sub>  gas becomes unreactive","O<sub>3<\/sub>  gas becomes unreactive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"If excess zinc is added to a bluish green solution of copper (II) sulphate, and the excess zinc filtered off after completion of reaction, a colourless solution is obtained because","options":["both zinc and copper are metals","the sulphate radical and the zinc ion are divalent","zinc is more electropositive than copper","both zinc and copper form depositive ions in solution","zinc is a reducing agent"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Three solutions contain carbonate, sulphate and sulphide ions respectively. One test that will identify just ONE of them completely is by addition to each of them of","options":["barium chloride solution","dilute hydrochloric acide","lead nitrate solution","calcium chloride solution","sodium hydroxide solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Two gas cylinders contain ethylene (ethene) and acetylene respectively. One test which can be used to distinguish between them is by","options":["passing each gas through bromine water","passing each gas through dilute potassium permanganate solution","passing each gas through silver nitrate solution","treating each gas catalytically with excess hydrogen gas"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Consider the following equation H<sub>2<\/sub>O + 2Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + Cl<sub>2<\/sub> \u2194 2Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> + 2Cl<sup>-<\/sup> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The only ion which behaves as an oxidising agent is","options":["Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","Cl<sup>-<\/sup>","H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"If hydrogen sulphide gas is passed into a solution of a pure iron chloride, a yellow deposit appears. If the deposit is filtered, a pale green solution is left behind. The pale green solution is","options":["dilute sulphuric acid","dilute hydrochloric acid","unreacted hydrogen sulphide in water","iron (III) chloride","Iron (II) chloride"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following changes is physical?","options":["Adding iron filing to aerated water","Adding sodium metal to water","Cooling a solution of Iron (II) sulphate to obtain the hydrated salt","Cooling water to obtain ice","Burning the domestic gas (Utilgas) for cooking"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"By means of filtration, one component can be obtained pure from an aqueous mixture of sodium chloride and","options":["potassium nitrate","sand","lead nitrate","sugar (glucose)","starch"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"In titration involving sodium hydroxide and dilute hydrochloric acid, where would you place the base?","options":["in the beaker","in the conical flask","in a burette","in the standard flask","in the measuring cylinder"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"A gas jar was inverted over burning yellow phosphorus floating over water in a beaker. After burning, the water level was found to rise in the gas jar. The water level rises because","options":["pressure inside the gas jar is greater than pressure outside it","the air in the gas jar had been used up by burning","oxygen in the gas jar had been used up by burning","nitrogen in the gas jar had been used up by burning","the temperature in the jar had risen considerably"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"You are provided with five gas jars containing SO<sub>2<\/sub>, CO<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>, CO and NO respectively. Select a test from A to E which will identify ANY ONE of the gases completely","options":["pass each gas into lime water","pass each gas into water and test with litmus paper","pass each gas into concentrated sulphuric acid","expose each gas to atmospheric air","expose each gas to fumes of hydrogen chloride"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the following substances would you see as an indicator in the titration of sodium carbonate solution against hydrochloric acid (complete neutralisation)?","options":["Litmus paper","Phenolphthalein","Methyl orange","Universal indicator","None of these"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Which of the five atoms can be described by the following properties: Relative atomic mass is greater than 30 but less than 40, it has odd atomic number and forms a unipositive ion in solution?","options":["T","W","X","Y","Z"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"A solid <b>X<\/b> when heated gives off a brown gas. If <b>X<\/b> is soluble in excess sodium hydroxide solution but insoluble in excess ammonium hydroxide solution, then <b>X<\/b> is","options":["basic lead carbonate","lead (II) nitrate","sodium carbonate","zinc nitrate","sodium nitrate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Consider the solubility curves of three salts <b>X, Y<\/b> and <b>Z<\/b> given in the diagram. If each solution of the salt contains 200 g, and is heated to 100<sup>o<\/sup>C, which solution or solutions will deposit 100 g of the solute when suddenly cooled to 0<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["X only","Y only","Z only","X and Z","Y and Z"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"An experiment test of the Law of conservation of Mass is illustrated in the diagram. In practice, the flask is weighed before and after reaction between solutions X and Y. Which of the following pairs of solutions will be unsuitable for the experiments","options":["X = hydrochloric  acid; Y = silver nitrate","X = barium chloride; Y = dilute sulphuric acid","X = hydrochloric acid; Y = sodium hydroxide","X = hydrochloric acid; Y = lead nitrate","X = hydrochloric acid; Y = sodium carbonate"],"answerIndex":5,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"Five compounds R,T,W,X and Y form the following compounds: a basic hydride R.H, an acidic hydride YH, atmospheric oxide W<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>, XO<sub>2<\/sub>. which of the elements is an alkali","options":["R","T","W","X","Y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1978"},{"question":"The size (diameter) of five elements are in the order R < T < W < X < Y, Y being the largest. If each atom has an electron situated on its circumference, and neglecting other factors, which of the atoms will lose its electron most reluctantly?","options":["R","T","W","X","Y"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1978"}]